Evaluate The View That Social Media Is
Now More Important Than Traditional Forms Of Media In Politics. (30) - Politics Explained Essay Plan
Topic      4. Voting Behaviour and The Media
Structure    Three paragraphs with for/against and an overall judgement within each
This Essay Plan Is Part Of A Package Of Essay Plans Covering The UK Politics Part Of The Politics
"A Level Course For The Edexcel Exam Board, Whilst Also Being Very Useful For The AQA Exam Board. It Can Be Purchased Here    https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/"
Keep In Mind       These are long plans as theyʼre intended to be revised from to cover the key
"content you need to know for the exam. In the exam, you would need to adapt them for the specific question you are asked and you certainly wouldnʼt need to include everything, especially not all of the examples. The judgements are also subjective and you donʼt have to agree with them!"
Introduction
Key Definitions
‘Traditional Mediaʼ is taken to mean 3 key types of media other than social media that have an
"influence on politics in the UK opinion polls, newspapers and TV & the radio."
Paragraph One     Social Media vs Newspapers
For: Social Media Is More Important Than Traditional Forms Of Media
The internet and social media are central to how younger voters consume political information and shape their political views. Parties and MPs focus a great deal on trying to influence the views of voters on social media.
Polling by YouGov prior to the 2024 election found that 43% of Britons use social media as
a source of news and that a majority of those under 50 access the news through social
"media. Facebook is the most significant of these, with 69% of voters using it regularly."
"Social media can therefore be seen as more important than traditional forms of media, as"
voters increasingly consume political information through social media.
Social media can also enable scandals and gaffes to go viral during election campaigns.
"In 2019, significant viral events were Jacob Rees Moggʼs comments on the Grenfell fire"
"which were condemned by many and coverage of a boy with pneumonia who had to sleep on the floor of a hospital. This being said, the Conservatives still comfortably won the election."
"In the 2024 election, news of Rishi Sunak leaving D Day commemorations early spread very"
"quickly on social media, greatly harming the Toriesʼ popularity."
Targeted advertising on social media is highly important to how parties try to reach specific
groups of voters who they believe may switch to support them during election campaigns.
Spending on digital advertising in the 2024 election was higher than in any previous
"election, with Google and Meta ads focused on by the major political parties and over £1M"
spent on the election day alone.
According to WhoTargetsMe Labour spent far more than any other political party. They
"spent over £2M on Google Ads during the campaign and over £1.15M on Meta advertising. By contrast, no other party spent more than £150,000 on Google ads and the Conservative Party spent £650,000 on Meta advertising."
"Labour bought a large number of online advertising spots in the run up to election day,"
"including on the Daily Mailʼs website, despite the paper backing the Tories."
"This kind of targeted advertising to particular, important demographics is impossible with"
traditional forms of media and allows parties to reach voters who traditionally wouldnʼt vote for them and therefore wouldnʼt read newspapers who support them.
Against: Traditional Forms Of Media Are More Important Than Social Media
"On the other hand, the press can be argued to still be more important than social media in"
influencing politics.
"Around 7 million people read newspapers daily in the UK, which is a key source of political"
"information and views, particularly for older voters who are more likely to vote and less likely to use social media."
The general public claimed newspapers had more influence than social media over their
voting choices in 2017; 32% vs 26%.
The fact that the press is important in reaching out to older voters can be seen in the fact
"that Keir Starmer, in an effort to broaden his appeal and reach out to traditionally conservative voters, has actively engaged with right-wing publications."
"In his writings, especially in The Telegraph in December 2023, he took a surprising"
"stance by praising Margaret Thatcher, a figure hated by the majority of the left."
This move was interpreted as an attempt to reposition Labour as a party that
"respects traditional values and conservative economic policies, possibly to win over voters who might have felt alienated by the party's previous leftward tilt under Jeremy   Corbyn."
"As newspapers present a biased view, newspapers can be seen to have a big impact changing"
"peopleʼs opinions and influencing how they vote. The Conservatives won 4 elections from 2010 2019 with the majority support of the press, but lost in 2024 after losing the support of a majority of the press, including the Sun, Financial Times and Sunday Times."
"After the 1992 election, in which their editorial on the day of the election was Neil Kinnock's"
head in a lightbulb with the caption 'If Kinnock wins today will the last person to leave
"Britain please turn out the lights.', the Sun celebrated with the headline 'It's the Sun wot won"
it.'
The Sun has backed the winner in every general election since 1979.
"In 2019, the Tories partly launched their manifesto in the Telegraph newspaper and in 2024,"
the Telegraph published a tactical voting guide to try and stop Starmer winning a landslide majority.
A lot of the political coverage on social media and the internet is dominated by traditional forms
"of media, with journalists using twitter in particular to report political news and many print newspapers having popular online sites."
Judgement
Social media is without doubt becoming increasingly influential in UK politics and is certainly
more important than traditional forms of media for younger voters.
"Overall, however, the press is still more important than social media at present, not only"
"because older people consume most of their political information from newspapers and they are more likely to vote, but also because journalists play a key role in political coverage on social media."
Paragraph Two      TV & Radio vs Social Media
Against: Traditional Forms Of Media Are More Important Than Social Media
"TV can be seen as important in how it projects visual images, helping voters to form an"
"impression of party leaders, including during TV debates which are watched by millions of"
voters.
"For example, a lot of the negative coverage of Corbyn focused on his personality and"
‘scruffyʼ appearance rather than his policies.
"In 2017, Theresa May refusing to take part in a head on head TV debate with Corbyn made"
her look weak in the eyes of voters and contributed to her unpopularity.
"Between elections, TV and radio interviews with key politicians can be highly important in"
holding them to account and shaping the views of voters.
"Newsnight, for example, often exposes government or opposition failures, such as how"
COVID was transmitted to care homes and of antisemitism in the Labour Party under
Jeremy Corbyn.
A series of disastrous local radio interviews were important in exposing the failure of Liz
"Trussʼ economic policies and showing her unpopularity with the public, consequently"
playing a part in her resignation soon after.
A survey in the run up to the 2024 election revealed that 58% of Britons access news through
"television and 42% through radio, compared to 43% through social media and 42% from a newspaperʼs website  or app."
TV can also be important in raising the importance of political issues and influencing policy
"change as a result, as can be seen in the Post Office Horizon scandal, which received"
significant public attention in 2024.
"The scandal, involving wrongful convictions of numerous Post Office operators based on"
"flawed software, had received limited coverage under the surface until it was thrust into the limelight by a compelling ITV documentary and subsequent detailed investigations by BBC's Newsnight."
"This media spotlight escalated public awareness and concern, which in turn pressured"
"politicians to take action. As a result of the programme, the government announced a new and improved compensation scheme for the wrongfully convicted sub-postmasters. This included not only compensations for the financial losses suffered but also for the personal"
distress and reputational damage.
For: Social Media Is More Important Than Traditional Forms Of Media
"Whilst TV and the radio are certainly important, it is arguably social media that allows these traditional forms of media to have a wider impact on politics in the UK."
"Clips from TV and the radio often go viral on social media, allowing them to have a much"
wider reach and impact on the beliefs and views of a greater number of voters.
"In April 2024, Minister of State for Crime, Policing and Fire Chris Philip was embarrassed"
when he appeared to think Congo was a part of Rwanda when defending his governmentʼs policy of deporting asylum seekers to Rwanda.
"This was on Question Time and went viral on social media, showing how the media can"
effectively embarrass the government and hold it to account and the role of social media in amplifying this impact.
"Further, unlike TV and the radio which has to be politically neutral, social media allows voters to"
"put forward their political opinions and try and sway others, therefore potentially having more"
impact.
The impact of TV debates also shouldnʼt be overstated. Most viewers have already made up
their mind and only a small portion of the electorate watch them.
"In 2024, After the head-to-head ITV debate between Sunak and Starmer on 4 June, viewers"
"were split almost exactly 50/50 on whether Sunak or Starmer performed better. It was watched by just 4.8M viewers, 2M less than the equivalent debate in 2019."
Judgement
"Overall, TV and the radio are certainly important, however social media is more important, not"
"only because it doesnʼt have to be political neutral, but also because it increases the reach and impact of TV and the radio, through clips going viral."
Paragraph Three     Opinion Polls vs Social Media
Against: Traditional Forms Of Media Are More Important Than Social Media
Opinion polls can have an important influence on elections by influencing turnout and voting
"behaviour, particularly tactical voting."
Turnout is more likely to be higher if opinion polls indicate that the election will be close.
"In the 2024 election, turnout was just 59.9%, which was likely influenced by the fact"
that is was clear Labour would win a landslide majority.
"This can also be seen in the 2015 election and in Brexit, both of which had relatively"
high turnouts as it wasnʼt clear what the result would be.
"If an election seems decided, people may be convinced they can not turnout or use their"
vote in protest safe in the knowledge that it is unlikely to affect the result.
"There is a strong argument that this is what happened in 2017, contributing to Jeremy"
Corbynʼs increase in support.
Opinion polls can influence tactical voting by giving voters an indication of who is likely to
"win, both nationally and in their area."
"In 2015, the fact that opinion polls looked very close may have convinced many Liberal"
Democrat supporters to switch to voting for the Conservatives to avoid a Labour victory.
Opinion polls can also be seen as important in shaping party policies.
"For example, opinion polls showing significant sections of the UK public being opposed to"
trans rights in 2022 likely played a role in key candidates in the Conservative Party leadership elections being opposed to trans rights.
For: Social Media Is More Important Than Traditional Forms Of Media
"On the other hand, the significance of opinion polls can be overstated. Whilst they are focused"
"on and debated a great deal by those interested in politics, the majority of voters arguably pay"
little attention to opinion polling.
"Further, when opinion polls do reach voters, it is often through social media."
"It must also be noted that opinion polls are often wrong, often due to voters being ‘shy Toriesʼ"
"and failing to disclose they will vote Conservative, which leads to an underestimation of their support."
"In 1992, they failed to predict Major's narrow victory, instead the majority of polls predicted"
"either a narrow labour victory or a hung parliament. The exit poll was even wrong that year, predicting a hung parliament."
"They were wrong again in 2015. They predicted Labour being wiped out by the SNP in 2015,"
but predicted Labour and the Conservatives would both have about 34% of the vote in
"England, in reality the Conservatives had about 36.9% and Labour 30.4%."
"Counterpoint: This being said, in both 2019 and 2024, polling was largely accurate with"
most polls predicting a sizeable Tory majority in 2019 and a Labour landslide in 2024.
Judgement
"Overall, opinion polls do have some impact on election results, but this impact is often"
"overstated as a limited portion of the population pays attention to them, whilst their influence is also dependent on social media. Social media is therefore more important than opinion polls in politics."
Overall Argument
"In conclusion, social media is without doubt becoming increasingly important in UK politics and"
"will soon be more important than traditional forms of media, as social media has a big impact on the voting behaviour and political views of younger voters in particular."
Whilst social media is important in allowing traditional forms of media to reach a wider
"audience, at present traditional forms of media remain more important in UK politics than social media. This is in large part because newspapers and the TV are key to how the majority of older voters, who are more likely to vote, consume political information, whilst journalists also play an important role on social media."
Other Possible Essay Questions To Practice Adapting
This Plan To Answer
Evaluate the view that newspapers are more important than social media in influencing voting
behaviour. 30
Follow Politics Explained For More Help With Your Politics A Level
Website → https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/
Instagram → https://www.instagram.com/polexplained/
YouTube   →   https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCQ1FvoFVL4fGJkx6dup3O-w
Twitter → https://twitter.com/Pol_Explain
