Evaluate The View That The Current
Conservative Party Is A Thatcherite Party. (30) - Politics Explained Essay Plan
Topic      2. Political Parties
Structure    Three paragraphs with for/against and an overall judgement within each
This Essay Plan Is Part Of A Package Of Essay Plans Covering The UK Politics Part Of The Politics
"A Level Course For The Edexcel Exam Board, Whilst Also Being Very Useful For The AQA Exam Board. It Can Be Purchased Here    https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/"
Keep In Mind       These are long plans as theyʼre intended to be revised from to cover the key
"content you need to know for the exam. In the exam, you would need to adapt them for the specific question you are asked and you certainly wouldnʼt need to include everything, especially not all of the examples. The judgements are also subjective and you donʼt have to agree with them!"
Introduction
Key Definitions
"When in charge of the Conservative Party in the 1970s and 1980s, Thatcher transformed the"
"partyʼs policies in almost all areas. She introduced neoliberal economic policies, and embodied"
"strong conviction politics, including in her crusade against trade unions."
Paragraph One     Economic Policy
For: The Conservative Party Is Still Thatcherite
"Perhaps the most important aspect of Thatcherism was in relation to economic policy, in which Thatcher greatly reduced taxes, public spending and the size of the state in an attempt to promote individualism and economic growth."
The top rate of income tax was reduced from 83% when she came to power to 40% in her
last budget. Corporation tax reduced from 52% to 34%.
"In her first few years, spending was cut by £1 billion including cuts in housing, energy,"
"education, employment, industrial subsidies, transport and foreign aid."
Thatcher supported privatisation and the removing the state from the market and
introduced a series of massive privatisations starting in 1981 with British Telecom.
Liz Trussʼ attempted economic reforms in the ‘mini-budgetʼ of September 2022 clearly sought
"to promote a Thatcherite agenda in order to tackle rising inflation, showing how there are key parts of the current Conservative Party that are strongly supportive of Thatchrism."
"Her mini-budget attempted to cut taxes significantly including corporation tax, abolish the"
"top rate of income tax and cut stamp duty, all to be funded by borrowing."
The Conservative Party under Rishi Sunak continued to be very supportive of privatisation and
"relatively low taxation and public spending, particularly in comparison to the high level of taxation prior to when Thatcher came into power."
"In the 2024 Spring Budget, the Conservative government announced a cut to National"
Insurance contributions for employees from 10% to 8% and in their 2024 election
"manifesto, the Conservative Party pledged to reduce it to 6% by April 2027."
"In April 2024, Rishi Sunak delivered a significant speech on welfare policy, focusing"
"particularly on disability benefits, which he said are overly generous and contribute to a ""sicknote"" culture in the UK."
"He said that too much money is being spent on disability benefits, which he sees as"
"unsustainable, especially when compared to other significant budget areas like education or policing."
This is consistent with Thatcherʼs opposition to a large welfare state and major
government spending and these ideas have also been echoed by Kemi Badenoch since becoming leader.
Against: The Conservative Party Isnʼt Still Thatcherite
"On the other hand, the economic policy of the Conservative Party under Rishi Sunak should be"
seen in the context of fixing the damage caused by Liz Trussʼ attempted Thatcherite reforms.
Rishi Sunakʼs government reversed Trussʼ planned tax cuts and pledged to increase some
taxes in order to try and bring down inflation.
"Corporation tax, for example, rose from 19% to 25% in April 2023."
Sunakʼs economic policy was focused on trying to prioritise national finances in the context of
the cost of living crisis by reducing the national debt and seeking to keep down inflation.
"Though her economic programme isnʼt yet clear, Kemi Badenoch also hasnʼt indicated she"
"supports any tax cuts to VAT, income tax or corporation tax since becoming leader in late 2024."
Judgement
"Overall, the economic policies of the Conservative Party remain largely Thatcherite, as they are"
very supportive of privatisation and relatively low taxes and public spending.
"Though Liz Trussʼ proposed tax cuts failed and have since been reversed by Rishi Sunak,"
"signalling a move away from a very ideologically Thatcherite economic policy, Sunakʼs government was still broadly supportive of Thatcherʼs economic approach and Kemi Badenoch is also."
Paragraph Two     Law and Order & The Unions
For: The Conservative Party Is Still Thatcherite
"Thatcherʼs government took a very strong approach to law and order and was generally very tough on crime. Despite cutting the budgets of other departments, she increased funding for the police and armed forces."
"Rishi Sunak took a similarly strong approach to tackling crime, meeting the partyʼs 2019"
"manifesto target of recruiting 20,000 additional police officers and pledging in their 2024 manifesto to recruit 8,000 more."
"In March 2023, Sunak introduced a comprehensive anti-social behaviour action plan aimed"
"at curbing what he described as the “scourge of anti-social behaviour"" in communities across the UK. The plan involves a series of measures designed to deliver swift and visible justice."
"One notable element is the introduction of immediate justice initiatives, where offenders"
are required to engage in community repair work such as cleaning graffiti or picking up litter within 48 hours of their sentencing.
Thatcher also had a very strong policy position in relation to trade unions. She called them the
"‘enemy withinʼ and successfully reduced their powers, by making striking more difficult and using the police against striking workers, often violently."
Sunak also took a very tough approach to striking workers and protests. He introduced the
"Strikes Minimum Service Levels) Act 2023, which requires minimum services levels in key public sectors and therefore limits the power of strikes."
"The Public Order Act  2023  introduced new offences such as ""locking-on"" and"
"interfering with national infrastructure (including the roads around Parliament), which are punishable by imprisonment or unlimited fines."
It was enacted in response to the UK government's concerns over highly disruptive
"protest tactics employed by groups like Extinction Rebellion and Just Stop Oil, but has been criticised for threatening the right to protest in the UK."
Against: The Conservative Party Isnʼt Still Thatcherite
Though the current Conservative government has taken a relatively strong approach to striking
"workers, it has arguably not been as harsh or uncompromising as the policies of Thatcherʼs"
governments.
"For example, the government did negotiate with some striking workers and come to an"
agreement with both teachers and nurses.
Judgement
"Overall, though the current Conservative Partyʼs stance in relation to the unions isnʼt as harsh as that of Thatcherʼs government, the party still takes a relatively strong stance on the unions"
and law and order and should therefore still be considered a Thatcherite party.
Paragraph Three       Foreign Policy & Immigration Policy
For: The Conservative Party Is Still Thatcherite
"Thatcher had a very strong, assertive foreign policy leading to her gaining the reputation of being the ‘iron ladyʼ. She strongly projected Britainʼs interests abroad, including against the USSR and in the Falklands War, and developed a strong relationship with Reagan in the US."
The current Conservative Party also takes a strong approach to foreign policy. Much like
"Starmer and Johnson, Sunak strongly supported Ukraine in the war against Russia."
"In 2024, the UK government committed £2.5 billion (approximately $3.2 billion) in"
"military funding to Ukraine, making the UK one of the largest providers of military aid to Ukraine in Europe, only behind Germany."
"In February 2025, Kemi Badenoch supported the Labour governmentʼs policy of increasing"
"defence spending to 2.5% of GDP by 2027, reflecting a continued commitment to a strong"
foreign policy in part to protect against Russia.
Thatcher was also eurosceptic and sought to protect Britainʼs sovereignty against a growing EU.
This can be seen as similar to the current Conservative Party that is strongly opposed to the
political union of the EU and is pledging to ‘take back controlʼ following Brexit.
Against: The Conservative Party Isnʼt Still Thatcherite
The policies of the current Conservative Party in relation to Brexit are a lot more economically
"reckless and anti-free trade than Thatcher likely wouldʼve supported. Thatcher was eurosceptic in relation to the political union of the EU, but strongly supported the EUʼs promotion of free trade and economic union."
The Conservative Party under Rishi Sunak took a very strong anti-immigration stance. This can
"be seen as different from Thatcherism, which wasnʼt strongly opposed to immigration and recognised its economic benefits."
The Conservative Party finally formalised its Rwanda immigration policy by passing the
Safety of Rwanda  Asylum and Immigration) Act in April 2024. The Act allows for the deportation of asylum seekers who enter the UK illegally to Rwanda for processing of their asylum cases.
It represents a very strong stance against immigration and illegal immigration in
particular and was introduced despite the extremely high cost and strong criticisms from human rights groups that Rwanda wasnʼt a safe country and that the asylum process would ensure fair and humane treatment.
"The cost included an initial payment to Rwanda of £290M and an additional £11,000 per"
"asylum seeker for flights, and nearly £151,000 per person for processing and integration over five years."
This major cost for a policy that has very little economic benefit also seems like
something Thatcher would strongly oppose.
Kemi Badenoch has continued this strong approach to immigration since becoming party
"leader in late 2024. In February 2025, she announced 5 new policies on immigration,"
including that immigrants should only be allowed to apply for British citizenship after 15
years of residence rather than the current 6.
Judgement
"Overall, the current Conservative Party is somewhat Thatcherite when it comes to foreign"
"policy. Though the partyʼs strong stance on the international stage and support for a Western foreign policy is Thatcherite, its economic recklessness in supporting Brexit and strong anti- immigration stance is less Thatcherite."
Overall Argument
"In conclusion, the current Conservative Party is certainly still a Thatcherite Party. Not only can"
"this be seen in economic policy, with the partyʼs strong support for privatisation and low taxes, it is also clear in the strong approach of Sunakʼs government to trade unions, foreign policy and"
law and order.
"Further, as was clear in Liz Trussʼ mini-budget, there are significant parts of the"
Conservative Party that seek to take Thatcherite reforms even further.
Other Possible Essay Questions To Practice Adapting
This Plan To Answer
Evaluate the view that the Conservative Party has abandoned Thatcherism. 30
Evaluate the view that the Conservative Party can be described as a one-nation party. 30
Follow Politics Explained For More Help With Your Politics A Level
Website → https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/
Instagram → https://www.instagram.com/polexplained/
YouTube  →  https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCQ1FvoFVL4fGJkx6dup3O-w
Twitter → https://twitter.com/Pol_Explain
