Evaluate The View That Referendums
Have A Positive Impact On Democracy And Politics In The UK. (30) Politics Explained Essay Plan
Topic       2. Electoral Systems
Structure    Three paragraphs with for/against and an overall judgement within each
This Essay Plan Is Part Of A Package Of Essay Plans Covering The UK Politics Part Of The Politics
"A Level Course For The Edexcel Exam Board, Whilst Also Being Very Useful For The AQA Exam Board. It Can Be Purchased Here    https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/"
Keep In Mind       These are long plans as theyʼre intended to be revised from to cover the key
"content you need to know for the exam. In the exam, you would need to adapt them for the specific question you are asked and you certainly wouldnʼt need to include everything, especially not all of the examples. The judgements are also subjective and you donʼt have to agree with them!"
Introduction
Key Definitions
"A referendum is a popular vote on a particular issue, usually requiring a yes/no vote. It's an"
example of direct democracy within a representative system.
"In the UK, there is no constitutional mechanism requiring them to be held. Instead the Prime"
Minister calls them when they think is right.
"Referendum results also technically donʼt have legal force in the UK, they need to be approved"
"afterwards by parliament, which has legal sovereignty."
Paragraph One
Democracy?
Do Referendums Benefit Representative
"For: It Can Be Argued They Do Because They Involve The People In Politics,"
Including Between Elections
It can be argued that referendums benefit democracy in the UK by directly involving the people
"in decision making on important issues, on which the electorate has the right to be consulted."
The 2014 Scottish Independence Referendum is a good example of this. The independence
of Scotland arguably shouldnʼt be decided by anyone other than the Scottish people themselves.
A referendum allows an important single issue to be isolated and an unambiguous popular
verdict to be given. This is especially important when trust in professional politicians is low and when an issue cuts across party lines so that a real choice canʼt be given in a general election.
"This can be seen in the 2016 Brexit referendum, in which the public disagreed with the"
parliament (in which 75% of MPs supported Remain) and in which the Conservative Party in
particular was split on the issue.
The referendum led to Parliament nonetheless implementing the result and many more pro-
Brexit MPs being elected in the 2017 and 2019 elections.
The holding of referendums between General Elections gives the people an opportunity to have
"their say more frequently, preventing the government from becoming remote and unaccountable. They can be seen as a check on ‘elective dictatorshipsʼ and as complementary to representative democracy and parliamentary politics rather than threatening/undermining it."
It can be argued that referendums are well regulated by the Electoral Commission. This reduces
"the chances that the result will be skewed as a result of unfair influence, because expenditure on both sides is controlled and the wording of the question is subject to review by an independent  body."
"For example, in 2016, the government had originally proposed to ask: ""Should the UK"
"remain a member of the EU?"". However, the Electoral Commission considered it to be insufficiently neutral and insisted the ballot paper should present two options: ""Should the UK remain a member of the EU or leave the EU?""."
Against: It Can Be Argued They Donʼt Because They Challenge Representative
Democracy And The Electorate Can Be Seen As Ill Informed
"On the other hand, it can be argued that the direct democracy of referendums are a challenge to parliamentary sovereignty and representative democracy in the UK."
The UK political system is based on voters electing professional representatives to take
"decisions on their behalf and this was the accepted way of doing things until the 1970s. It can be argued that ordinary people lack the expertise to make decisions on complex issues, which are often presented as simple by referendum questions and campaigns, and can be easily misled by campaigns and political leaders."
"In 2016, the Electoral Commission reported that the arguments used by the leaders of both"
"campaigns included a degree of distortion, and that there should be a greater regulation of"
referendum campaigns to ensure people receive a fair presentation of the arguments.
"For example, the likely future level and negative impact of EU immigration to the UK was"
overstated by the Leave campaign and they falsely claimed that leaving the EU would free
up £350M per week to fund the NHS.
Referendums can also be extremely divisive and have a profound impact on the ordinary
"working of representative democracy in the UK, conflicting with parliamentary sovereignty and creating more problems than they solve."
"This can be seen in the EU referendum, where the vast majority of Parliament supported"
"Remain, whilst the majority of the electorate voted to leave, leading to complications in the passage of Brexit through parliament following the vote, including a second referendum movement supported by many MPs."
Brexit continued to be extremely divisive and defined politics in the 4 years following the
"referendum before the COVID pandemic changed. It led to a significant shift to the right from the Conservative Party and there was difficulty getting a Brexit deal through parliament, which eventually had to be resolved by the 2019 general election."
Judgement
"Overall, referendums do benefit representative democracy, though there should be greater"
"regulation of referendum campaigns. The Brexit campaign certainly was divisive and did challenge representative democracy, however this was because Parliament wasnʼt representative of the population, whilst the distortion of the referendum was unique to Brexit and could be resolved with more effective regulation by the Electoral Commission."
Referendums are important in involving the people in democracy on important constitutional issues on which they have the right to be consulted and they improve representative
democracy in the UK and make it more responsive rather than undermining it.
Paragraph Two     The Reasons Why Referendums Are Held
For: Referendums Are Sometimes Held Due To Public Pressure And To Give
Legitimacy To Key Constitutional Issues
"Referendums are sometimes held due to clear pressure from the public, especially when this public support isnʼt represented by support in parliament. This can be seen as positive as it is democratic and ensures proper representation of the population."
"This can be seen especially in the 2014 Scottish Independence referendum, which was"
called following the growth in popularity of the Scottish National Party in the past decade and polling which indicated significant support for independence among the Scottish population.
"The same could be said of the 2016 Brexit referendum, which reflected growing support for"
"UKIP and leaving the EU among the population, as shown in the 2014 European Parliament election where the Brexit supporting UKIP won 26.6% of the vote and was the largest party."
Referendums are also sometimes called to give legitimacy to key constitutional issues. Since
"Blair came into power, it has become the accepted practice to secure a demonstration of public support before embarking on important, possibly irreversible constitutional changes."
"Referendums give constitutional changes legitimacy and ensure theyʼre unlikely to be reversed,"
even though the UK has an uncodified constitution.
"The devolution referendums in Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland are good examples of"
"this, ensuring the new devolved bodies had legitimacy."
Against: Referendums Are Sometimes Held To Benefit Individual Parties
"On the other hand, the holding of referendums has also been influenced by political party"
"motivations, with Prime Ministers calling them in order to benefit their own party. This can be seen as negative for democracy and politics in the UK as it leads to important constitutional issues being decided in order to benefit individual parties at a specific time, rather than due to democratic pressure."
"This can be seen in the 1975 European Economic Community Referendum, where Harold"
"Wilsonʼs government and party was divided on the issue of Europe. Making a decision himself wouldʼve divided his party further and risked his premiership. As a consequence, handing the decision to the people and committing to unite behind their decision was a convenient way to avoid the party splitting."
"Similar can be said of the 2016 Brexit referendum, which aided Cameronʼs Conservative"
"Party. In the run up to the 2015 election, the rise of UKIP risked the Conservatives losing a lot of votes and therefore threatened the Tories electorally. Pledging to hold an EU Referendum in the 2015 election campaign enabled the Conservatives to maintain the"
support of many important voters and win the 2015 election.
Referendums are also sometimes held to try and pass an important policy for a particular
political party.
This can be said of the 2011 Alternative Vote Referendum which was important to the Liberal
"Democrats, but had little support as shown by the 68% no vote on a 42.2% turnout."
Judgement
"Overall, referendums are sometimes held for reasons that benefit democracy and politics in the"
"UK, but sometimes for narrow party political reasons that donʼt. This doesnʼt mean that referendums shouldnʼt be held anymore, instead there should be a law introduce to regulate when they can be called, for example only for important constitutional issues with support from an e-petition."
Paragraph Three     Turnout And Political Awareness
For: Referendums Can Be Argued To Engage Voters And Increase Political
Awareness
Referendums can be seen as positive for democracy and politics in the UK because they engage voters and increase their political awareness around important constitutional issues. This especially true of the two most important recent referendums.
The Scottish Independence referendum in 2014 has been praised for giving an opportunity
"to air a wide range of issues related to independence, such as the impact on the economy and the future of Trident. There was a very high turnout at 84.6%, including many 16 and 17 years olds who were able to vote."
"Brexit also had a relatively high turnout of 72.2%, which was higher than that of recent"
"general elections. This reflected the fact that many who were disillusioned with the traditional political process voted and felt like they were able to have a say on important issues. The referendum also educated many citizens on the impact of the EU on the British political system, including in relation to questions of sovereignty and trade."
Some local referendums also have relatively high turnouts if voters see the issue as important
"to their lives and their finances. For example, the 2005 Edinburgh Congestions Charge"
Referendum received a 74.4% no vote on a 61.7% turnout.
Against: Referendums Can Be Argued To Not Engage Voters And Lead To
Protest Votes
"Whilst recent referendums had relatively high turnouts, this is certainly not the norm, with many"
"referendums failing to engage voters, leading to the legitimacy of the outcome being questioned, as the result doesnʼt prove broad support/rejection across the population."
This can be seen in the 2011 Alternative Vote Referendum which had a turnout of just 42.2%
despite being a national referendum.
"Perhaps more importantly, it can be seen in some successful referendums, including the"
1997 Welsh Devolution Referendum which had a 50.3% ‘yesʼ vote on just a 50.1% turnout and the 2011 Welsh Further Devolution referendum which had a just 35.6% turnout.
Turnouts are even lower in some local referendums such as the unsuccessful 2012
"Birmingham Directly Elected Mayor Referendum and the successful 2012 Bristol Directly Elected Mayor Referendum, which had just 27.6% and 24.1% turnouts respectively."
"Further, it can be argued that many of those who do turnout and vote during referendums do so"
"not because of the specific constitutional issue at stake, but in order to protest against the political class of the day/a particular party. This can be seen as negative for democracy and politics in the UK, as highly consequential changes can be made because of factors entirely separate to the issue itself."
"This can be seen in the Brexit Referendum, where many who voted for Brexit did so due to a"
feeling of being ‘left behindʼ by the UK political system and channelled this into anti-EU sentiments.
"The rejection of AV in the 2011 Alternative Vote Referendum, for example, can be seen in"
large part as a protest against the Liberal Democrats who had become unpopular since the
"2010 General Election because of their U-turn on a pledge to scrap tuition fees, which had gained them a lot of support in 2010"
Judgement
"Overall, recent referendums show how they can be important in engaging voters and increasing"
"political awareness. The low turnouts in other referendums is arguably due to them being held as a consequence of party motivations rather than due to public pressure, in which case they shouldnʼt be held and they arenʼt positive for UK democracy and politics. In the future, therefore, they should only be held if there is significant public support for doing so, which could be included in an act of parliament."
Overall Argument
"In conclusion, referendums do on balance have a positive impact on democracy and politics in"
"the UK, though there should be a law passed stating that they can only be held when there is sufficient public support to do so (for example through an e-petition/being included in a winning manifesto at an election), to ensure this is the case."
"Referendums can pose problems to representative democracy, but largely only because it isnʼt"
"representative enough, and do play an important role in giving legitimacy to key constitutional issues and actively involving and engaging the people in key political issues."
Other Possible Essay Questions To Practice Adapting
This Plan To Answer
Evaluate the view that referendums have more advantages than disadvantages. 30
Evaluate the view that referendums should be used to determine important political and
constitutional issues. 30
Evaluate the view that increased use of referendums would improve democracy in the UK.  30
Follow Politics Explained For More Help With Your Politics A Level
Website → https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/
Instagram → https://www.instagram.com/polexplained/
YouTube  →  https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCQ1FvoFVL4fGJkx6dup3O-w
Twitter → https://twitter.com/Pol_Explain
