Evaluate The View That The Labour
and Conservative Parties are the Only Parties That Matter In UK Politics. (30) Politics Explained Essay Plan
Topic      2. Political Parties
Structure    Three paragraphs with for/against and an overall judgement within each
This Essay Plan Is Part Of A Package Of Essay Plans Covering The UK Politics Part Of The Politics
"A Level Course For The Edexcel Exam Board, Whilst Also Being Very Useful For The AQA Exam Board. It Can Be Purchased Here    https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/"
Keep In Mind       These are long plans as theyʼre intended to be revised from to cover the key
"content you need to know for the exam. In the exam, you would need to adapt them for the specific question you are asked and you certainly wouldnʼt need to include everything, especially not all of the examples. The judgements are also subjective and you donʼt have to agree with them!"
Introduction
Key Definitions
"Minor parties stand candidates in elections, but have very little chance of winning themselves."
"Some, such as the SNP and Sinn Fein, are nationalist parties which only stand candidates in a part of the UK, whilst others stand across the UK and seek to have a distinct policy message, including Reform UK and the Green Party."
"In this essay plan, the Liberal Democrats are considered as a minor party, though you can"
definitely consider them a major party in other essays. It is best to set out how you are treating them in your introduction.
Paragraph One      Success In Elections
For: Arguments That Minor Parties Donʼt Matter In UK Politics
The First Past The Post voting system greatly reduces the power and relevance of smaller
"parties and benefits the Labour Party and the Conservative Party, one of whom has either been"
in government alone or as the majority partner in a coalition since the end of WWII.
This was the case despite the core vote of the two main parties decreasing from over 80%
"in 1979 to just 57.4% in 2024, which has not been reflected in seats. In 2024, Labour and the Tories won 81.8% of seats."
"In the 2017 and 2019 elections, there was also an increase in the support for the two main"
parties.
"In 2017, Labour and the Conservatives won 82.4% of the vote, whilst in 2019 they won"
75.7% of the vote.
UKIP/Reform are perhaps the most striking example of a smaller party harmed by FPTP.
"In 2015, UKIP won 3.88 million votes but just one seat."
"In 2024, Reform UK was the third largest party in terms of vote share with 14.3% of the"
"vote, but received just 5 seats."
"Not only does FPTP lead to a two-party system despite significant support for minor parties, it"
"also gives the winner a major ‘winnerʼs bonusʼ, where their seats share significantly outstrips their vote share."
"In 2019, the Conservatives won 43% of the vote but 56.2% of the seats."
"In 2024, Labour won just 33.7% of the vote, but 63.2% of the seats."
The FPTP voting system therefore makes it extremely difficult for parties other than Labour or
the Conservatives to succeed and to get the number of seats to play a meaningful role in
Parliament.
Against: Arguments That Minor Parties Do Matter In UK Politics
"In the 2024 election, there was a clear return to a multi-party system in terms of vote share."
Parties other than Labour and the Conservatives won 42% of the vote and also picked up a
significant number of seats.
"Even though they are still greatly underrepresented in terms of seats currently, if their"
"support marginally increases, it could catapult them in terms of seats won, especially for"
"Reform UK, who finished second in 98 seats."
It can be argued that the 2024 election is the FPTP system stretched to its limit maintaining
"a two-party system. If minor partiesʼ support grows any more, it will greatly harm the two main parties in terms of seat share."
"Further, minor parties have also had significant success in terms of seat shares in recent"
"elections, especially where they had significant geographically concentrated support."
"In 2015, the SNP won 56 seats with just 4.7% of the vote, whilst in 2019 they won 48 seats"
with just 3.9% of the vote.
"In 2024, the Lib Dems won a record 72 seats with 12.2% of the vote. The fact that they"
increased their number of MPs by 61 by increasing their share of the vote by 0.6% shows
how vulnerable two-party dominance is.
"Further, even though they have just 5 and 4 MPs respectively, Reform UK and the Green"
Party represent significant threats to the two main parties on both their left and their right.
They won 14.3% of the vote and 6.4% of the vote respectively and arenʼt too far off
becoming major electoral forces.
Minor parties can have a huge influence on elections through the ‘spoiler effectʼ. This is when a
"minor party draws votes away from a major party, potentially causing it to lose an election. This effect can inadvertently benefit another major party by splitting the vote, particularly when the minor party's platform appeals to voters who might otherwise support the more dominant party."
"In the 2024 election, though Reform took votes from both Labour and the Tories, with both"
"partiesʼ support dropping through the campaign, they did much more damage to the Conservative Party in terms of seats."
"By splitting the right wing vote in many Leave voting constituencies, Reform stopped the"
"Conservatives from winning a large number of seats, a lot of which Labour won even if they"
also lost some voters to Reform.
Judgement
"Overall, it is undeniable that in terms of success in elections the Labour and Conservative"
"Parties are very dominant due to the nature of FPTP. However, it would be wrong to say that minor parties donʼt matter. They can have significant influence through the ‘spoiler effectʼ and are potentially close to breaking the two party dominance in terms of seat share, due to the fact that their vote share was over 40% in 2024."
Paragraph Two      Ability To Play A Role In Government
For: Arguments That Minor Parties Donʼt Matter In UK Politics
"Labour or the Conservative Party have always been in government since the end of WWII, either on their own or as a major partner in a coalition."
"In the last two elections, either party has won a significant majority that has enabled them to"
dominate Parliament and easily pass significant legislative changes.
"In the Welsh Parliament, also, the Labour Party has dominated and always been in"
government since devolution.
"Even when in a coalition, the major parties dominate government and policy."
"In the 2010 coalition government, for example, the Conservative Partyʼs austerity policies"
dominated and the Lib Dems werenʼt able to keep their key promise of not raising university tuition fees.
Against: Arguments That Minor Parties Do Matter In UK Politics
Minor parties have had a lot more electoral success in devolved bodies and have been able to wield a significant amount of power and influence over policy as a result.
"The Scottish National Party, for example, has been in power in Scotland since 2007 and has"
"been able to make significant policy changes, such as abolishing prescription charges and tuition fees."
Minor parties have also been able to have significant influence as junior partners in coalitions or
confidence and supply agreements.
"The Lib Dems, for example, drove policies through such as increasing the personal"
allowance and introducing the 2015 Recall of MPs Act.
The DUP was also able to have a significant impact over Brexit policy due to the power the
party held due to a Confidence and Supply Arrangement with the Conservative Party
"following the 2017 election, playing a key part in the move towards a hard Brexit."
"Further, polling in early 2025 indicates that Reform UK have a strong chance of challenging to"
win the next UK general election.
"In a January 2025 YouGov poll, the party came in second place and within the margin of"
"error to overtake Labour, polling at 25% compared to Labour's 26% and the Conservativesʼ 22%."
"Further, Reform has overtaken the Conservatives in terms of Party membership and the"
polls show gains especially concentrated in the 18 24 age category.
Judgement
"Overall, minor parties do matter as they are able to play a very significant role in government in"
"devolved bodies, particularly in Scotland. They are able to do so much less in the UK Government, however, which is always dominated by either Labour and the Conservatives and gives minor parties a relatively insignificant role even when they are in coalition."
Paragraph Three     Impact Over Policy
For: Arguments That Minor Parties Donʼt Matter In UK Politics
The two main parties have played a part in every government since the Second World War and
have been able to have a major impact over politics and policy in the UK.
"Thatcher, for example, was able to implement her New Right philosophy and massively"
change economic policy.
"Blair too was able to have a massive impact, especially in the area of constitutional reform"
and foreign policy.
It can be argued that the major parties are broad churches that represent a range of voters and
"policy positions, therefore enabling them to maintain significant support."
"Even when minor parties do have influence, it is often only temporary and reverts back to the"
major parties having influence afterwards.
"Further, even when minor parties do influence policy, the two main parties are able to"
determine the exact nature of these policies and water them down to an extent.
Against: Arguments That Minor Parties Do Matter In UK Politics
"Minor parties have significant indirect influence over policy, through threatening the two main"
parties electorally with the ‘spoiler effectʼ and using their platforms and public support to put issues on the political agenda.
"In many ways, these parties could therefore be seen as pressure groups that use the"
electoral process to pursue their aims.
By threatening the ‘spoiler effectʼ - taking votes away from a major party so that they lose the
"election to the other major party - minor parties can have a significant impact on the policies of the major parties, who want to hold on to these votes."
"For example, the electoral threat that Nigel Farage and UKIP posed to the Conservative"
"Party played a major role in David Cameron calling the Brexit referendum, whilst his Brexit Party played a major role in shifting the Tories in a more right wing, populist direction in the 2019 election."
"If the Tories hadnʼt made this shift to Boris and a hard Brexit, the Brexit Party may have"
taken away key voters and caused them to lose the 2019 election.
"Since the 2024 election, Reform UK threatening the Labour Party on immigration has"
influenced the government to adopt a much tougher policy on immigration
This can be seen in the February 2025 decision to remove the path to British citizenship
"for refugees who enter the UK illegally, as well as Starmerʼs major policy"
"announcements to shift the party to the right on immigration in May 2025, where"
Starmer said Britain had become an “island of strangersˮ.
These included doubling the residency requirement for permanent settlement from five
"to ten years, raising English proficiency standards and restricting visas for care workers."
"Even if they have a small number of MPs in Parliament, minor parties can also influence the"
policies of the main parties by using this political platform to raise the importance of issues and put things on the political agenda.
"The Green Party is a key example of this. For a long time, it had just 1 MP  Caroline Lucas) in"
"Parliament, but Lucas used this platform to raise the political profile of environmental issues and force Labour and the Conservatives to support them."
Judgement
"Overall, minor parties certainly matter a huge amount when it comes to influence over policy."
"Through raising the profile of key issues and threatening the two main parties electorally, minor parties UKIP and the Brexit Party in particular) have been able to cause massive policy shifts in the Labour and Conservative Parties."
Overall Argument
"In conclusion, The Labour Party and Conservative Party are certainly not the only parties that"
"matter in UK Politics. Whilst it is true that they dominate UK Parliament elections and UK Government due to FPTP, they donʼt dominate devolved bodies or have sole influence over policy."
"Minor parties are able to play a highly significant role in devolved bodies, particularly the SNP in"
"Scotland, and are crucially able to have major indirect influence over policy in the UK, by using their electoral threat and publicity to shape the policies of the two main parties."
Other Possible Essay Questions To Practice Adapting
This Plan To Answer
Evaluate the view that the UK is still a two-party system.  30
Evaluate the view that minor political parties are having an increasing impact on UK politics.
30
Follow Politics Explained For More Help With Your Politics A Level
Website → https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/
Instagram → https://www.instagram.com/polexplained/
YouTube  →  https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCQ1FvoFVL4fGJkx6dup3O-w
Twitter → https://twitter.com/Pol_Explain
