Evaluate The View That The Franchise
Should Be Extended. (30) Politics Explained Essay Plan
Topic        1. Democracy and Participation
Structure    Three paragraphs with for/against and an overall judgement within each
This Essay Plan Is Part Of A Package Of Essay Plans Covering The UK Politics Part Of The Politics
"A Level Course For The Edexcel Exam Board, Whilst Also Being Very Useful For The AQA Exam Board. It Can Be Purchased Here    https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/"
Keep In Mind       These are long plans as theyʼre intended to be revised from to cover the key
"content you need to know for the exam. In the exam, you would need to adapt them for the specific question you are asked and you certainly wouldnʼt need to include everything, especially not all of the examples. The judgements are also subjective and you donʼt have to"
agree with them!
Introduction
Key Definitions
Franchise is the right of a citizen to vote in elections. There has been a steady expansion of voting rights since the late 19th Century. Crucially in Wales and Scotland this includes the right for 16 and 17 year olds to vote in local and devolved elections.
Paragraph One      Votes at 16
For: The Franchise Should Be Extended To 16 And 17 Year Olds
Perhaps the most important possible reform to the franchise is introducing votes at 16 in UK
General Elections. This can be seen as beneficial to UK democracy for both moral and practical reasons.
"16 and 17 year olds have other legal rights; such as leaving school, starting work, and"
"joining the armed forces and it can therefore be argued they should be able to vote too, if"
they are deemed mature enough to be granted more autonomy and have these other rights.
"Therefore, voting can be seen as within their capacity."
"Crucially, 16 year olds are liable for taxation and therefore should be consulted in how"
their taxes are spent via the right to elect representatives. “Taxation without representationˮ violates democratic principles that individuals should not be subject to taxation unless they have a voice in the government that levies those taxes.
"Labour have committed to lowering the voting age in 2024 as a manifesto commitment,"
"which would introduced 1.5 million voters to the electorate. They argue that it is crucial for the social contract, as if youʼre old enough to pay your taxes, then you are entitled to have a say on how your taxes are spent."
"Additionally, lowering the voting age would ensure equal democratic rights across the UK. In"
"Scotland 16 year olds were first given the right to vote in the 2014 Independence Referendum,"
and since 2015 they can participate in Scottish Parliamentary elections.
The fact that in England 16 year olds cannot vote in any election means that young people
"of the same age are given different levels of political power simply based on where they live. This breaks the principle of equal citizenship, as democratic equality rests on the idea that citizens should have the same rights and say in how they are governed."
A final argument in favour of extending the franchise to 16 year olds is that lowering the voting
age could reverse low political engagement in young adults.
"In the 2014 Scottish Independence Referendum, 75% of 16 and 17 year turned out to vote -"
a notably higher turnout that those in the 18 24 bracket who had a turnout of just 64%.
"Importantly, turnout in Scottish Parliamentary elections for older age groups has also"
"gone up, indicating that earlier access to voting may create positive habits and young people may remain more likely to vote in later life, therefore improving the overall health of democracy"
Against: The Franchise Should Not Be Extended To 16 And 17 Year Olds
"Though there is growing support for votes at 16, many argue that this franchise reform shouldnʼt"
be introduced as it would harm democracy.
"While 16-year-olds may be able to form opinions, understand political issues, and make"
"decisions, it can be argued that their ability to evaluate long-term consequences isnʼt as"
"developed as that of adults, which would risk them misusing the right to vote."
"This is compounded by the fact that, in comparison to older voters, they disproportionately"
get their news from online sources and therefore are more subject to peer pressure and misinformation.
"In their 2024 report, OFCOM found 71% of 16 24 year olds used social media as their"
main source of news. This means they are more likely to be influenced by algorithms driving personalised news feeds which promote sensationalist misinformation over
facts.
"For example, in 2024 “online deepfakesˮ of Keir Starmer and London Mayor Sadiq Khan"
were shared on X receiving over 1.5 million views. Children donʼt have the cognitive capacity to distinguish reliable and unreliable information online which may compromise the integrity of their vote.
Most 16-year-olds havenʼt yet developed the life experience or emotional maturity to make
"informed decisions about complex political issues. At 16, most are still in compulsory education and have limited exposure to the reality of the world, whilst they also lack education and awareness on topics such as taxation, public spending and defence"
"Additionally, voter turnout amongst young people is at historic lows and is significantly lower"
"than older demographics, suggesting the impact of lowering the voting age on participation and the health of democracy would in fact be limited."
Only 37% of 18 24 year olds turned out to vote in the 2024 General Election. if a similar
"proportion of 16  and 17-year-olds turned out they would only amount to 520,000 new"
voters.
"Together, this shows that the franchise should not be extended to include 16 and 17 year olds"
they lack the resources to make informed decisions and it would not result in a meaningful increase in participation.
Judgement
"Overall, even though 16 and 17 year olds may lack political education, this is not exclusive to their age group and political apathy exists across the electorate. Allowing votes at 16 would create a lifelong habit which would boost participation and ensure fair and equal democratic rights across the UK."
When 16 year olds have been given the vote they have shown that they will take that
"opportunity. Therefore the franchise should be reformed to include 16 and 17 year olds, as it would help improve turnout, public participation in politics and therefore the health of democracy."
Paragraph Two     Prisoner Voting
For: The Franchise Should Be Extended To Prisoners
"Extending the franchise to allow prisoners to vote is a contentious issue in British politics. Currently, prisoners are universally denied the vote in England, Wales and Northern Ireland, whilst in Scotland any prisoner serving a sentence of less than 12 month can vote in regional elections."
The most compelling argument in favour of allowing Prisoner Voting is that not doing so
undermines the human rights of prisoners in the UK. This was demonstrated in the 2005 European Court of Human Rights case Hirst v United Kingdom.
"In 2005, the European Court of Human Rights  ECtHR  ruled that the blanket ban on"
prisoner voting by the UK Government violated Article 3 of the European Convention on Human Rights ECHR which ensures governments hold free elections under conditions which ensure the free expression of the opinion of the people.
The ruling argued a blanket ban was indiscriminate and disproportionate.
"This suggests that the franchise should be reformed to include prisoners, as voting is a"
fundamental right which shouldnʼt be removed from anyone. Denying prisoners the vote undermines the system of universal suffrage which is essential for liberal democracy.
"Furthermore, it can be argued that extending the franchise to prisoners would enhance"
"pluralism, which is when a government makes decisions as a result of the interplay of various"
"ideas and based on the interests of a range of different groups in society,"
"If the franchise were extended to prisoners, the government would be forced to listen and"
"respond to marginalised voices presenting competing ideas - perhaps forcing the Government to address the prisons crisis prior to the population reaching 88,000 and the dire state of prisons."
"Clearly, the ban is incompatible with international law and extending the franchise would"
"ensure greater pluralism in UK democracy, ensuring all voices in society are heard and minority groups are not neglected."
Against: The Franchise Shouldnʼt Be Extended To Prisoners
"On the other hand, it can be argued that the franchise should not be extended to prisoners, as"
"the are criminals who have broken the law and threatened society. As a result, they shouldnʼt be able to have a say in how society is run."
"In particular, they shouldnʼt be able to have a say in how the criminal justice system is run,"
as theyʼve ultimately broken the law and have no respect for Parliament and the rules it has created.
"This belief is broadly reflected in public opinion, and prisoner voting is not a popular"
measure despite pressure groups such as the Howard League for Penal Reform
campaigning strongly for prisonerʼs rights.
A YouGov opinion poll on the issue showed a majority of voters remain opposed to
prisoner voting; with 71% of people saying that criminals do not deserve a say in
elections.
This has been mirrored in the House of Commons when a Backbench Business debate
on the subject of voting by prisoners rejected prisoner voting by 234 22 with cross
party support.
"Further, prisoners lose other civil rights due to breaking the law, including liberty and"
"property, and it therefore shouldnʼt be seen as against human rights to remove their right to"
vote.
MPs have consistently argued that the Commons should continue to defy the ECtHR
"ruling in Hirst v United Kingdom, as it is an illegitimate challenge to a democratically elected Parliament."
Judgement
"Overall, the franchise should not be extended to prisoners as public opinion is clearly opposed"
"to it. The majority of the electorate agree that individuals who commit serious crimes have broken the social contract and should lose certain rights. Despite the ECtHR ruling, the more persuasive argument is that it isnʼt against human rights to deny prisoners the vote."
"Further, public resistance has played a key role in preventing reform and therefore extending"
"the franchise to prisoners would increase disillusionment and disengagement with politics, which is already a huge challenge to democracy in the UK."
Paragraph Three     Compulsory Voting
For: The Franchise Should Be Extended To Compulsory Voting
A final possible reform to the franchise in the UK is the introduction of compulsory voting at
"elections, as is the case in Australia where turnout is always over 90%."
The most persuasive argument in favour of compulsory voting is that it would help to tackle one
of the biggest challenges to the health of democracy in the UK; how low turnout undermines the legitimacy of government.
"British democracy is based upon the principle of representation, as governments command"
"the support of the House of Commons which is seen to be representative of the electorate. However, persistent low turnout in elections threatens the legitimacy of MPs and Governments as they cannot claim to genuinely speak for the people."
"In the 2024 General Election, turnout was just 59%, meaning over 1/3rd of the"
electorate failed to participate in the electoral process. This is a historic decline from
turnout in the 20th century which averaged over 75%.
Introducing compulsory voting would drive turnout to over 90% and improve democracy in
"the UK, as governments and MPs would be elected by a much larger portion of the population and therefore have much greater legitimacy and a stronger mandate."
"This would not only improve the health of democracy in the UK, it would also enable"
"governments to better deliver on their manifesto pledges, as Parliament would be less"
likely to stop a policy with major public support.
"Introducing compulsory voting would improve democracy in the UK, not only as it would"
"improve turnout and the legitimacy of governments, but also because it would mean that governments are elected with support from across the population."
"As all demographics would be represented in the electorate, politicians and parties would"
"be forced to run their campaigns with the whole electorate in mind, therefore improving the responsiveness of parties and making Parliament more representative of the whole population."
"Currently, older voters turnout in far higher numbers than younger voters. In 2017 ,"
turnout among the 65  age group was around 25 percentage points higher than among 18 24 year olds. This results in a greater focus from politicians on serving the interests of older voters than younger voters.
"For example, older voters benefit disproportionately from economic measures such"
"as the “triple lockˮ on state pensions which has lead to substantial increases in state pensions, despite questions over itʼs long term affordability and the lack of focus from Parliament on young people."
"If there was compulsory voting, older voters wouldnʼt form such a disproportionate"
"amount of the electorate and parties would be forced to represent all age groups equally, therefore improving democracy and representation in UK politics, particularly for young people."
Against: The Franchise Shouldnʼt Be Extended To Compulsory Voting
"On the other hand, it can be argued that extending the franchise to compulsory voting would"
not enhance UK democracy as it would not solve the core issues driving low turnout and the participation crisis in the UK.
Low turnouts are indicative of deeper issues in politics which would remain unaddressed by
"forcing people to vote, whilst if FPTP was still in place, parties would still disproportionately"
focus on different voters.
"Arguably, electoral reform is much more pressing than franchise reform, as politicians"
would continue to focus their campaigns on marginal seats if their was compulsory voting
and therefore continue to not represent the interests of the electorate as a whole.
"Safe seats and “wastedˮ votes that are produced by FPTP, where voters preferred"
"candidates have little chance of winning may cause voters to abstain/spoil their ballots even if there was compulsory voting, as voters would continue to believe that it isn't worth participating if their vote has no impact on parliamentary results due to FPTP."
"In the 2024 General Election, a majority of voters ended up with an MP they did not vote"
for and this would continue to be the case under FPTP as MPs donʼt require majority support from within their constituency to win.
"Additionally, it can be argued that compulsory voting shouldnʼt be introduced as it"
"undemocratic to force people to vote, which should be a matter of choice."
Voting is an individual right not a civic duty and people should be able to exercise this right
"by deciding not to vote, which communicates to Parliament that they donʼt have faith in the political system. Compulsory voting therefore undermines the rights of voters and liberal democracy by forcing the public to vote and preventing them from exercising their democratic right however they want."
"Further, forcing people to vote could lead to issues like spoilt ballots and “donkey"
"votingˮ, which do do little to genuinely enhance political participation, despite producing artificially high turnout."
Judgement
"Overall, the franchise should be extended to include compulsory voting as it is a reliable way to boost turnout and ensure near-universal participation. Elections would be more equal and social disparities minimised, creating beneficial electoral incentives for parties to appeal to disaffected sections of the electorate rather than tailing policies for a narrow few."
"Further, voters would still be able to communicate their dissatisfaction with the political"
system by spoiling their ballots.
Overall Argument
"In conclusion, reforms to the franchise in the UK havenʼt gone far enough and it should be"
"extended. The two most important franchise reforms are to extend the vote to 16 and 17 year olds, as well as to establish compulsory voting."
Both of these reforms would improve the health of democracy by challenging the core
"challenge of low turnout and participation. This would not only ensure that governments have a stronger mandate and are more legitimate, it would also make Parliament more likely to represent the interests and views of all voters, rather than just those who are currently able to vote and are most likely to, which is disproportionately older voters."
Other Possible Essay Questions To Practice Adapting
This Plan To Answer
Evaluate the view that introducing votes at 16 is the most important reform that should be
introduced to improve democracy in the UK. 30
Evaluate the view that introducing votes at 16 is the most important reform to the franchise.  30
Follow Politics Explained For More Help With Your Politics A Level
Website → https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/
Instagram → https://www.instagram.com/polexplained/
YouTube  →  https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCQ1FvoFVL4fGJkx6dup3O-w
Twitter → https://twitter.com/Pol_Explain
