"Evaluate The View That Think-Tanks,"
Lobbyists And Pressure Groups Have Little Impact On Government Decisions. (30) Politics Explained Essay Plan
Topic        1. Democracy and Participation
Structure    Three paragraphs with for/against and an overall judgement within each
This Essay Plan Is Part Of A Package Of Essay Plans Covering The UK Politics Part Of The Politics
"A Level Course For The Edexcel Exam Board, Whilst Also Being Very Useful For The AQA Exam Board. It Can Be Purchased Here    https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/"
Keep In Mind       These are long plans as theyʼre intended to be revised from to cover the key
"content you need to know for the exam. In the exam, you would need to adapt them for the specific question you are asked and you certainly wouldnʼt need to include everything, especially not all of the examples. The judgements are also subjective and you donʼt have to agree with them!"
Introduction
Key Definitions
Pressure groups are groups that seek to influence politics in order to achieve particular goals.
"They donʼt seek political office, but seek to change policy through influencing public opinion, parliament and the government"
Think-Tanks are groups of experts who are brought together to investigate topics and offer
"solutions to complicated, economic, social and political issues."
Lobbyists are members of professional organisations paid by clients seeking access to
"government, MPs and members of the House of Lords. Their purpose is to gain influence on behalf of their clients and prevent/promote legislation damaging/promoting their interests."
Paragraph One     Insider Pressure Groups
For: Arguments That Insider Pressure Groups Have A Significant Impact
"Insider Pressure Groups exert influence on UK politics through the close contacts they have with ministers, government departments, MPs and civil servants."
"Due to being aligned with the government politically, they often have close links with"
government departments and can therefore directly lobby the government in order to try and achieve their aims.
"The National Farmersʼ Union, for example, had close links with the Department of"
"Environment, Food and Rural Affairs DEFRA under the Conservative Party and was able to provide the department with specific expertise and advice. Itʼs influence was based on the importance of farmers to the UK economy."
They had a particular success in 2013 when they helped to bring about a badger cull to
"control the spread of bovine tuberculosis to farm animals, despite pressure groups supporting animal welfare (such as the Badger Trust and Royal Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals) opposing it."
"More recently, in early 2024 Prime Minister Rishi Sunak attended their annual"
"conference and pledged to protect British Farming in the agricultural market - leading to the UK suspending their trade talks with Canada after they refused to loosen food standards. This benefited the 55,000 farmers the union represents."
"Due to their specific expertise, insider groups are sometimes able to brief the government on"
"issues of concern, play a key role in drafting legislation, or give evidence to select committees."
"When New Labour were in power, for example, LGBT  Rights Pressure Group Stonewall had"
"insider status group and was able to play a key role in policy formulation. As a result, they had important successes including equalising the age of consent for gay and straight individuals to 16 years old as part of the Sexual Offences Act 2000, for which the"
Parliaments Acts 1911 and 1949 had to be invoked to overrule House of Lords opposition.
Against: Arguments That Insider Pressure Groups Have Limited Impact
"On the other hand, the influence of Insider Pressure Groups shouldnʼt be overstated. The"
"government does sometimes listen to them and does use their expertise, however it is still the government that ultimately makes the final decisions on policy."
"Further, as they have to be broadly aligned with government policies to have an impact, they"
are unlikely to majorly shift policy in a direction the government wouldnʼt have done so anyway.
"The National Union Of Farmers, for example, had influence over Conservative"
governments because the Conservative Party broadly supports their aims anyway.
This also makes Insider Pressure Groups very dependent on the political leanings of the
government of the day and can quickly become outsider groups and lose their influence if
the political situation changes.
"For example, key trade unions wielded a lot of influence under the Labour governments"
"of the 1970s, but had little-to-no influence once Thatcher was elected and was intent on curtailing trade union power."
"Crucially, this can also be seen in the National Farmers Unionʼs  influence over policy"
"decreasing significantly after the election of Labour in 2024, which meant they were no longer an insider group due to Labour performing less well in rural seats and the countryside being less important to their identity as a party."
"In the 2024 Budget, Chancellor Rachel Reeves introduced a tax of 20% on inherited"
"farming assets over £1 million - president of the NFU Tom Bradshaw has criticised this for leading to the ""death of the family farm""."
The government has refused to reverse the policy despite mass protests by farmers
"outside of Westminter, including 13,000 farmers protesting outside of Westminster on the 19th of November 2024, and the NFU organising a “mass lobbyˮ event where thousands of farmers met 150 MPs in London."
"Finally, it is also often very difficult to judge the success of Insider Pressure Groups as they"
"often donʼt publicise the successes they have had as to not offend, and therefore risk losing, their government contacts."
Judgement/Mini Conclusion
"Overall, though it is difficult to judge the success of Insider Pressure Groups as they work behind the scenes, it seems fair to argue that they can often have a significant impact on government decisions, particularly when they can provide the government with specific expertise."
"This being said, they are unlikely to instigate major policy shifts and it must be recognised that"
the government ultimately makes the final decision on policy.
"Their impact on government decisions can therefore sometimes be significant, but their overall"
influence shouldnʼt be overstated.
Paragraph Two     Outsider Pressure Groups
For: Arguments That Outsider Pressure Groups Have A Significant Impact
Outsider Pressure Groups seek to exert over government policy by mobilising public opinion
"and support through the use of the media, public protests and other non-discrete methods."
They are able to raise the salience of an issue in UK politics and put pressure on the
government to change policy. Social movements in particular are sometimes able to have success due to their ability to demonstrate to the government their goals have significant public support and could therefore influence their popularity and election outcomes.
This can be seen in the success of the 2020 campaign to extend free school meals to
"children during the school holidays, led by footballer Marcus Rashford. The campaign effectively used social media, traditional media and e-petitions to generate a social movement and demonstrate public support, which made the government u-turn and accept"
the groupʼs demands on 16 June 2020.
This can also be seen in the success of protests calling for a ceasefire in Gaza that took
"place consistently in London throughout 2024, with over 100,000 attendees."
The public pressure and anger demonstrated by this social movement played a key role
in the Labour Governmentʼs decision in September 2024 to suspend some of its arms export licences to Israel.
Another effective method often used by well-funded outsider pressure groups are legal
challenges with the intention of influencing government policy. A key example of this is the pressure group For Women Scotlandʼs successful legal challenge against the Scottish Government in April 2025.
Not only did this get the Supreme Court to reverse the Scottish Governmentʼs decision to
"include transgender people with Gender Recognition Certificates in their definition of ‘sexʼ in the Equality Act, it also got the Supreme Court to explicitly define a ‘womanʼ as based on biological sex in the Equality Act - one of the pressure groupʼs key beliefs and aims."
This also led to the UK government accepting the ruling and the Supreme Courtʼs
"definition of a ‘womanʼ, demonstrating how pressure groups can use judicial review to influence the government and achieve their policy aims."
Against: Arguments That Outsider Pressure Groups Have Limited Impact
"On the other hand, many Outsider Pressure Groups struggle to have an impact on government"
"policy, because they lack contacts within government and are often very far from being aligned with government attitudes and policy goals."
"For example, Women Against State Pension Inequality WASPI has failed to convince the"
Labour Government to compensate the 3.6 million women affected by the poorly communicated change to the womenʼs state pension age that began in 2010.
"Despite campaigning through demonstrations and e-petitions, the Labour Government"
"rejected compensation in December 2024, largely due to the fact that it would cost over"
£10bn and this wasnʼt aligned with the governmentʼs goals of reducing the deficit and promoting growth.
"Further, Outsider Pressure Groups often struggle if they fail to get significant public support,"
which is often the case if their methods are disruptive/violent.
"A good example of this is the Just Stop Oil movement, which gained a lot of media attention"
"in 2022 due to disruptive public demonstrations, including blocking roads and stopping Premier League football matches."
This alienated a lot of the public to their cause of ending all new licences for the
production of fossil fuels in the UK and made it easier for Sunakʼs government to announce in July 2023 that he was going to grant 100 new North Sea oil and gas licences.
This shows how disruptive outsider methods can be ineffective if they have limited
government support and alienate the public to their cause.
"The Public Order Act, passed in May 2023, was also introduced by the government to limit the"
"effectiveness of outsider pressure groups that use disruptive tactics to draw attention to their causes, by imposing stricter penalties and giving law enforcement new tools to manage and"
respond to protests.
"The Act introduced new offences such as ""locking-on"" (attaching oneself to objects or"
"other people to cause serious disruption) and interfering with national infrastructure (including the roads around Parliament), which are punishable by imprisonment or unlimited fines."
"In March 2025, the Public Order Act was used to prevent farmers protesting against"
inheritance tax changes from bringing tractors to their protests in Westminster and blocking the roads.
Judgement/Mini Conclusion
"Overall, the majority of Outsider Pressure Groups struggle to have an impact on government"
"policy, because their views arenʼt aligned with the government and they are very dependent on gaining significant public support."
When Outsider Pressure Groups are able to gain major public support and generate a social
"movement, however, they can have a significant impact on policy and cause major u-turns."
Paragraph Three      Think Tanks and Lobbyists
For: Arguments That Think Tanks and Lobbyists Have A Significant Impact
Think Tanks:
Think-Tanks are groups of experts who are brought together to investigate topics and offer
"solutions to complicated, economic, social and political issues."
"They can be an alternative source of ideas to the civil service, with more time and expertise"
"than parties to carry out research. As a result, they can influence the policies of parties and the actions of government, particularly as they have strong political leanings and party allegiances."
The Universal Credit benefits system was first proposed by the Centre for Social Justice (set up
by Ian Duncan Smith) and then implemented by the Coalition government.
Liz Truss and Kwasi Kwartengʼs disastrous economic policies of deregulation and tax breaks for
"the rich in October 2022 can be seen as influenced by the very neoliberal Institute of Economic Affairs  IEA , with Trussʼ senior special adviser Ruth Porter a former communications directors"
at the IEA.
"In late 2023 and early 2024, it has been reported that the Tony Blair Institute For Global Change,"
has been consulted and had considerable influence on Labour Party Policy under Keir Starmer. The think tank set up by former Prime Minister Tony Blair offers policy advice that aligns with centrist and progressive ideologies.
Its influence can be seen in the Labour Party shift under Starmer to centrist policies and
"messaging that are similar to New Labour. This includes emphasising that the party is once more ‘pro-businessʼ and tough on crime and antisocial behaviour. Labour has focused on policies such as increasing police numbers, investing in community policing, and supporting tougher sentences for serious offenses."
Lobbyists:
Lobbyists are members of professional organisations paid by clients seeking access to
"government, MPs and members of the House of Lords. Their purpose is to gain influence on behalf of their clients and prevent/promote legislation damaging/promoting their interests."
Lobbying is big in the UK; employing 4000 people with a total of £2 Billion spent on it each year.
Lobbyists frequently discuss their concerns with MPs and government departments and can
"use the economic importance of their clients, as well as the potentially corrupting influence of"
"money more generally, to try and influence policy."
"Scott Benton, former Conservative MP for Blackpool South, was caught in an undercover"
"sting operation by The Times in late 2023, where he was filmed offering to lobby on behalf of a fake gambling company."
"During the meetings, which were secretly filmed, Benton proposed to ask parliamentary"
"questions and leak confidential policy papers for the company, suggesting he could do so in exchange for payments of up to £4,000 a month."
Many lobbying firms and individual companies also hire former politicians to lobby on their
"behalf, due to the importance of their contacts and friends in Westminster."
The Guardian reported in March 2023 that since 2017 over 170 former UK ministers and
"senior officials have taken up jobs that relate to policy areas they previously managed. This raises concerns about potential conflicts of interest, as these individuals may leverage their"
insider knowledge and connections to lobby on behalf of private interests.
A recent example of this is Penny Mourdaunt taking a job at British American Tobacco
"just 5 months after being out of office. This led to accusations from some that they had influenced her behaviour when Leader of the House, as the Tobacco and Vapes Bill (which would have been against  British American Tobaccoʼs commercial interest if passed) wasnʼt chosen to make it through Parliament after Sunak called a snap general election, despite receiving a majority in its second reading just weeks prior."
Against: Arguments That Think Tanks and Lobbyists Have Limited Impact
"As with Insider Pressure Groups, it is very difficult to judge the extent of the influence of"
lobbyists and think tanks on government policy. The government still makes the final decision on policy and their influence perhaps shouldnʼt be overstated.
"Further, as both groups lack significant public support, they may struggle to have as much"
"influence and pressure groups, who are able to demonstrate that adopting a policy may"
increase support for the government across the population.
"Whilst lobbyists certainly can have influence through their contacts and financial incentives, the"
"extent of corruption shouldnʼt be overstated, particularly as it would represent a serious breach of the the Ministerial Code and cause a major media and public backlash if it was revealed."
"For example, in April 2024, the House of Commons voted for the Tobacco and Vapes Act,"
"which would have prohibited anyone born after 2009 from purchasing cigarettes. The bill was passed with 383 MPs voting in favour and just 67 voting against, despite intense lobbying by the tobacco industry for MPs to vote down the bill."
This shows the limits of lobbyingʼs success if it goes against clear government
intentions and popular policies.
Counterpoint: the bill was never passed as it ran out of time before the 2024 general
election. It can be argued that the decision to drop the bill due to timing may have been influenced by lobbying efforts.
"In March 2023, the UK Parliament also sought to regulate lobbying more strictly by"
introducing new standards rules to enhance transparency and regulate MPs' conduct more stringently.
"Key updates include an outright ban on MPs providing paid parliamentary advice,"
"consultancy, or strategy services related to lobbying. Additionally, MPs are now required to have a written contract for any outside work explicitly stating that their duties do not include lobbying activities."
Judgement
Though Think Tanks and Lobbyists certainly can have influence on government decisions
"through their contacts, as with pressure groups they are very dependent on being aligned the attitudes of the government of the day, whilst they often struggle as they lack the public support that pressure groups often have."
Overall Argument
"In conclusion, the influence of pressure groups, think tanks and lobbyists on government"
"decisions varies greatly and is often hard to judge. The government does ultimately make the final decision on policy, which leads to alignment with government attitudes being an important factor in the success of these groups."
"As this is the case, however, the policy shifts they are able to instigate are often minor and"
their influence therefore somewhat limited.
When pressure groups have significant public support and are able to generate a social
"movement, however, they can at times have significant influence on government decisions."
"Overall, the influence of pressure groups, think tanks and lobbyists on government decisions is"
"usually limited, but can sometimes be significant, particularly for outsider pressure groups."
Other Possible Essay Questions To Practice Adapting
This Plan To Answer
Evaluate the view that Insider Pressure Groups are more effective than Outsider Pressure
Groups 30
Evaluate the view that lobbyists and corporations have more influence on government decisions
than pressure groups 30
Follow Politics Explained For More Help With Your Politics A Level
Website → https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/
Instagram → https://www.instagram.com/polexplained/
YouTube  →  https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCQ1FvoFVL4fGJkx6dup3O-w
Twitter → https://twitter.com/Pol_Explain
