Evaluate The View That Current Labour
Party Policy Is Closer To Old Labour Than It Is To New Labour. (30) - Politics Explained Essay Plan
Topic      2. Political Parties
Structure    Three paragraphs with for/against and an overall judgement within each
This Essay Plan Is Part Of A Package Of Essay Plans Covering The UK Politics Part Of The Politics
"A Level Course For The Edexcel Exam Board, Whilst Also Being Very Useful For The AQA Exam Board. It Can Be Purchased Here    https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/"
Keep In Mind       These are long plans as theyʼre intended to be revised from to cover the key
"content you need to know for the exam. In the exam, you would need to adapt them for the specific question you are asked and you certainly wouldnʼt need to include everything, especially not all of the examples. The judgements are also subjective and you donʼt have to agree with them!"
Introduction
Key Definitions
"In the years since Keir Starmer has become leader, Labour Party policy has shifted significantly"
away from that of Corbynʼs Labour Party. This essay will therefore take ‘current Labour Party
policyʼ to mean the policies of the Labour Party under Starmer currently.
Paragraph One     Economic Policy
For: The Labour Party Is Closer To Old Labour
"Since coming into power in 2024 the Labour Party has passed The Passenger Railway Services Public Ownership) Act to re-nationalise the rail service and has introduce the Great British Energy Bill to establish Great British Energy as a state-owned energy company that would reinvest profits into public services. This is a significant difference from New Labour, which supported privatisation and didnʼt nationalise any industries when in power."
"Nationalisation is also a key economic aim and principle of Old Labour, which believed that"
"key industries should be run by the state in the interest of the whole population, rather than being driven by private profit."
"Under Starmer in opposition, the Labour Party criticised the Conservativesʼ approach to the"
cost of living crisis and pledged to decrease disparities within society.
Starmer also criticised the Conservativesʼ approach to striking workers and pledged to
negotiate with public sector trade unions in order to agree on new pay deals and prevent further  strikes.
"In the summer of 2024, Chancellor Rachel Reeves announced an above inflation pay"
"rise for public sector workers, including a 22% pay rise for junior doctors and a 5.5% pay rise for teachers."
"This can be seen as being aligned with the principles of Old Labour, which is driven by"
improving equality in society and representing the working class.
"Supporting this approach, the Labour Government has also recently introduced the"
"Employment Rights Bill, with the aim of promoting the rights of workers in the UK through reforms that include ending zero-hours contracts and strengthening statutory sick pay."
Against: The Labour Party Is Closer To New Labour
"Since becoming leader, Starmer has sought to shift the Labour Partyʼs image away from being"
anti-business as it was perceived under Corbyn and towards a greater support of capitalism and the business community. This is similar to the transformation of the Labour Party under Blair and New Labour.
"This was clear in the Labour Investment Summit in October 2024, which attracted over 300"
industry leaders and resulted in £63 billion of private investment commitments.
"In his speech at the summit, Starmer emphasised his commitment to reducing bureaucracy"
and reassured business owners that Labourʼs workersʼ rights agenda would not hinder economic growth.
"Though Starmer has pledged to nationalise rail and create a publicly owned energy company,"
he has scrapped the other four planned nationalisations that Corbynʼs Labour Party supported.
Starmer has also pledged to reform the NHS and cut waiting times by making greater use of
private providers and being ruthless with ‘bureaucratic nonsenseʼ.
"This is very similar to New Labour, which introduced Private Finance Initiatives  PFIs), in"
"which private contractors were used to help deliver public services, including the NHS."
"The economic policy of Starmerʼs Labour Party has shifted away from the ‘high taxation, high"
"spendingʼ policies of the Corbyn era, instead moving towards a prioritisation of national finances through limited spending and pledging to freeze the taxes."
Labourʼs 2024 manifesto pledged not to increase tax for businesses or working people. This
"includes income tax, national insurance, VAT and corporation tax. This was delivered in their first budget in October 2024."
"They instead pledged to increase some limited taxes, including removing private"
schoolsʼ VAT exemption and abolishing tax loopholes particularly those associated with non-domiciled residents (non-doms).
"This is similar to New Labour, which pledged in the 1997 election not to increase taxes,"
"especially income tax, and to conserve resources before investing more in key public services."
"When in opposition, Starmer discouraged Labour MPs from going to picket lines in order to"
"demonstrate their support for striking workers, showing a key difference with the principles of Old Labour, which supported workers using industrial action (striking) in order to achieve better pay and conditions."
"Sam Tarry, a left-wing MP and shadow rail minister, who was dismissed in the summer of"
"2022 for participating in a picket line with striking rail workers, contrary to Starmer's"
directive that shadow ministers shouldnʼt do so.
Judgement
Starmerʼs two pledged nationalisations are an important move away from New Labourʼs staunch
"support for privatisation. Overall, however, current Labour Party policy is closer to New Labour than it is to Old Labour, as it is generally supportive of privatisation, has developed links with the business community and takes a generally cautious approach to taxation and public spending."
Paragraph Two      Law and Order & Welfare
Against: The Labour Party Is Closer To New Labour
"One of New Labourʼs key policy shifts was on Law and Order, with the Labour Party shifting to taking a tough stance on crime, which was traditionally a policy stance associated with the Conservative Party."
"Blair famously said that Labour must be 'tough on crime and tough on the causes of crime',"
"setting out his policy of punishing criminal behaviour, whilst continuing to tackle poor social conditions."
The current law and order policies of the Labour Party are very similar.
"In their 2024 manifesto, Labour pledged to recruit 13,000 extra neighbourhood police and"
"PCSOs, showing a strong approach to tackling crime. Furthermore, Labour intends to intensify the monitoring of the 1,000 most dangerous sexual predators, proposing surveillance measures akin to those used for tracking terrorists, which include covert operations, manhunts, and electronic tagging."
The Labour Party under Starmer has also taken a strong stance against low-level anti-
"social behaviour and recreational drug use, opposing the legalisation of cannabis and"
saying that the smell of cannabis is ‘ruining livesʼ.
"Starmer has also supported policies that promote rehabilitation, including specific attention"
"to the importance of working alongside youth workers, mental health services, schools and drug rehabilitation centres to ensure the police are working closer with communities."
"The exact same can be seen in the Labour Partyʼs current welfare policy, which demonstrates a"
"similar approach to New Labourʼs attempt to get people into work through welfare-to-work programmes and increasing means testing of benefits to ensure that the benefits system was a “hand-up, not a handoutˮ."
"In March 2025, Starmerʼs government announced £6 billion in benefits cuts with the"
"intention of getting people into work and reducing the spiralling costs of welfare spending. Work and Pensions Secretary Liz Kendal expressing concern about individuals ""taking the mickey"" by claiming benefits when they should be working."
The changes include tougher eligibility tests for Personal Independence Payment PIP  a
key disability benefit - and significant changes to Universal Credit calculations to cut payments for those unfit to work.
For: The Labour Party Is Closer To Old Labour
"Though being tough on crime wasnʼt a central part of Old Labourʼs political messaging, they werenʼt lax on crime and also supported a rehabilitative approach."
"Corbyn, for example, who can be seen as supportive of Old Labour, also opposed cuts to"
police numbers.
The current Labour Partyʼs law and order policies therefore donʼt differ markedly from the
policies and principles of Old Labour.
"On immigration, the current Labour Partyʼs tough stance and intention to reduce immigration"
"numbers is arguably similar to neither New Labour or Old Labour, which were both largely"
supportive of immigration.
This can be seen in the February 2025 decision to remove the path to British citizenship for
"refugees who enter the UK illegally, as well as Starmerʼs major policy announcements to shift the party to the right on immigration in May 2025, where Starmer said Britain had become an “island of strangersˮ."
These included doubling the residency requirement for permanent settlement from five to
"ten years, raising English proficiency standards and restricting visas for care workers."
Judgement
"Overall, current Labour Party policy on law and order is very similar to that of New Labourʼs"
"‘tough on crime, tough on the causes of crimeʼ and is clearly trying to appeal to a similar group"
"of voters, using the same playbook."
The exact same can be said of Labourʼs current welfare policy.
"In relation to law and order, the policies of the current Labour Party is therefore closer to New"
"Labour than it is to Old Labour, though it isnʼt opposed to Old Labour and its immigration policies are similar to neither."
Paragraph Three     Foreign Policy
Against: The Labour Party Is Closer To New Labour
New Labour and Tony Blairʼs time as Prime Minister became largely defined in the eyes of many
by its interventionist foreign policy and strong relationship with the United States.
Blair and the Labour Party supported George Bushʼs War on Terror and Western military
"intervention across the world, most famously in the 2003 invasion of Iraq."
"Current Labour Party policy can be seen as somewhat similar, with Starmer stressing the"
"partyʼs strong commitment to NATO, the special relationship with the United States and"
defending Western interests.
"After Trump indicated a reduced commitment to Ukraineʼs defence in February 2025,"
"Starmer announced an increase in defence spending to 2.5% by 2027, citing the growing"
security threats posed by global instability.
"Starmer has also continued funding for Ukraine since coming into power, including"
giving Ukraine a £2.26B loan in March 2025.
Further a meeting between Trump and Starmer in February 2025 indicated Starmerʼs
intention to maintain the special relationship with the U.S. with both leaders praising each other and Starmer offering Trump an unprecedented second state visit.
This strong commitment to defence and Western support for Ukraine can be seen as different
"to Old Labour, which opposes Western intervention and supports nuclear non-proliferation."
"Jeremy Corbyn, for example, has cautioned against the UKʼs strong support for Ukraine,"
suggesting instead that the UK should help to facilitate a peace deal. Corbyn has also
previously supported getting rid of Trident (the UKʼs nuclear weapons).
For: The Labour Party Is Closer To Old Labour
"Though Old Labour principles supported peace and opposed Western intervention and NATO,"
Old Labour governments often didnʼt pursue these policies strongly.
"When Labour Party leader, for example, Corbyn didnʼt support taking the UK out of NATO or"
"getting rid of Trident, even though he may have personally supported these policies, as this"
wouldʼve been very unpopular with the electorate.
"Further, the Labour governmentʼs cut to foreign aid spending in February 2025, from 0.5% of"
GDP to 0.3% of GDP wouldʼve been opposed by both New Labour and Old Labour which were strongly committed  to tackling poverty globally.
Judgement
"Overall, the current Labour Partyʼs strong commitment to defence and Western intervention in Ukraine is similar to New Labourʼs foreign policy and much more so than it is similar to Old Labourʼs foreign policy."
Overall Argument
"In conclusion, current Labour Party policy is closer to New Labour than it is to Old Labour."
"Particularly in relation to law and order policy, welfare policy and a centrist, cautious approach"
"to economic policy, the current Labour Party is seeking to move to the centre and win middle class voters, in the same way New Labour did. Old Labourʼs policies were far more radical than the policies of the current Labour Party, particularly in relation to nationalisation and taxation."
Other Possible Essay Questions To Practice Adapting
This Plan To Answer
Evaluate the view that the current Labour Party policy is closer to that of New Labour than it is
to Labour Party policy under Corbyn.  30
Evaluate the view that the Labour Party currently remains true to its traditional values and
principles. 30
Follow Politics Explained For More Help With Your Politics A Level
Website → https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/
Instagram → https://www.instagram.com/polexplained/
YouTube   →   https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCQ1FvoFVL4fGJkx6dup3O-w
Twitter → https://twitter.com/Pol_Explain
