Evaluate The View That The Policies Of
The Main Parties Are More Similar Than They Are Dissimilar. (30) Politics Explained Essay Plan
Topic      2. Political Parties
Structure    Three paragraphs with for/against and an overall judgement within each
This Essay Plan Is Part Of A Package Of Essay Plans Covering The UK Politics Part Of The Politics
"A Level Course For The Edexcel Exam Board, Whilst Also Being Very Useful For The AQA Exam Board. It Can Be Purchased Here    https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/"
Keep In Mind       These are long plans as theyʼre intended to be revised from to cover the key
"content you need to know for the exam. In the exam, you would need to adapt them for the specific question you are asked and you certainly wouldnʼt need to include everything, especially not all of the examples. The judgements are also subjective and you donʼt have to agree with them!"
Introduction
Key Definitions
"In this essay plan, the Liberal Democrats are considered as a main party, along with the Labour"
Party and Conservative Party
Paragraph One     Economic Policy
For: Arguments That The Economic Policies Of The Main Parties Are More
Similar Than Dissimilar
"All of the Conservative Party, the Labour Party and the Liberal Democrats are strongly supportive of capitalism and business. They also support the prioritisation of national finances in the context of the cost of living crisis and huge debts incurred in recent decades."
"Both the Conservative and Labour parties prioritised reducing the debt, bringing down"
inflation and driving economic growth and are trying to win the centre ground and seem economically  competent.
"Halving inflation, growing the economy and reducing the debt were 3 of Rishi Sunakʼs 5"
priorities when in power
"Starmer has also moved the party away from the high taxation, high spending policies"
"of the Corbyn era. Instead, he has supported a more cautious, centrist approach to the economy and is rebuilding links with the business community."
Chancellor Reeves has made clear that the governmentʼs economic policy will focus
"on fiscal responsibility and providing a stable economic environment that can promote economic growth, rather than the emphasis on major investment and change promoted by Corbyn. She has called this approach ‘securonomicsʼ."
Key aspects of Securonomics include avoiding running a budget deficit and
"implementing a ""fiscal lock"" to ensure fiscal discipline, mirroring measures to"
ensure economic stability and growth without excessive borrowing.
This emphasis on fiscal responsibility can be seen in Labour ditching its
"previously proposed £28 billion-a-year green prosperity plan, which it justified by saying it was prioritising financial stability."
"Further, since coming to power the Labour Party has actively sought to strengthen"
"ties with the business community, including through its investment summit in October 2024, which attracted over 300 industry leaders and resulted in £63 billion of private investment commitments."
"All three parties pledged in the 2024 election campaign to freeze the majority of taxes, in"
"particular income tax, corporation tax and VAT. The Labour government delivered on this in"
their first budget in October 2024.
Against: Arguments That The Economic Policies Of The Main Parties Are More
Dissimilar Than Similar
Whilst the Conservative Party and the Liberal Democrat completely support privatisation and
"donʼt support any renationalisation of industries, since coming into power in 2024 the Labour Party has passed The Passenger Railway Services  Public Ownership) Act to re-nationalise the rail service and has introduce the Great British Energy Bill to establish Great British Energy as a state-owned energy company that would reinvest profits into public services."
"Though they agreed on the majority of taxes, the three parties did have some different taxation"
policies in their 2024 manifestos.
"In the 2024 Spring Budget, the Conservative government announced a cut to National"
Insurance contributions for employees from 10% to 8% and in their 2024 election
"manifesto, the Conservative Party pledged to reduce it to 6% by April 2027."
This reflects a strong tax-cutting Thatcherite strain that remains in the Conservative
Party. This is not as central to the policies of the Lib Dems or Labour.
The Lib Dems pledged in 2024 to raise funds through reforming Capital Gains Tax to close
"loopholes, raising levies on banks and introducing a new aviation duty to penalise frequent fliers and cracking down on tax avoidance."
This represented a greater commitment to tax rises and introduction than the Labour
Party and Conservative Party.
"In the 2024 election, the Liberal Democrats took a more ambitious approach to government"
spending than Labour or the Conservatives. The party pledged to spend £27B more per year by
"2029, including by spending an extra £9.5B on health and social care."
The party also had more left wing welfare policies than the Labour or Conservative parties.
"They pledged to remove both the two-child limit, which affects Universal Credit and Child Tax Credit, as well as the benefit cap – the limit on the total amount of benefit one household can claim."
"The Labour Party was criticised for pledging neither of these measures, which would"
have a significant impact in reducing poverty.
Judgement
"Overall, whilst the Labour Partyʼs two proposed nationalisations are certainly an important difference from the Lib Dems and Tories and they do have slightly different taxation policies, overall they are more similar than they are dissimilar."
All three parties have relatively centrist economic policies that are strongly supportive of
capitalism and business and support largely maintaining the current taxation framework.
Starmer has significantly moved the Labour Partyʼs economic policies away from where
"they were under Corbyn, which were very different from the policies of the Conservatives or Lib Dems."
Paragraph Two     Law and Order & The Unions
For: Arguments That The Law and Order & Unions Policies Of The Main Parties
Are More Similar Than Dissimilar
Both the Labour Party and the Conservative Party have strong stances on Law and Order and
antisocial behaviour. Both parties have also pledged to recruit more police officers.
"Sunakʼs government took a strong approach to tackling crime, meeting the partyʼs 2019"
"manifesto target of recruiting 20,000 additional police officers and pledging in their 2024 manifesto to recruit 8,000 more."
"In March 2023, Sunak introduced a comprehensive anti-social behaviour action plan"
"aimed at curbing what he described as the “scourge of anti-social behaviour"" in communities across the UK. The plan involves a series of measures designed to deliver swift and visible justice."
"One notable element is the introduction of immediate justice initiatives, where"
offenders are required to engage in community repair work such as cleaning graffiti
or picking up litter within 48 hours of their sentencing.
The Conservative government also showed a strong stance against drugs by banning
the use of nitrus oxide (laughing gas).
The current law and order policies of the Labour Party are very similar.
"In their 2024 manifesto, Labour pledged to recruit 13,000 extra neighbourhood police"
"and PCSOs, showing a strong approach to tackling crime. Furthermore, Labour intends"
"to intensify the monitoring of the 1,000 most dangerous sexual predators, proposing"
"surveillance measures akin to those used for tracking terrorists, which include covert"
"operations, manhunts, and electronic tagging."
The Labour Party under Starmer has also taken a strong stance against low-level anti-
"social behaviour and recreational drug use, opposing the legalisation of cannabis and"
saying that the smell of cannabis is ‘ruining livesʼ.
"In the 2024 manifestos of all three main parties, there was also a focus on the importance of"
"rehabilitation to stop reoffending, reflecting the fact that there are very high reoffending rates"
and there is an overcrowding crisis in prisons.
Against: Arguments That The Law and Order & Unions Policies Of The Main
Parties Are More Dissimilar Than Similar
"The Conservative Partyʼs approach to the unions, striking and protests has also been a lot"
stronger than the Labour Party or the Lib Demsʼ approach
"Sunak introduced the Strikes  Minimum Service Levels) Act 2023, which requires minimum"
services levels in key public sectors and therefore limits the power of strikes.
"The Public Order Act  2023  introduced new offenses such as ""locking-on"" and"
"interfering with national infrastructure (including the roads around Parliament), which are punishable by imprisonment or unlimited fines."
It was enacted in response to the UK government's concerns over highly disruptive
"protest tactics employed by groups like Extinction Rebellion and Just Stop Oil, but has been criticised for threatening the right to protest in the UK."
"By contrast, in the summer of 2024, Chancellor Rachel Reeves announced an above inflation"
"pay rise for public sector workers, including a 22% pay rise for junior doctors and a 5.5% pay rise for teachers, demonstrating a greater willingness in the Labour Party to support striking"
workers.
"Further, the government has introduced legislation with the intention of repealing the the"
Strikes  Minimum Service Levels) Act 2023 in 2025.
Judgement
"Overall, the policies of the main parties are more similar than they are dissimilar in relation to law and order, with both parties taking a strong approach, but more dissimilar than they are similar with regards to policies towards the unions."
Paragraph Three       Foreign Policy & Immigration Policy
For: Arguments That The Foreign and Immigration Policies Of The Main Parties
Are More Similar Than Dissimilar
"The Labour Party, Conservative Party and Liberal Democrats have supported a strong foreign"
"policy against Russiaʼs war in Ukraine, with the Conservative and Labour Governments giving Ukraine significant military support and the Liberal Democrats pledging to do the same in their 2024  manifesto."
"In 2024, the Conservative UK government committed £2.5 billion (approximately $3.2"
"billion) in military funding to Ukraine, making the UK one of the largest providers of military"
"aid to Ukraine in Europe, only behind Germany."
"Starmer has continued funding for Ukraine since coming into power, including giving"
Ukraine a £2.26B loan in March 2025.
The Lib Demsʼ 2024 manifesto pledged to “stand with the people of Ukraine and
provide them with the support that they need in the face of Putinʼs illegal invasion.ˮ
All three parties also have a strong foreign and defence policy more generally.
"After Trump indicated a reduced commitment to Ukraineʼs defence in February 2025,"
"Starmer announced an increase in defence spending to 2.5% by 2027, citing the growing security threats posed by global instability. This was funded by a cut to the foreign aid budget."
Conservative Party leader Kemi Badenoch supported Starmerʼs decision and the Liberal
Democrats also stated an intention to reach 2.5% in their 2024 manifesto.
All three of the main parties are now committed to making the most of Brexit and not trying to
"reverse it with a second referendum, which had been the Liberal Democrats and Labour Partyʼs"
position in the 2019 General Election.
Both the Labour and Conservative Party have made it a priority to tackle illegal immigration and
"change the UKʼs immigration system, with Starmer shifting to the right on immigration since becoming Prime Minister."
This can be seen in the February 2025 decision to remove the path to British citizenship for
"refugees who enter the UK illegally, as well as Starmerʼs major policy announcements to shift the party to the right on immigration in May 2025, where Starmer said Britain had become an “island of strangersˮ."
These included doubling the residency requirement for permanent settlement from five to
"ten years, raising English proficiency standards and restricting visas for care workers."
Against: Arguments That The Foreign and Immigration Policies Of The Main
Parties Are More Dissimilar Than Similar
"Whilst all of the parties do now accept Brexit, the Conservative Party continues to be much"
"more supportive of a hard Brexit than the Labour Party, which was forced to go through with Brexit due to their failure in the 2019 election, and the Liberal Democrats who retain strong pro- European attitudes within the party and their voters."
"In early 2025, Lib Dem leader Ed Davey urged Starmer to start talks on a new customs"
union with the European Union.
"There is also a key difference between the parties in relation to immigration policy, particularly"
the former Conservative governmentʼs Rwanda immigration plan.
The Conservative Party finally formalised its Rwanda immigration policy by passing the
Safety of Rwanda  Asylum and Immigration) Act in April 2024. The Act allowed for the deportation of asylum seekers who enter the UK illegally to Rwanda for processing of their asylum cases.
It represents a very strong stance against immigration and illegal immigration in
particular and was introduced despite the extremely high cost and strong criticisms from human rights groups that Rwanda was a safe country and that the asylum process would ensure fair and humane treatment.
"The cost included an initial payment to Rwanda of £290M and an additional £11,000"
"per asylum seeker for flights, and nearly £151,000 per person for processing and integration over five years."
"Whilst the Labour Party is certainly not strongly supportive of immigration, they differ"
significantly from the Conservativesʼ in their approach to doing so.
They strongly opposed the Conservative Partyʼs policy of handling the claims of asylum
seekers in Rwanda. They see the approach as inhumane and a waste of money and are set to repeal the Act in 2025.
"Instead, they focus on making the asylum system work and processing claims quickly,"
"including through establishing a ""returns-and-enforcement unit"" aimed at swiftly removing failed asylum seekers and foreign national offenders."
The Liberal Democratsʼ 2024 manifesto didnʼt have such a strong focus on bringing down
"immigration numbers, but did like Labourʼs focus on making the asylum system work and opposed the Rwanda scheme."
Judgement
"Overall, the policies of the Labour, Liberal Democrat and Conservative parties on foreign policy"
"are rather similar, with all parties demonstrating a strong commitment to defence spending, Ukraine and no party supporting rejoining the EU."
"They are also increasingly similar in relation to immigration, due to the Labour Party shift to the"
right on immigration since coming to power in the 2024 election.
Overall Argument
"In conclusion, there are some clear differences between the policies of the main parties in"
relation to nationalisation and policy towards the unions.
"These are certainly significant, however they are outweighed by the agreements between the"
"parties on the majority of economic policy, law and order policy, foreign policy and increasingly immigration policy."
"Overall, therefore, the policies of the main are slightly more similar than they are dissimilar."
Other Possible Essay Questions To Practice Adapting
This Plan To Answer
Evaluate the view that the Labour and Conservative Parties are presenting fundamentally
different visions to the public.  30
Evaluate the view that Labour Party policy is more radical than that of the Conservative Party.
30
Follow Politics Explained For More Help With Your Politics A Level
Website → https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/
Instagram → https://www.instagram.com/polexplained/
YouTube  →  https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCQ1FvoFVL4fGJkx6dup3O-w
Twitter → https://twitter.com/Pol_Explain
