Evaluate The Argument That Direct Democracy Is Superior To Representative Democracy (30) - Politics Explained Essay Plan

Introduction
Key Definitions
"In this essay, the analysis of ‘direct democracyʼ will largely focus on referendums, as this is the most important use of direct democracy in the UK.

Paragraph One     Involving The People In Decision Making
For: Direct Democracy Directly Involves The People In Decision Making
"Direct democracy can be seen as a superior system to representative democracy because it directly involves the people in decision making, which gives them real power in democracy and prevents their wishes being ignored by representatives."
Not only does this better fulfil the central purpose of democracy (rule by the people) more
"effectively than representative democracy, it also encourages participation in politics as the"
population is confident their vote will matter in influencing the outcome of a referendum.
"This can be seen in recent referendums in the UK, which have given the people decision"
"making power over key constitutional issues and engaged voters in the process, whilst also increasing political awareness."
The Scottish Independence referendum in 2014 was praised for giving an opportunity to air
"a wide range of issues related to independence, such as the impact on the economy and the future of Trident. There was a very high turnout at 84.6%, including many 16 and 17 years olds who were able to vote."
Brexit also had a relatively high turnout of 72.2%. This reflected the fact that many who
"were disillusioned with the traditional political process voted and felt like they were able to have a say on important issues. The referendum also educated many citizens on the impact of the EU on the British political system, including in relation to questions of sovereignty and trade."
This compares with UK General Election turnouts in the 21st century. Turnout in the
"2019 general election was around 68%, which is higher than the 2001 general election turnout of 58% but is still a great deal less than the average between 1945 and 1997, which was 76%."
"This can also be seen in citizenʼs assemblies in the UK, which can be seen as an important"
check on Parliament as the sole site of decision making power in UK democracy.
"In 2019, the UK Parliament commissioned the Climate Assembly UK to explore public"
opinions on achieving the goal of reaching net zero greenhouse gas emissions by 2050.
The assembly consisted of 108 members who were selected through a process known
"as sortition to ensure that they collectively mirrored the broader public in terms of age, gender, ethnicity, educational level, and geography (whether they lived in urban or rural areas), as well as their level of concern about climate change."
The assembly produced a detailed report with recommendations across various policy
"areas. Some of these recommendations have been reflected in government policy, such as advancing the ban on the sale of new petrol and diesel cars and increasing the capacity for renewable energy."
Against: The Public Are Open To Manipulation And Representative Democracy
Is Practical
"Whilst direct democracy does directly involve the people in decision making, it also leaves them open to manipulation by the cleverest and most articulate speakers (known in Ancient Greece  as demagogues) who are able to swing public opinion in their direction."
"In the 2016 EU referendum, for example, the Leave campaign lied a number of times, which"
"may have played an important role in winning them the referendum. In particular, the"
"campaign, but on the side of the bus the misleading claim ‘We send the EU £350 million a week, letʼs fund our NHS insteadʼ."
By contrast a key benefit of representative democracy is that key decisions are made by
"professional representatives who are supposed to be knowledgable and focus on politics as their full time job. As a consequence, they are less likely to be manipulated."
"Whilst direct democracy can be beneficial in infrequent referendums, it can also be argued that"
"using it all the time would be impractical in large, heavily populated modern states which often require quick decision making, such as responding to the COVID 19 pandemic and other emergencies."
"Further, MPs can seek to implement some direct democracy in how they represent their"
"constituents, therefore ensuring they listen to their constituents without the whole system being based on direct democracy."
"For example, Reform UK MP for Great Yarmouth, Rupert Lowe, voted in favour of the"
landmark Terminally Ill Adults  End of Life) Bill 2024 after hosting a mini-referendum in his
constituency.
He promised to vote according to the majority of the wishes of people in his
"constituency, after 75% of 1181 constituents voted in favour of assisted dying in a poll. He cited wanting to consult his constituents and hand them the power as the reason to"
do so.
Judgement
"Overall, direct democracy is superior to representative democracy as it directly involves the people in decision making, therefore encouraging participation and fulfilling the key purpose of democracy; to give power to the people, which is important even if the people are sometimes misguided."
"This is not to say it should entirely replace representative democracy, however, as this"
"would be impractical. Instead, it should be used for key constitutional decisions."
Paragraph Two     Representing The Whole Of The Population
For: Direct Democracy Gives Equal Weight To All Votes
"One key benefit of direct democracy is that it gives equal weight to all votes. Not only is this fair, it also forces campaigns to seek to appeal to all voters, rather than targeting specific important groups of voters in specific constituencies."
"This contributes to relatively high turnouts in recent referendums, as people can be"
confident their vote will matter.
"This contrasts with representative democracy in the UK, where the First Past The Post electoral"
"system leads to votes being of greatly unequal value. This is not only because a vote in a smaller constituency counts for more than it does in a larger constituency, but also due to the difference between safe and marginal seats."
"In safe seats, many voters have little hope of seeing their favoured candidate winning,"
leading to depressed turnout among certain voters. Little campaign focus by parties is on these constituencies/voters.
"In marginal seats, votes matter a lot more, leading to higher turnout. A great deal of"
campaign focus by parties is on these constituencies/voters.
"A good example of a highly important marginal seat is Thanet South, Kent, which has"
been won by the winning party at every General Election since its creation.
Against: Tyranny Of The Majority
"Whilst direct democracy does give equal weight to all votes, a key disadvantage of direct"
democracy is that it leads to a ‘tyranny of the majorityʼ.
"As direct democracy is a majoritarian system, where if over 50% of the population vote for"
"something then this gets introduced, it can be seen as disregarding the viewpoints of those who arenʼt part of the majority."
This has the potential to threaten those who are in the minority and fail to represent
them politically.
"For example, if turnout is taken into account, less than half of the population voted to leave"
"the EU in the EU referendum, however since the referendum the Conservative government pursued and negotiated a hard Brexit which can be seen as disregarding the views of those who voted Remain, who supported a softer Brexit once it was voted for."
"Representative democracy has much less chance of leading to ‘tyranny of the majorityʼ, as"
minority groups will have representation in Parliament and will have professional politicians who can work on their behalf.
Representative democracy therefore leads to more of a pluralist democracy in which the
"government makes decisions as a result of the interplay of various ideas and contrasting arguments from competing groups and organisations, rather than simply implementing the will of the majority."
Judgement
"Overall, though direct democracy certainly is more effective in equally representing each vote,"
representative democracy is superior in terms of representing the whole of the population as is
prevents the tyranny of the majority and promotes a pluralist democracy.
Paragraph Three     How Effective Is Representative Democracy
Against: Representative Democracy Allows For Accountability And Effective
Representation
It can be argued that representative democracy is superior to direct democracy as the former
allows for accountability and effective representation.
"In a representative democracy, elections are held on a regular basis, which allows the public to"
hold their representatives to account and vote them out if they donʼt think they have done a god job.
This leads to MPs putting great emphasis on representing their constituencies effectively.
"MPs handle correspondence from their constituents, address problems their constituents have and hold weekly constituency surgeries. They also seek to represent their interests effectively in Parliament."
"On December 5, 2023, 22 Conservative MPs supported a Labour amendment aimed at"
"speeding up compensation for victims of the infected blood scandal, rebelling against a 3 line conservative whip to do so."
"The amendment, which was successfully passed by a narrow majority, called for the"
establishment of a body to administer compensation within three months of passing the Victims and Prisoners Bill.
This is a good example of the strong MP-constituency link and local representation
"under FPTP, as the rebels were influenced by strong local movements and victims of the scandal in their constituency."
"For example, Conservative MP Caroline Nokes rebelled to represent the local"
movement for greater compensation and the number of victims affected in her
Romsey and Southampton North Constituency.
"Further, representative democracy can be argued to lead to effective governance and"
"representation, as MPs act as trustees rather than simply delegates."
Edmund Burke introduced the idea that MPs shouldnʼt simply follow exactly what their
"constituents want them to do, but exercise their own professional judgement when making decisions in the public interest."
"This judgement can be seen in the fact that since the 2019 UK general election, two"
"Members of Parliament have defected from the Conservatives to Labour, each citing"
significant concerns with the Conservative Party's direction and policies as their reasons for the switch.
"Dan Poulter announced his defection to Labour in April 2024. Poulter, who also works"
"part-time as a mental health doctor, cited his firsthand experiences with the overstretched NHS and his inability to reconcile these experiences with the Conservative Party's policies as key reasons for his switch."
"It can be argued that this shows the benefit of representative democracy, as MPs are"
able to use their judgement and respond to events in whatever way they think is best for their constituents.
For: In Representative Democracy Politicians Follow Their Own Interests
"On the other hand, it can be argued that direct democracy is superior to representative democracy, as the latter fails to deliver effective representation in practice."
"Whilst politicians are supposed to, and claim to, serve in the interests of their constituents, in"
reality they often make decisions that are in their own interests.
MPs rely on their parties to gain power and are whipped heavily by them to vote with the
"party in Parliament. If they fail to do so, they have little chance of climbing the party ladder and gaining more power by entering the cabinet. As a consequence, the rarely vote against the party line."
"Further, many MPs have second jobs and therefore donʼt devote their whole attention to"
representing the public. The Guardian reported in August 2023 that MPs were paid £10
million from second jobs and freelance work in 2022/23.
"Examples include former Chancellor Sajid Javid, who is taking a £300,000 a year role as"
"an adviser to the Jersey-based investment firm Centricus Partners and Boris Johnson, who made £4.8M from speaking opportunities and consulting among other things."
Polling conducted by YouGov for Sky in 2024 shows that distrust of politicians has declined
"since the 2019 election. 49% of respondents say they ""almost never"" trust the British government to place the needs of the nation above the interests of their own party, up from 26% in  2019."
This increase is likely driven by the manifold scandals that have occurred since the 2019
"election. Since the 2019 election, there have been 23 by-elections, the majority of which were triggered due to MPs (most of whom Conservative MPs) being forced to resign for breaking the law/severe misconduct issues. In most of these cases, MPs resigned instead of facing a recall petition."
"The Blackpool South By-Election on May 2, 2024  followed the resignation of the"
"Conservative MP Scott Benton, who had been suspended from the Commons for breaching lobbying rules, after being exposed by the Times for offering to leak documents and ask questions for a fake gambling company."
"This distrust has continued following the election of the Labour in the 2024 election,"
"particularly due to the ‘freebiegateʼ scandal in the summer of 2024, when Labour was accused of cronyism due to accepting substantial gifts from donor Lord Alli, who was given a security pass to Downing Street."
"It was accused that Starmer receiving clothing and eyewear valued at over £16,000"
from Alli contributed to this decision to give him access and potentially influence in
the Labour Government.
Direct democracy can therefore be seen as superior to representative democracy in practice as
there is no possibility for the views and wishes of the public to be ignored or manipulated to serve the interests of professional politicians.
"The EU referendum, for example, was voted for by a majority of voters despite over 75% of"
Parliament supporting Remain.
Judgement
"Overall, though in theory representative democracy offers effective representation through the"
"Burkean model of representation, in practice this is often limited as MPs make decisions in their"
own interests. Direct democracy is therefore superior.
Overall Argument
"In conclusion, representative democracy is certainly the more practical system in the modern"
"day and shouldnʼt be entirely replaced with direct democracy. It is flawed, however, and fails to"
deliver effective representation.
Direct democracy is superior as it directly involves the people in decision making and gives
"equal weight to all votes. As a consequence, there should be a greater use of referendums on key political issues in order to supplement and improve representative democracy."
Other Possible Essay Questions To Practice Adapting
This Plan To Answer
Evaluate the argument that there should be greater use of direct democracy in the UK  30
Follow Politics Explained For More Help With Your Politics A Level
Website → https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/
Instagram → https://www.instagram.com/polexplained/
YouTube   →   https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCQ1FvoFVL4fGJkx6dup3O-w
Twitter → https://twitter.com/Pol_Explain
