Evaluate The View That Pressure
Groups Are Successful Due To Their Ability To Generate Mass Support. (30) Politics Explained Essay Plan
Topic        1. Democracy and Participation
Structure    Three paragraphs with for/against and an overall judgement within each
This Essay Plan Is Part Of A Package Of Essay Plans Covering The UK Politics Part Of The Politics
"A Level Course For The Edexcel Exam Board, Whilst Also Being Very Useful For The AQA Exam Board. It Can Be Purchased Here    https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/"
Keep In Mind       These are long plans as theyʼre intended to be revised from to cover the key
"content you need to know for the exam. In the exam, you would need to adapt them for the specific question you are asked and you certainly wouldnʼt need to include everything, especially not all of the examples. The judgements are also subjective and you donʼt have to agree with them!"
Introduction
Key Definitions
Pressure groups are groups that seek to influence politics in order to achieve particular goals.
"They donʼt seek political office, but seek to change policy through influencing public opinion, parliament and the government"
Paragraph One     Ability To Generate Mass Support
For: Arguments That Generating Mass Support Is Highly Important To Pressure
Group Success
"Generating and proving mass support around a particular issue is highly important to the success of pressure groups, especially for outsider groups. The government is much more likely to change policy if it is clear there is support from large sections of the population, as not doing so may alienate voters at the next election."
This can be seen in the success of the 2020 campaign to extend free school meals to
"children during the school holidays, led by footballer Marcus Rashford. The campaign effectively used social media, traditional media and e-petitions to generate a social movement and demonstrate public support, which made the government u-turn and accept the groupʼs demands on 16 June 2020."
This can also be seen in the success of protests calling for a ceasefire in Gaza that took
"place consistently in London throughout 2024, with over 100,000 attendees."
The public pressure and anger demonstrated by this social movement played a key
role in the Labour Governmentʼs decision in September 2024 to suspend some of its
arms export licences to Israel.
"This contrasts with the lack of success of the Just Stop Oil movement, which gained a lot of"
"media attention in 2022 due to disruptive public demonstrations, including blocking roads and stopping Premier League football matches. This alienated a lot of the public to their cause of ending all new licences for the production of fossil fuels in the UK and made it easier for Sunak to announce in July 2023 that he was going to grant 100 new North Sea oil"
and gas licences.
This shows how disruptive outsider methods can be ineffective if they have limited
government support and alienate the public to their cause.
"For some pressure groups with hard to reach goals, generating mass support and media"
"attention may be considered success in itself, as it makes policy change more likely in the"
future.
Mass support can also be important to pressure group success as it can lead to large
"memberships that pay subscriptions, therefore allowing pressure groups to run offices, pay staff and organise publicity. The size of membership can also be significant in persuading the government that it represents a significant portion of the population."
"For example, the RSPCA employs around 1600 people, supported by thousands of"
volunteers and can afford to spend a lot on advertising.
"For trade unions and other sectional groups, a bigger membership that is more important to"
the economy will have a higher likelihood of influencing policy through industrial action.
Against: Counterarguments To The Importance Of Mass Support For Pressure
Groups
"On the other hand, it is often still very difficult for pressure groups to get the government to change policy even if they have significant public support. Changing policy due to pressure groups would lead to the government admitting they were wrong, which they are reluctant to do, especially on major policy issues that may be key to their ideology/legitimacy among other groups  of  voters."
"The major anti-Iraq War protests in 2003, arranged by the Stop the War Coalition, and the"
"2019 Peopleʼs Vote march for a second referendum on Brexit both had over 700,000 participants but failed to change government policy."
Government u-turns are also more likely if the government is weak and has a small majority.
"If the government has a large majority and significant public support overall, they will be less threatened by some public opposition/loss of parliamentary support."
Having mass public support must also be combined with effective strategy and leadership in
"order to be successful, including having a thought-out, attainable goal."
The ‘Occupy Londonʼ movement in 2011 is key proof of this. The anti-capitalist movement
"gained significant support from certain sections of the population and was part of a wider global movement, but failed due to having the unattainable goal of overthrowing capitalism and lacking a figurehead to represent the movement effectively."
Judgement
"Overall, generating mass support is the most important factor in the success of outsider pressure groups whoʼs goals arenʼt aligned with government attitudes.  Mass support must nonetheless be combined with effective leadership and strategy to be successful."
Paragraph Two    Government Attitudes (Being An Insider Group)
For: Arguments That Pressure Group Success Is Highly Dependent On
Government Attitudes And Being An Insider Group
"Whilst public support plays a role, it can be argued that being an insider pressure group that"
aligns with government attitudes and has important contacts is more important to pressure group  success.
"Insider pressure groups rely on close contacts with ministers, members of parliament and civil"
"servants to achieve their aims. Some have close links with relevant government departments and most insider groups' objectives are generally in line with the views of the government, making it more likely for them to be listened to."
"LGBT  Rights Pressure Group Stonewall, for example, was primarily an insider pressure"
"group when New  Labour were in power, using lobbying and playing a key role in policy formulation to achieve their aims. As a result, they had important successes including equalising the age of consent for gay and straight individuals to 16 years old as part of the Sexual Offences Act 2000, for which the Parliaments Acts 1911 and 1949 had to be invoked"
to overrule House of Lords opposition.
"The National Farmersʼ Union, for example, had close links with the Department of"
"Environment, Food and Rural Affairs DEFRA under the Conservative Party and was able to provide the department with specific expertise and advice. Itʼs influence was based on the importance of farmers to the UK economy."
They had a particular success in 2013 when they helped to bring about a badger cull to
"control the spread of bovine tuberculosis to farm animals, despite pressure groups supporting animal welfare (such as the Badger Trust and Royal Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals) opposing it."
"More recently, in early 2024 Prime Minister Rishi Sunak attended their annual"
"conference and pledged to protect British Farming in the agricultural market - leading to the UK suspending their trade talks with Canada after they refused to loosen food standards. This benefited the 55,000 farmers the union represents."
The success of these insider groups contrasts with their failure once the government changed
and they were no longer insider groups.
"When Stonewall became an outsider group under Sunakʼs Conservative government, they"
"failed to convince the government to ban trans conversion therapy, despite consistent lobbying. This was due to the fact that the governmentʼs ‘anti-wokeʼ agenda doesnʼt align with Stonewallʼs views and aims."
"Similarly, the National Farmers Unionʼs influence over policy decreased majorly after the"
"election of Labour in 2024, which meant they were no longer an insider group due to Labour performing less well in rural seats and the countryside being less important to their identity as a party."
"In the 2024 Budget, Chancellor Rachel Reeves introduced a tax of 20% on inherited"
"farming assets over £1 million - president of the NFU Tom Bradshaw has criticised this for leading to the ""death of the family farm""."
The government has refused to reverse the policy despite mass protests by farmers
"outside of Westminter, including 13,000 farmers protesting outside of Westminster on the 19th of November 2024, and the NFU organising a “mass lobbyˮ event where"
thousands of farmers met 150 MPs in London.
Against: Counterarguments To The Importance Of Government Attitudes For
Pressure Groups
"On the other hand, the importance of government attitudes shouldnʼt be overstated. Outsider groups can have significant success even when the government isnʼt aligned with their policies, whilst insider groups are very dependent on their contacts with the government of the day."
The fact that government changes can result in their ability to influence policy disappearing
overnight could also be used to suggest that government attitudes only result in temporary influence and dependence.
"Further, whilst insider pressure groups do have an impact, the government still ultimately makes"
"the final decision on policy and is less likely to be influenced by insider lobbying on issues that differ significantly from its existing policy programme, and would therefore constitute a significant change."
"For example, Women Against State Pension Inequality  WASPI  failed to convince the"
"Labour Government to compensate the 3.6 million women affected by the poorly communicated change to the womenʼs state pension age that began in 2010, despite the fact that Chancellor Rachel Reeves had previously publicly supported their cause."
"Despite campaigning through demonstrations and e-petitions, the Labour Government"
"rejected compensation in December 2024, largely due to the fact that it would cost over"
£10bn and this wasnʼt aligned with the governmentʼs goals of reducing the deficit and promoting growth.
Judgement
"Overall, government attitudes are highly important to the success of pressure groups. Insider pressure groups can have major influence over policy, whilst outsider pressure groups struggle to have success when their cause isnʼt aligned with government attitudes. For insider pressure groups, the ability to gain mass public support is therefore much less important than it is for outsider  pressure  groups."
Paragraph Three     Strategy and Leadership (including methods)
For: Arguments That Pressure Group Success Is Highly Dependent On Strategy
and Leadership
The ability to generate mass support and government attitudes are certainly important factors
"in the impact of pressure groups. In order to have significant success, though, they must be combined with effective strategy and leadership."
"Leadership is highly important to pressure groups, particularly outsider pressure groups"
who use the media and seek to mobilise public opinion behind their cause. A well known personality in particular can be an important figurehead and publicly challenge the government using their notoriety.
"Marcus Rashford, for example, provided clear leadership in the campaign to extend free"
"school meals to children during the school holidays. Not only did he engage with the public on twitter in particular, an open letter he wrote to the government proved decisive in the governmentʼs decision to u-turn on 16 June 2020. Rashford was frequently"
described as providing more effective opposition to the government than Keir Starmer.
Strategy is also central to the success of pressure group campaigns. Key to this is knowing
which ‘access pointsʼ in the political system to target and how to articulate an attainable and popular goal in order to have the most chance of success.
The British Medical Associationʼs success in campaigning for a ban on smoking in cars
"with children is a perfect example of this. The BMA originally campaigned for an outright ban of smoking in cars, regardless of whether passengers were present, however, realising there was insufficient support for this, they switched to campaigning for a ban when children were being carried, allowing them to gain support from Asthma UK."
They used online technology to allow supporters to lobby MPs and then made its case
to the House of Lords. A Labour peer introduced an amendment to the 2014 Children
"and Families Bill, which passed the House of Lords and then the House of Commons and the ban came into force in October 2015."
Another effective method often used by well-funded outsider pressure groups are legal
challenges with the intention of influencing government policy. A key example of this is the pressure group For Women Scotlandʼs successful legal challenge against the Scottish Government in April 2025.
Not only did this get the Supreme Court to reverse the Scottish Governmentʼs decision
"to include transgender people with Gender Recognition Certificates in their definition of ‘sexʼ in the Equality Act, it also got the Supreme Court to explicitly define a ‘womanʼ as based on biological sex in the Equality Act - one of the pressure groupʼs key beliefs and aims."
This also led to the UK government accepting the ruling and the Supreme Courtʼs
"definition of a ‘womanʼ, demonstrating how pressure groups can use judicial review to influence the government and achieve their policy aims."
Against: Counterarguments To The Importance Of Strategy and Leadership For
Pressure Groups
"On the other hand, it can be argued that strategy and leadership are certainly important factors"
"in the success of pressure groups, but they are less important than public support and"
"government attitudes, which are the key determinants of success."
"This can be seen in the failure of Liberty to prevent the Police, Crime, Sentencing and"
"Courts Act from being passed in 2021, which they saw as limiting the right to protest in the UK. Liberty organised widespread protests under the slogan #KillTheBill and is a very experienced organisation, but was nonetheless unable to stop the bill being passed, due to sections of the public opposing disruptive protests by Just Stop Oil which the bill was in response to, and the fact that the government was intent on passing it."
Another example is the fact that the Farmers protests in 2024 and 2025 have failed to
"convince the Labour Government to u-turn on their inheritance tax changes, despite being led by the experience National Farmers Union and having celebrity Jeremy Clarkson as a powerful figurehead."
"Legal challenges are also often unsuccessful. For example, the Countryside Alliance failed to"
reverse government policy when they challenged the ban on fox hunting in the High Court in 2004.
Judgement
"Overall, there is no doubt that strategy and leadership are key to the success of pressure groups. Being able to generate mass support and being aligned with government attitudes are arguably more important to the success of pressure groups, however."
Overall Argument
"In conclusion, it is very difficult to judge which factors are important to the success of pressure"
"groups, particularly as insider pressure groups are unlikely to speak out about their influence."
"Overall, whilst strategy and leadership are certainly important factors in the success of"
"pressure groups, the ability to generate mass support and government attitudes are more"
important.
"For insider pressure groups, government attitudes are more important whilst for outsider"
"pressure groups, the ability to generate mass support is more important."
Other Possible Essay Questions To Practice Adapting
This Plan To Answer
Evaluate the view that government attitudes are the most important factor in the success of
pressure groups  30 .
Evaluate the view that alignment with government attitudes is more important than public
support for the success of pressure groups   30 .
Follow Politics Explained For More Help With Your Politics A Level
Website → https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/
Instagram → https://www.instagram.com/polexplained/
YouTube   →   https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCQ1FvoFVL4fGJkx6dup3O-w
Twitter → https://twitter.com/Pol_Explain
