Evaluate The View That UK Democracy
Is In A Participation Crisis. (30) Politics Explained Essay Plan
Topic        1. Democracy and Participation
Structure    Three paragraphs with for/against and an overall judgement within each
This Essay Plan Is Part Of A Package Of Essay Plans Covering The UK Politics Part Of The Politics
"A Level Course For The Edexcel Exam Board, Whilst Also Being Very Useful For The AQA Exam Board. It Can Be Purchased Here    https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/"
Keep In Mind       These are long plans as theyʼre intended to be revised from to cover the key
"content you need to know for the exam. In the exam, you would need to adapt them for the specific question you are asked and you certainly wouldnʼt need to include everything, especially not all of the examples. The judgements are also subjective and you donʼt have to"
agree with them!
Introduction
Key Definitions
"It has been suggested that UK democracy has a ‘participation crisisʼ, as particularly in the 21st"
"century, there has been declining traditional political involvement."
Paragraph One     Elections and Referendums
For: The UK Does Have A Participation Crisis
Voter turnout in recent UK General Elections has been a great deal less than the average
"between 1945 and 1997, which was 76%."
In the 2024 general election it was just 59.8%.
Turnout is even lower in so-called 'second order' elections and referendums such as those for
devolved bodies and councils.
"For example, turnout in devolved assembly elections is generally low. It was just 63.5% in"
"the 2021 Scottish Parliament elections, the same in the 2022 Northern Irish Assembly elections and 46.6% in the 2021 Senedd elections."
"Low turnout means that governments are elected on a reduced share of the popular vote,"
therefore calling the strength of their democratic mandate into question.
One explanation for lower voter turnout is political apathy; a lack of awareness or interest in
political issues that affect society.
"This is particularly true of younger voters, who are much less likely to vote than the older"
"generation, therefore limiting the responsiveness of political institutions to the interests of"
young people.
Turnout among the 65  age group in 2017 was around 25 percentage points higher than
among 18 24 year olds.
It can be argued that this low turnout is driven by low trust in politicians. Polling conducted by
YouGov for Sky in 2024 shows that distrust of politicians has declined since the 2019 election.
"49% of respondents say they ""almost never"" trust the British government to place the"
"needs of the nation above the interests of their own party, up from 26% in 2019."
This is likely driven by the manifold scandals that have occurred since the 2019 election.
"Since the 2019 election, there have been 23 by-elections, the majority of which were triggered due to MPs (most of whom Conservative MPs) being forced to resign for breaking the law/severe misconduct issues. In most of these cases, MPs resigned instead of facing a recall petition."
"The Wellingborough By-Election on February 15, 2024 followed the recall of Peter Bone"
after he was suspended from Parliament for six weeks due to allegations of bullying and
sexual harassment.
"This distrust continued following the election of the Labour in the 2024 election, particularly"
"due to the ‘freebiegateʼ scandal in the summer of 2024, when Labour was accused of cronyism due to accepting substantial gifts from donor Lord Alli, who was given a security pass to Downing Street."
"It was accused that Starmer receiving clothing and eyewear valued at over £16,000"
from Alli contributed to this decision to give him access and potentially influence in the Labour Government.
Against: The UK Doesnʼt Have A Participation Crisis
The 2014 Scottish independence referendum and the 2016 EU referendum had turnouts of
"84.6% and 72.2% respectively, showing there is still significant engagement surrounding critical issues."
This perhaps suggests that the population is still very engaged on important political issues
"on which they feel they can have significant control, but vote less in elections as they have  a distrust of professional politicians, particularly in light of the 2010 Expenses Scandal. This may continue in the next election in light of Partygate and an increased focus on MPsʼ second jobs."
An alternative viewpoint is the idea of 'hapathy' (happiness and apathy) suggesting people are
generally content and therefore don't need to push for change.
"Counterpoint: This may explain the low voter turnout in the 2001 and 2005 elections, when"
"the UK economy was booming, but not the low turnout in 2010 and 2024."
Judgement
"Overall, though it is clear that participation in elections and referendums has been higher in the"
"past decade that it was in the 2000s, participation is still low and UK democracy arguably does have a participation crisis, as high turnout in elections is key to granting the system legitimacy."
Paragraph Two    Party Membership
For: The UK Does Have A Participation Crisis
"Only 1.6% of the electorate now belongs to a political party, compared to 3.8% in 1983, however"
this differs party-to-party.
"The Conservative Party has an estimated 100,000 members today, a significant drop from"
"an estimated 400,000 in the mid 1990s."
"Less traditional political involvement could be associated with a negative perception of MPs,"
due to various scandals and promises being broken.
Since Keir Starmer became Labour Party leader there has been a drop in membership in the
"party, in part due to a perception that his increasingly centrist policies betray the promises he made in the leadership election."
"The Labour Partyʼs membership has fallen from 500,000 under Corbyn to 370,000 today."
"If one takes a ‘developmentalʼ perspective on democracy, which sees regular active political"
"engagement from the public as key to the successful functioning of democracy, then this lack of party membership can be seen as a major problem for democracy in the UK."
Against: The UK Doesnʼt Have A Participation Crisis
"There was a surge in Labour Party membership in 2015, when Milliband made it possible to join"
"for just 3 pounds, with the party rising to over 500,000 members."
"Following the first Scottish Independence Referendum, membership of the SNP surged and"
"it had over 125,000 members in April 2018, in a country with a population of just 5M."
"In February 2025, Nigel Farage claimed that Reform UK had surpassed 200,000 members"
"and therefore doubled the membership of the Conservative Party, whilst not being far off the membership of the Labour Party."
These examples suggest the public will still use parties as a vehicle for political action if they
are proposing some kind of radical change and donʼt represent the establishment.
"The public want to participate in politics, but their support for the major parties has declined"
and they are therefore engaging in different ways.
"This declining support for major parties can be seen in the 2024 election, when Labour and"
the Conservatives received just 57.4% of the vote.
"Further, the ‘protectiveʼ perspective on democracy suggests that mass political involvement"
"isnʼt necessary for the protection of democracy, just enough to grant the system legitimacy."
Democracy isn't a means of mass participation but a system where a competitive group of
"leaders vie for electoral support in the context of a broader respect for individual freedoms and liberties. As long as these freedoms continue to be respected, then democracy isnʼt in a crisis."
Judgement
"Overall, active political engagement from across the population is arguably important to"
granting UK democracy legitimacy.
There is clearly a lack of active political engagement and affinity with the Labour and
Conservative Parties who are always in government. This undermines democratic legitimacy and contributes to the UKʼs significant participation crisis.
Paragraph Three       Other Methods Of Political Participation
Against: The UK Doesnʼt Have A Participation Crisis
"Pressure group membership in the UK has been on the increase, whilst many young people in"
particular actively engage with politics on social media.
"Many demonstrations have been well attended on issues such as the Iraq war, Brexit, Black"
"Lives Matter and the climate crisis. This direct action has been recognised as a feature of modern politics, indicating that people feel conventional politics has let them down and are turning to new methods of expression."
"Throughout the first half of 2024, there were consistent protests in London and across the"
UK for an immediate ceasefire in Gaza and to put pressure on the Isreali government to end the war.
This has been important in pressuring both the Labour and Conservative parties to
"weaken their support for Israelʼs war, with  the Conservative foreign secretary David Cameron calling for de-escalation in early 2024 and the Labour Government suspending some of its arms export licenses to Israel in September 2024."
"E-petitions on specific political issues regularly receive hundreds of thousands of signatures,"
with 202 petitions debated in the House of Commons in the 2019 2024 Parliament.
The Revoke Article 50 petition of March 2019 received over 6 million signatures.
Following Rachel Reevesʼ announcement in the summer of 2024 that Winter Fuel Payments
"for pensioners would become means-tested, Age UK created an online E Petition urging the government to reverse its decision."
"Since its creation in August 2024, it has received over 590,000 signatures."
"This is a crucial example of the electorate engaging in politics between elections,"
"suggesting that there isnʼt a participation crisis, there is just disengagement with party politics and the two main parties."
For: The UK Does Have A Participation Crisis
"Other forms of political involvement are certainly important, but are arguably less impactful and"
important than voting and party membership.
"Further, it can be argued that e-petitions and other forms of engaging in politics online are a"
form of ‘slacktivismʼ that take little real effort and arenʼt a replacement for traditional forms
of participation.
"For example, on the 24th of November 2024, a petition to call an immediate general"
"election received 2.9 million signatures, and will be debated in Parliament in 2025,"
despite the fact that this is certainly not going to happen and will make little real change.
Voting in elections and party membership are crucial to granting the UKʼs democratic system
"legitimacy, whilst if pressure groups and demonstrations often arenʼt listened to by professional politicians, then this could be seen as undermining UK democracy and showing there is a participation crisis."
Judgement
"Overall, there is clearly political interest and engagement across the population. Rather than in"
"voting or membership of political parties, this is increasingly being manifested in other forms of political participation, suggesting a lack of support for the political system and therefore a participation crisis."
Overall Argument
"Overall, UK democracy is in a participation crisis. There is clearly a lack of support for political"
"parties and the traditional political system, shown clearly in low election turnout in 2024 and low party membership."
This is in large part a consequence of the perception of politicians as out of touch and
unrepresentative and threatens the legitimacy and stability of UK democracy. The UKʼs
participation problem is therefore a crisis.
Other Possible Essay Questions To Practice Adapting
This Plan To Answer
Evaluate the view that declining political involvement undermines UK democracy.  30
Follow Politics Explained For More Help With Your Politics A Level
Website → https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/
Instagram → https://www.instagram.com/polexplained/
YouTube  →  https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCQ1FvoFVL4fGJkx6dup3O-w
Twitter → https://twitter.com/Pol_Explain
