Evaluate The Argument That The FPTP
Electoral System Should Be Scrapped And Replaced With A More Proportional Electoral System. (30) Politics Explained Essay Plan
Topic       2. Electoral Systems
Structure    Three paragraphs with for/against and an overall judgement within each.
This Essay Plan Is Part Of A Package Of Essay Plans Covering The UK Politics Part Of The Politics
"A Level Course For The Edexcel Exam Board, Whilst Also Being Very Useful For The AQA Exam Board. It Can Be Purchased Here    https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/"
Keep In Mind       These are long plans as theyʼre intended to be revised from to cover the key
"content you need to know for the exam. In the exam, you would need to adapt them for the specific question you are asked and you certainly wouldnʼt need to include everything, especially not all of the examples. The judgements are also subjective and you donʼt have to agree with them!"
Introduction
Key Definitions & Info
First Past The Post is the current electoral system used for UK Parliament elections and local
council elections in England and Wales. It is a simple plurality system.
"The system has come under particular scrutiny lately as the Gallagher Index, used to measure"
"proportionality, rated the 2024 General Election the least proportional election since elections in"
the UK began.
Paragraph One      Representation and Proportionality
Arguments That First Past The Post Should Be Scrapped And Replaced
"First Past The Post is very unrepresentative, as it is a simple plurality system that results in"
"elected MPs often lacking majority support in their constituency. This weakens the mandate of each MP, leading to many voters feeling unrepresented and MPs lacking legitimacy."
"In the 2024 election, for example, Labour candidate Terry Jermy was elected in South West"
"Norfolk with just 26.7% of the vote, which is just 15.7% of the constituencyʼs population if"
those who didnʼt vote are also counted.
This lack of representation in constituencies translates to a lack of proportionality at the
"national level, with votes not translated into seats with any real accuracy."
"FPTP results in a ‘winnerʼs bonusʼ, where the party with the most votes, even when they"
"donʼt have a majority, hugely benefits and enjoys a share of the seats in excess of the share of the vote it receives. This is because this party will often win a lot of the marginal seats between the two main parties, which usually determine the election outcome."
"In the 2024 election, the Labour Party won 63% of the seats with just 33.7% of the vote,"
despite winning just 202 seats with 32.1% of the vote in 2019.
FPTP favours parties with geographically concentrated support and therefore massively
under-represents the majority of minor parties.
"In 2024, Reform UK received 14.3% of the vote, but just 5 seats  0.8% of the seats)."
"Other electoral systems are much more proportional. For example, Pressure group"
"Make Votes Matter modelled how the 2024 election result would have been different if voters had voted in the same way under different, more proportional electoral systems."
"Under AMS, Reform wouldʼve received 91 seats and under STV Reform wouldʼve"
received 71 seats.
"In 2019, the Liberal Democrats won 11.5% of the vote but just 11/650 seats 1.7% of the"
"seats). If the system was fully proportional, they wouldʼve won 75 seats."
"In 2024, the Lib Dems won a very similar share of the vote 12.2% but just 72 seats."
This demonstrates how the results of FPTP have little correlation with vote shares.
Arguments That First Past The Post Shouldnʼt Be Scrapped And Replaced
"On the other hand, FPTP can be seen as representative as it has a strong MP Constituency"
Link.
"The relatively small size of most FPTP constituencies, and the fact that a single MP is"
"responsible for those who live within the constituency, result in effective representation of local interests and a strong link between the constituency and MP."
A study by the House of Commons found that MPs handle approximately 300 500
"emails per week, whilst it is estimated that MPs allocate around 40% of their time to constituency matters, including surgeries and casework."
"On December 5, 2023, 22 Conservative MPs supported a Labour amendment aimed at"
"speeding up compensation for victims of the infected blood scandal, rebelling against a 3 line conservative whip to do so. The amendment, which was successfully passed by a narrow majority, called for the establishment of a body to administer compensation within three months of passing the Victims and Prisoners Bill."
This is a good example of the strong MP-constituency link and local representation
"under FPTP, as the rebels were influenced by strong local movements and victims of the scandal in their constituency."
"For example, Conservative MP Caroline Nokes rebelled to represent the local movement"
for greater compensation and the number of victims affected in her Romsey and Southampton North Constituency.
"Further, the fact that it under-represents minor parties leads to the exclusion of extremist"
"parties, who are very unlikely to have success under FPTP."
"In 2010, for example, the extreme right wing British National Party  BNP  won 2% of the"
"national vote, but didnʼt finish higher than 3rd in any constituency."
"In the 2009 European parliament elections, which used a proportional Closed Party List"
"system, by contrast, they won 6.2% of votes and 2 seats."
Judgement
"Overall, whilst the MP-constituency link is certainly a benefit of First Past The Post that"
"improves representation, FPTP is on the whole a very unrepresentative system that is unfair to minority parties in particular."
As representation/proportionality is arguably the key criteria according which to judge electoral
"systems, this leads to a persuasive argument that FPTP should be scrapped."
Paragraph Two     Voter Choice
Arguments That First Past The Post Should Be Scrapped And Replaced
Voter choice is very limited under FPTP. Voters only get one vote and can therefore only vote
"for one party, preventing them from showing their political preferences more fully."
"This contrasts with the Additional Member System when voters get 2 votes, one for a party"
and one for a constituency member. They can therefore vote for a ‘split-ticketʼ if they wish.
This leads to votes for the party that doesnʼt win in a constituency being effectively ‘wastedʼ
"and to many voters resorting to ‘tactical votingʼ, which is where voters select a different party to their preferred party (which has little chance of winning in their constituency) to try and prevent their least favourite party from winning in their constituency."
Pressure Group MakeVotesMatter reported that in 2024 1/5 voters intended to vote
"tactically and 58% of those who voted ended up with an MP they didnʼt vote for, the highest since WWII."
"In a more proportional system, such as STV where voters rank their preferences,"
tactical voting isnʼt a problem.
Votes are also of greatly unequal value. Not only because a vote in a smaller constituency
"counts for more than it does in a larger constituency, but also due to the difference between safe and marginal seats."
"In safe seats, many voters have little hope of seeing their favoured candidate winning,"
leading to depressed turnout among certain voters. Little campaign focus by parties is
on these constituencies/voters.
"Manchester Rusholme, for example, was won by Labour in 2024 with 51.9.3% of the"
vote on a turnout of just 40%.
"In marginal seats, votes matter a lot more, leading to higher turnout. A great deal of"
campaign focus by parties is on these constituencies/voters.
"A good example of a highly important marginal seat is Thanet South, Kent, which"
has been won by the winning party at every General Election since its creation.
Arguments That First Past The Post Shouldnʼt Be Scrapped And Replaced
"Whilst FPTP may have limited voter choice, it is extremely easy to use for voters, who only have"
to select one candidate/party. The result is also usually known early in the morning after polling
"day and the government is quickly formed, with a swift and orderly transfer of power."
"In 2024, the first constituency result  Sunderland South) was announced at 23 15 on the day"
"of the election, the result was clear by the early hours of the next morning and Starmer arrived at Downing Street as the new Prime Minister at 12 40pm the day after the election."
"The simplicity and familiarity of FPTP can be seen as key factors in the public support for it, as"
"shown in the 2011 Alternative Vote  AV  referendum, in which 68% of those who voted voted"
"against changing the electoral system, on a 42% turnout."
"This rejected should be seen in part as a protest vote against the Liberal Democrats,"
though.
More complicated electoral systems can confuse voters and lead to ‘donkey votingʼ.
"For example in the 2019 local elections in Northern Ireland, In District Electoral Areas where"
"there were two candidates running from the same party, the candidate whose surname was first alphabetically was elected 85% of the time, whilst the second candidate on the ballot paper was elected only 54% of the time."
Judgement
"Overall, a more proportional electoral system than FPTP would certainly lead to greater voter"
"choice than under FPTP, where it is limited due to it being a simple plurality system."
"This being said, voters favour FPTP as it is simple to use. This support can be seen in the 2011"
"AV referendum. On the basis of voter choice alone, therefore, FPTP shouldnʼt be scrapped."
Paragraph Three     Type Of Government Created
Arguments That First Past The Post Shouldnʼt Be Scrapped And Replaced
The key benefit of First Past The Post that is often cited is that it produces strong single-party governments that are able to pass laws effectively.
These governments have a strong mandate and are able to carry out their programme of
government and bring about effective change.
"In the 1980s, this enabled Thatcher to bring about widespread changes to the economy,"
whilst in 1997 it gave Blairʼs government the mandate to carry out extensive
constitutional reforms.
"In 2024, Starmerʼs Labour Party won a 174 seat majority with just 33.7% of the popular"
"vote, but there was limited public outrage and questioning of his mandate."
"These government are also elected very quickly, with the result usually known early in the"
morning after polling day and the government formed within 24 hours.
This contrasts with more proportional electoral systems which are more prone to causing
"minority/coalition governments, which can be seen as weak as they are more likely to lead to compromised/watered down policies and struggle to implement significant changes."
This can be seen in the breakdown of the Scottish government in April 2024. First Minister
Humza Youssaf decided to end the coalition agreements after the Greens strongly criticised the SNP for abandoning a key climate change target and pausing the prescription of  puberty blockers to new patients at Scotland's only gender services clinic for young people.
"As a result, the Greens supported a no confidence motion against Yousaf, who soon"
after resigned as party leader and First Minister.
This shows a key disadvantage of the Additional Member System  AMS ; that it routinely
leads to coalition and minority governments which are weak and vulnerable to
instability.
Arguments That First Past The Post Should Be Scrapped And Replaced
"On the other hand, recently FPTP has led to some weak governments that havenʼt had"
majorities. In particular the 2010 Lib Dem-Conservative coalition and the Confidence and Supply Agreement between the Conservatives and the DUP following the 2017 election.
"Further, even though FPTP often leads to strong governments, this can be seen as a"
drawback as these governments donʼt have majority support from the population that could grant legitimacy to this strength.
"Coalitions also shouldnʼt necessarily be seen as negative. Scottish governments, for example,"
"have often been coalitions/minority governments, but they have been stable and able to pass significant changes."
"Compromise can be seen as an advantage, as it leads to more considered, representative"
policies.
Judgement
"Overall, the fact that FPTP leads to strong, majority governments shouldnʼt necessarily be seen as an advantage. These governments usually arenʼt supported by a majority of the population and therefore push major policy changes through parliament without legitimacy."
"Whilst more proportional systems are more likely to lead to coalition governments, these"
"government are more representative and can be both stable and effective, as Scottish"
governments elected by AMS show.
Overall Argument
"Overall, First Past The Post should be scrapped and replaced with a more proportional electoral"
"system. Whilst it is true that FPTP is easy and simple to use for voters, this results in limited"
voter choice and many votes being wasted.
The key reason why FPTP should be scrapped is that it is unrepresentative. Representation is
the key function of a democratic electoral system and FPTP not only under-represents minor
"parties with significant support, but also over-represents the winning party, which is able to use"
its majority to introduce major changes without the legitimacy to do so.
A more proportional voting system such as AMS strikes a much more effective balance. It is
"relatively proportional and offers voters significant voter choice, whilst not being too confusing for voters and still leading to stable and effective governments."
Other Possible Essay Questions To Practice Adapting
This Plan To Answer
Evaluate the view that the emergence of multiple parties in the UK means that the Westminster
electoral system must be changed. 30
Follow Politics Explained For More Help With Your Politics A Level
Website → https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/
Instagram → https://www.instagram.com/polexplained/
YouTube  →  https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCQ1FvoFVL4fGJkx6dup3O-w
Twitter → https://twitter.com/Pol_Explain
