Evaluate The View That The Influence
Of The Media In Politics Is Exaggerated. (30) - Politics Explained Essay Plan
Topic      4. Voting Behaviour and The Media
Structure    Three paragraphs with for/against and an overall judgement within each
This Essay Plan Is Part Of A Package Of Essay Plans Covering The UK Politics Part Of The Politics
"A Level Course For The Edexcel Exam Board, Whilst Also Being Very Useful For The AQA Exam Board. It Can Be Purchased Here    https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/"
Keep In Mind       These are long plans as theyʼre intended to be revised from to cover the key
"content you need to know for the exam. In the exam, you would need to adapt them for the specific question you are asked and you certainly wouldnʼt need to include everything, especially not all of the examples. The judgements are also subjective and you donʼt have to agree with them!"
Introduction
Key Definitions
Paragraph One     Influence Of The Media On Elections
For: Arguments That The Influence Of The Media Is Significant
"During elections, most newspapers come out strongly in favour of a political party and"
"effectively campaign for one party. This can be seen as important in convincing their millions of readers to vote for a particular party. The Conservatives won 4 elections from 2010 2019 with the majority support of the press, but lost in 2024 after losing the support of a majority of the press, including the Sun, Financial Times and Sunday Times."
"On the night before the 2017 general election, the Daily Mail published a front page with the"
"headline ‘Corbinʼ and attacked Jeremy Corbyn and the Labour Party, imploring voters not to vote Labour."
"In 2019, the Tories partly launched their manifesto in the Telegraph newspaper and in 2024,"
the Telegraph published a tactical voting guide to try and stop Starmer winning a landslide majority.
TV debates and interviews are key moments in campaigns and are watched by millions of
voters.
"In 2017, Theresa May refusing to take part in a head on head TV debate with Corbyn made"
her look weak in the eyes of voters and contributed to her unpopularity.
The media is key to how voters consume political information and form opinions and can
therefore be seen as very important to election outcomes.
"The media can also be important in setting the agenda of elections, such as “the Brexit"
electionˮ in 2019.
Key moments during campaigns can go viral on social media and shape votersʼ perceptions of
parties and leaders.
"In 2019, significant viral events were Jacob Rees Moggʼs comments on the Grenfell fire"
"which were condemned by many and coverage of a boy with pneumonia who had to sleep on the floor of a hospital. This being said, the Conservatives still comfortably won the election."
"In the 2024 election, news of Rishi Sunak leaving D Day commemorations early spread very"
"quickly on social media, greatly harming the Toriesʼ popularity."
"Parties try to control their media appearance as much as possible during elections, sometimes"
avoiding tough interviews and having very stage managed performances and photo opportunities. This shows that political parties see the influence of the media on election outcomes as potentially highly significant.
"In 2019, Johnson refused to be interviewed by Andrew Neil, fearing the impact a mishap"
could have on the campaign.
Against: Arguments That The Influence Of The Media Is Insignificant
The impact of the media during elections can be overstated. Voters donʼt simply follow what the
"media says but form their own opinions, whilst many have strong allegiances to parties and are highly unlikely to be swayed by anything the media does during elections."
For example YouGov polling revealed that 30% of Sun readers and 39% of FT readers voted
"for the Labour Party in the 2017 election, despite both papers backing the Tories."
Pre-election polling by Best For Britain indicated that a majority of readers of prominent
right wing leaning newspapers intended to vote for the Labour Party.
"Specifically, the polling reveals that 52% of The Daily Mail's readership and 47% of the"
"Telegraphʼs readership, both of which are key conservative newspapers, intended to support Labour in the 2024 election."
"Further, most individuals consume the media and political opinions they already agree with,"
therefore only reinforcing views rather than having much potential to change them. This is
especially true of social media.
Judgement
"Overall, the media without doubt plays an important role in election campaigns, especially since"
"the advent of TV debates in the 2010 election. The influence of the media in elections is exaggerated, though, as the media voters consume doesnʼt simply determine how they vote as is often suggested. Instead, they make up their own mind and sometimes donʼt vote according to the views of the media they consume."
Paragraph Two     Influence Of The Media In Holding The
Government To Account Between Elections
For: Arguments That The Influence Of The Media Is Significant
The media plays a key role in holding the government to account and exposing its failures
between elections.
"The media was crucial in exposing the Partygate scandal, through receiving leaks and"
exposing different parts of the story gradually in order to cause maximum damage to the government and expose them for misleading Parliament. This was crucial in bringing down the Johnson government.
Freedom of information requests by media outlets were also crucial in exposing the
"“freebiegateˮ scandal in the summer of 2024, when they revealed that the Labour leadership accepted substantial gifts from donor Lord Alli, who was given a security pass to Downing Street."
"It was accused that Starmer receiving clothing and eyewear valued at over £16,000"
from Alli contributed to this decision to give him access and potentially influence in the Labour Government.
This exposed an important government scandal and led to low poll ratings for the
government despite them having just won a large majority.
"Ministers are interviewed on the radio and on TV daily, where journalists can question them and"
"expose their failings. This was especially true of the Johnson government, where ministers were asked to defend the indefensible."
A series of disastrous local radio interviews were important in exposing the failure of Liz
"Trussʼ economic policies and showing her unpopularity with the public, consequently"
playing a part in her resignation soon after.
"As parliament was shut down during COVID  19 and news conferences were highly important,"
"the media took on a more important role, becoming the main source of opposition to the government in the way that parliament normally is."
The media can also be an important vehicle for the public and pressure groups to seek to
"influence government policy between elections, through reporting on protests/industrial action and giving pressure group leaders a public platform they can use to influence public opinion"
and put public pressure on the government.
"The Post Office Horizon scandal, which received significant public attention in 2024, shows"
the crucial role of the media in influencing public opinion and holding politicians accountable between elections.
"The scandal, involving wrongful convictions of numerous Post Office operators based"
"on flawed software, had received limited coverage under the surface until it was thrust"
into the limelight by a compelling ITV documentary and subsequent detailed
investigations by BBC's Newsnight.
"This media spotlight escalated public awareness and concern, which in turn pressured"
"politicians to take action. As a result of the programme, the government announced a new and improved compensation scheme for the wrongfully convicted sub- postmasters. This included not only compensations for the financial losses suffered but also for the personal distress and reputational damage."
Against: Arguments That The Influence Of The Media Is Insignificant
"Parliament can be seen as playing a far more important role in holding the government to account than the media, whilst the media often only provides a platform for politicians to scrutinise other politicians."
"For example Question Time, a weekly political programme on the BBC, which includes on its"
panel politicians from different political parties.
"There have been allegations of bias against the BBC from both sides of the political spectrum,"
"with Laura Kuenssberg in particular being accused of spreading fake news, including a false story about labour activists pushing a Conservative Party advisor, and benefitting the Conservative Party."
This can therefore be seen as limiting the extent to which they can effectively hold the
government to account.
"Much of the population pays little attention to politics and political media, especially outside of"
"election campaigns, therefore limiting the impact of the political media."
The ability of the media to hold the government to account is arguably limited by the fact that
"the government seeks to control the news agenda and how it is presented to the public, including through favouring some journalists over others."
"In 2023, UK Home Secretary Suella Braverman made a controversial visit to Rwanda to"
"highlight the government's plans to deport asylum seekers there. Notably, Braverman only invited journalists from right-wing media outlets including the Daily Mail and Telegraph based on how they were expected to report favourably on the policy."
This resulted in headlines that varied significantly in tone and content. The Daily Mail
"ran with a supportive headline like ""Braverman's Bold Step for a Safer Britain,"" whereas The Guardian, which had to rely on second-hand sources, published more critical takes, such as ""Rwanda Plan: A Blow to Refugee Rights?"""
This stark difference in reporting highlights the extent of newspaper bias and alignment
with different parties. The governmentʼs selection of certain news outlets and attempts to manipulate coverage can be seen as limiting the extent to which the media holds the government to account between elections.
Judgement
"Overall, the influence of the media in holding the government to account in between elections"
"isnʼt exaggerated. The media, in particular TV and the radio, plays a crucial role in holding the government to account and played a vital role in bringing down both Boris Johnson and Liz Truss."
Paragraph Three
Democracy
Influence Of The Media In Undermining
For: Arguments That The Influence Of The Media Is Significant
"Large sections of the media present an oversimplified interpretation of political issues and focus too much on leaders, personalities and images rather than policy. This is influenced by the fact they are driven by getting as many clicks as possible."
Newspapers are notoriously partisan and will alter their allegiance in response to changing
circumstances and boosting their circulation figures as much as to any ideological loyalties.
"For example, The Sun began supporting Labour but switched to Conservative in the mid-"
"70s, as Thatcher's approach to Trade Unions was in line with owner Rupert Murdoch's business interests. In the run up to the 1997 election, it switched to Labour, as Blair showed business had nothing to fear under him, but it switched back to the Conservatives in 2010"
after repudiating Brown and back to Labour in 2024.
This can be seen as having a negative impact on democracy because newspaper owners
"canʼt be held to account in the same way politicians can, yet are able to wield significant influence on politics, both in terms of whether politicians are held to account and in terms of how the population votes."
"The Guardian reported in February 2024 that Rupert Murdoch, a media tycoon who"
"controls a vast empire including influential outlets like The Times, The Sun, and Sky News in the UK, met with Prime Minister Rishi Sunak five times over a 12-month period spanning from early 2022  2023."
Such frequent interactions underscore the significant power Murdoch wields within
"the political landscape, with politicians seeking his favour in order to secure favourable  media coverage."
Governments have been increasingly making important policy announcements in TV studios
rather than in the House of Commons and summarising Ministerial speeches in the press before
they're delivered.
This can be seen as detracting from the role of parliament and the House of Commons
"especially, which is elected to perform this role, therefore negatively impacting scrutiny of the   executive."
"In October 2024, the Speaker of the House of Commons, Sir Lindsay Hoyle, criticised the"
"Chancellor Rachel Reeves on the floor of the House, accusing her of prematurely disclosing Budget details to the media through broadcast interviews"
He said it was unacceptable to make major policy announcements to the Press without
first giving the information to MPs via formal ministerial statement.
"Finally, social media in particular can be seen as damaging democracy by allowing for members"
of the public to spread disinformation threaten violence against MPs.
"For example, Elon Musk was criticised in late 2024 for spreading disinformation and hate"
against the Labour government and Home Office Minister Jess Phillips in particular.
"The tech billionaire labelled Phillips as an “evil witchˮ and a “rape genocide apologistˮ,"
calling for her to be jailed. This was due to a dispute over historic grooming cases and
"Muskʼs calls for a national inquiry, despite his limited knowledge of the issue."
Against: Arguments That The Influence Of The Media Is Insignificant
"On the other hand, it can be argued that the media doesnʼt fundamentally undermine"
"democracy, instead it plays a positive role in democracy."
A free media is a vital feature of a healthy democracy and can play an essential role in holding
"governments to account and highlighting key political issues, especially when parliamentary opposition is weak."
"In March 2023, The Telegraph published over 100,000 leaked WhatsApp messages from"
"Matt Hancock, the former UK Health Secretary, which revealed details about the government's handling of the COVID 19 pandemic."
"These messages, given to The Telegraph by journalist Isabel Oakeshott, exposed"
"several controversial decisions and discussions within the government, including the suggestion that face masks were mandated in schools not based on public health advice but rather to avoid political disagreements with Scottish authorities."
The Telegraph's decision to publish these messages demonstrates that right-wing
"media can act independently of the government, prioritising public interest and journalistic integrity over political allegiance. This shows the key democratic role of the media in holding the government accountable, regardless of its political leanings."
"With the growth of social media, the media can now be seen as more democratised, with many"
"more individuals able to have a voice and participate in politics. This limits the influence of biased newspapers, which no longer dominate the publicʼs perception of politics."
Newspaper circulation has declined significantly in recent years as many voters move to
"other forms of media.In 2024 the Daily Mail had a circulation of 736,000, compared to"
1.85M in 2012 and 2.4M in 1997.
TV and radio coverage is less biased than newspapers and therefore doesnʼt seek to shape the
views of voters. The BBC Charter insists upon political neutrality and this is by and large
followed by other channels.
Judgement
"Overall, the role the media plays in undermining democracy isnʼt exaggerated. Newspapers in particular are driven by their own interests rather than holding politicians to account and fail to play the role they should do in upholding democracy."
Overall Argument
"In conclusion, the influence of the media in politics in the UK is somewhat exaggerated. It is"
"exaggerated in terms of how it is sometimes suggested that the media determines how individuals vote, when in reality many voters donʼt vote according to the media they consume."
The influence of the media in holding the government to account between elections and
"undermining democracy, particularly newspapers, isnʼt exaggerated, however. TV, radio and newspapers have played an important role in bringing down two recent Prime Ministers by exposing scandals, whilst newspapers undermine democracy in the UK as they are biased and driven by their own interests."
Other Possible Essay Questions To Practice Adapting
This Plan To Answer
Evaluate the view that the press has little impact on general election results.  30
Evaluate the view that the media plays a limited role in UK politics. 30
Evaluate the view that the role of the media in politics is generally positive. 30
Follow Politics Explained For More Help With Your Politics A Level
Website → https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/
Instagram → https://www.instagram.com/polexplained/
YouTube   →   https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCQ1FvoFVL4fGJkx6dup3O-w
Twitter → https://twitter.com/Pol_Explain
