Evaluate The View That The Funding Of
Political Parties In The UK Should Be Reformed. (30) Politics Explained Essay Plan
Topic      2. Political Parties
Structure    Three paragraphs with for/against and an overall judgement within each
This Essay Plan Is Part Of A Package Of Essay Plans Covering The UK Politics Part Of The Politics
"A Level Course For The Edexcel Exam Board, Whilst Also Being Very Useful For The AQA Exam Board. It Can Be Purchased Here    https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/"
Keep In Mind       These are long plans as theyʼre intended to be revised from to cover the key
"content you need to know for the exam. In the exam, you would need to adapt them for the specific question you are asked and you certainly wouldnʼt need to include everything, especially not all of the examples. The judgements are also subjective and you donʼt have to agree with them!"
Introduction
Key Definitions
One key proposal for reforming party funding in the UK is through making political parties state
"funded, as they are in other Western democracies including Australia, the Netherlands and"
Germany.
This state funding could be based on the number of votes/seats received by a party in the
"previous election, or it could match small donations from members of the public."
Paragraph One   Party Fundingʼs Influence On The Potential For
Corruption And Undue Influence
For: Arguments That Party Funding Should Be Reformed
Donations from rich individuals and businesses are a key source of party funding in the UK.
"This is particularly true of the Conservative Party, which receives the majority of its funds from donations, but is also important for the Labour Party, especially now that Starmer is moving the party to the centre ground."
"In 2023, the Conservative Party received £44.5M from donations."
£20M of the The Conservative Partyʼs £44.5M received in 2023 came from two
"sources. The first was from David Sainsburyʼs cousin and Tory Peer John Sainsbury, who left £10M to the Conservative Party in his will. The second was from Frank Hester, who gave £5m personally and another £5m through his firm, The Phoenix Partnership."
"In 2023, The Labour Party received £21.5M from donations."
"Of this £21.5M, just £5.9M came from trade unions, with £14.5M from companies and"
"individuals, more than in the three previous years of Keir Starmerʼs leadership combined. This reflects the fact that Starmer focused on making the party more pro-"
"business, moving away from Corbynʼs more left wing policies."
Large donors included Gary Lubner  £4.6M  and David Sainsbury  £3.1M . Lubner is the
"former CEO of Belron, a global firm specialising in vehicle glass repair and Sainsbury (from the supermarket) was a big donor to Labour under Blair, but stopped donating under Corbyn."
"There are major concerns that rich donors are able to buy political influence, which is highly"
"undemocratic, and there have been a number of scandals in relation to party funding across a"
range of parties.
There has been concern in relation to the influence of Russian money in the Conservative
Party.
"When Boris Johnson was in power, over £2 million of donations to the Conservative"
"Party were linked to Russia, raising major security concerns. This included Evgeny"
Lebedev who was made a peer by Boris Johnson.
"At the same time, the Conservative Party hasnʼt implemented any of the 21"
"recommendations of the Russia Report, which discovered widespread attempts by Russia to try and influence voters in the Brexit referendum."
"In the summer of 2024, the UK Labour government was involved in a significant controversy"
"named ‘freebiegateʼ involving prominent donor Lord Waheed Alli, a media entrepreneur and Labour peer who had donated over £500,000 to the party since 2020."
Freedom of Information requests from the media revealed that revealed that Prime
"Minister Keir Starmer had accepted substantial gifts from Alli, including clothing and eyewear valued at over £16,000."
"This was particularly controversial, as following Labourʼs electoral victory in July 2024,"
"unelected Alli was granted a temporary security pass to Downing Street, which he used to organise a post-election event and reportedly advise on public appointments—a project referred to as “Operation Integrity.ˮ"
"These revelations led to allegations of cronyism, undermining public trust in"
"politicians and increasing opposition to parties being largely funded by donations, due to the accusation that those with money can influence politics despite being unelected."
There is therefore a strong argument that party funding should be reformed to reformed to
reduce the reliance of parties on donations from rich businesses and individuals and to therefore reduce the possibility of corruption.
Against: Arguments That Party Funding Shouldnʼt Be Reformed
"Whilst donations are certainly an issue, they arenʼt the only source of party funding in the UK,"
"with membership subscriptions, trade unions (for the Labour Party) and some public funding also being key sources."
"This is particularly true of the Labour Party. In 2023/24, the Labour Party received around"
"13% of their total income from state funding that is available to opposition parties and 10% of their total income from trade unions, as well as significant funding from their 370,000 members."
"The extent of possible corruption perhaps shouldnʼt be overstated, as the amount of donations"
is minuscule in comparison to the US and political parties are mainly motivated by staying in power and therefore developing policies that appeal to the electorate.
"Further, donations are regulated by the Electoral Commission, which ensures that all large"
donations and loans are transparent and come from individuals or businesses who are on the UK electoral roll.
Political parties are mandated to ensure their donations/loans come from permissible
sources and to report to the Electoral Commission any that donʼt.
Judgement
"Overall, the potential undue influence of donations from rich individuals and businesses is"
"certainly a problem in relation to party funding, particularly for the Conservative Party which"
receives a majority of its funds from donations.
Party funding should therefore be reformed to reduce the reliance of the Conservative Party on
donations.
This could be done by banning donations to any party over a certain amount and increasing
state funding to compensate for it.
Paragraph Two    Party Fundingʼs Influence On The Party System
For: Arguments That Party Funding Should Be Reformed
One of the key arguments for reforming party funding is that the current system of party funding favours the Labour and Conservative Parties and upholds a two-party system in the UK.
Labour and the Conservatives receive a great deal more funding than minor parties. In
"2023, for example, Labour received £58,628,000, the Conservative Party received"
"£59,361,000, whilst the next highest amount of party funding was just £8,069,285 for the Liberal Democrats."
The high levels of funding received by Labour and the Conservatives allow them to greatly
"outstrip minor parties in terms of spending on fighting elections, hiring staff and spending"
money on advertising.
Even the limited public funding currently available to parties in the UK upholds the two-party
system.
Short Money forms the vast majority of public funding and is only available to opposition
"parties that have won either two seats in the House of Commons at the previous general election, or one seat and more than 150,000 votes in total from all seats contested."
Funding is granted in relation to the number of seats won and therefore favours parties who
are already able to succeed in the FPTP voting system.
This issue could be resolved by moving to a fully state funded system in which funding was
allocated either based on votes won at the previous elections (not seats) or by matching small donations made by the public. This would be effective at ensuring party funding reflects public support.
Against: Arguments That Party Funding Shouldnʼt Be Reformed
"The current system of party funding can be seen as reflecting public support. Labour and the Conservative Party do receive by far the most funding, but they do also have by far the most support across the UK."
"The Labour Party received £58,628,000 in 2023, however this reflects the fact they also"
"have the largest membership of any party with an estimated 370,000 members, as well as receiving contributions from trade unions such as GMB and UNITE which represent lots of voters themselves."
If state funding was introduced and determined based on how well a party did at the
"previous election, as it is in many countries, then it would do little to tackle the two-party system."
"Further, Reform UK has also having significant success in party funding since the 2024"
"election. In December 2024, the party hired billionaire Nick Candy as their treasurer to help the party improve its fundraising before the next election."
"He said he intended to raise enough funds for Reform to win in the next general election,"
and donated £1M of his own money.
This suggests that the dominance of the two main parties in terms of party funding may be
"broken due to growing support for Reform UK, which could aid their electoral chances."
"Finally, the influence of party funding on the success of political parties shouldnʼt be"
"overstated. Whilst it is a factor, it seems very unlikely that reforming party funding would have a"
significant impact on the relative electoral success of different parties.
Judgement
"Overall, reforming the current party system by moving to a fully state funded system would help"
to challenge the dominance of Labour and the Conservative Parties if it was done correctly.
"The potential impact of this shouldnʼt be overstated, however, whilst if the system of state"
"funding introduced was based on matching small donations or determined by votes won in the previous election, it would do little to challenge the two-party system as Labour and the Conservatives still receive the most support across the UK."
Paragraph Three   Party Fundingʼs Influence On Democracy
For: Arguments That Party Funding Should Be Reformed
Political parties are key to representing the public and upholding effective democracy. As a
"consequence, it can be argued that they deserve the effective, stable funding that would be"
delivered by state funding.
This could be overseen by the Electoral Commission and done through matching small
donations from members of the public to ensure state funding remains democratic and isnʼt
manipulated.
State funding would also allow parties and politicians to focus more on representing the public
"and government effectively, instead of spending time focusing on raising money, particularly before elections."
Politicians often host fundraising dinners and events in order to try and raise money for their
party. This can be seen as a distraction from representing the public effectively.
State funding would also prevent governments from passing laws that seek to limit the funding
"of opposition political parties, as happened in the Trade Union Act 2016."
"The act, passed by the Conservatives, harmed Labour Party funding from Trade Unions by"
"obliging new trade union members to choose whether they wanted to opt into making payments towards political influence, rather than automatically being opted in as they were previously."
Labour now intends to revoke the act after regaining power.
Against: Arguments That Party Funding Shouldnʼt Be Reformed
On the other hand it could be argued that the limited public funding currently available ensures
"that parties are independent from the state, and therefore the party currently in power, which can be seen as important in a democracy."
"If a fully state funded system was introduced, it could isolate parties from the wishes of the"
"public and their members, which could be seen as harming democracy."
"Importantly, it would also cost the state a significant amount per year and many taxpayers likely"
"wouldnʼt want to fund parties they donʼt support, especially as they donʼt trust politicians and those in power, as is the case at present following Partygate."
Judgement
"Overall, it is clear that there are benefits and drawbacks in terms of the influence of reforming"
"party funding on democracy. Whilst taxpayers likely wouldnʼt be happy funding parties they donʼt support, moving to a fully state funded system would improve democracy and representation by allowing parties to focus more of their time on representing the public and governing effectively."
Overall Argument
"In conclusion, whilst party funding currently is certainly less of an issue in relation to the Labour"
"Party than the Conservative Party due to the reliance of the latter on donors, party funding in"
the UK does require reform.
"Moving to a state funded system, either based on matching small donations by the public or"
"relative to the number of votes received in the previous election, would reduce the potential of"
"corruption, challenge the two party system and improve democracy in the UK."
Other Possible Essay Questions To Practice Adapting
This Plan To Answer
Evaluate the view that political parties should be state funded. 30
Evaluate the view that the current system of party funding in the UK harms democracy.  30
Follow Politics Explained For More Help With Your Politics A Level
Website → https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/
Instagram → https://www.instagram.com/polexplained/
YouTube  →  https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCQ1FvoFVL4fGJkx6dup3O-w
Twitter → https://twitter.com/Pol_Explain
