Evaluate The Extent To Which General
Elections In The UK Are Lost By The Government Rather Than Won By The Opposition. (30) - Politics Explained Essay Plan
Topic      4. Voting Behaviour and The Media
Structure    Three paragraphs with for/against and an overall judgement within each
This Essay Plan Is Part Of A Package Of Essay Plans Covering The UK Politics Part Of The Politics
"A Level Course For The Edexcel Exam Board, Whilst Also Being Very Useful For The AQA Exam Board. It Can Be Purchased Here    https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/"
Keep In Mind       These are long plans as theyʼre intended to be revised from to cover the key
"content you need to know for the exam. In the exam, you would need to adapt them for the specific question you are asked and you certainly wouldnʼt need to include everything, especially not all of the examples. The judgements are also subjective and you donʼt have to agree with them!"
Introduction
Key Definitions
"As this essay focuses on elections that are ‘lost by the governmentʼ, the key examples used will"
"be from the 1979, 1997, 2010 and 2024 elections, in which there was a change of government."
Paragraph One     Leadership
For: Arguments That General Elections In The UK Are Lost By The Government
It can be argued that general elections in the UK are lost by the government because the unpopularity of Prime Ministers is often a key reason why voters vote against a governing party and the opposition leader isnʼt required to be hugely popular.
"This was clear in the 2024 election, when Rishi Sunak was one of the least popular party"
"leaders fighting an election in history, with a net favourability of  51% with the public. He was tarnished by his involvement in Partygate and viewed by the public as out of touch and smug."
"During the campaign, his popularity dropped even further after he made the highly"
"unpopular decision to leave an event commemorating D Day early to attend an ITV interview, leaving Cameron to deputise for him."
Starmer was able to win a landslide 174 seat majority despite not being widely popular
"himself, with a net favourability of  17% on election day according to YouGov."
"This can also be seen in the 2010 election, when David Cameron didnʼt have particularly high"
"approval ratings, but was still able to win the election due to the unpopularity of Prime Minister Gordon Brown."
An IPSOS Mori poll shortly before the election showed 33% regarded Cameron as the most
"capable PM, compared to 29% for Brown."
"However, he was still able to defeat the government and win the most votes of any party"
"due to Brownʼs reputation of being cowardly, boring and uninspiring. Against this, Cameron didnʼt need to be hugely popular for the Conservative Party to win."
"The same can be seen in the 1979 election, when Prime Minister James Callaghan was derided"
"for his failure to deal with militant trade unions, leading to the Winter of Discontent. Labour were highly unpopular and started the campaign way behind in the polls."
"As a consequence, it was largely irrelevant that Conservative Party leader Margaret"
"Thatcher wasnʼt well known and didnʼt have major popularity, as she and the Conservatives were able to benefit from the unpopularity of Callaghan and the Labour government."
Against: Arguments That General Elections In The UK Are Won By The
Opposition
"On the other hand, if the governing political party recognises that their leader has become"
"unpopular and is no longer an electoral asset, they will often remove them in favour of a new leader who can convince the electorate they are offering something new."
"This can be seen most clearly in the Conservative Party in the past decade, which has"
"removed three leaders who had become unpopular with the public due to failing when in power: Theresa May, Boris Johnson and Liz Truss."
"Before the 2019 election, the Conservative Party removed May and brought in Johnson,"
"who was able to distance himself from the rest of the party and successfully win the election for the Conservatives, in part due to his charisma and personal popularity."
Popular opposition leaders can also be highly important in why opposition parties are able to
win elections against the governing party.
This can be seen in particular in the 1997 election. Blair was very popular across the
"country and was seen as a strong, competent and charismatic leader with a clear vision and"
control over his party.
"This contrasted with Prime Minister John Major, who was seen as a weak, boring leader"
presiding over a party divided over Europe and tainted by ‘sleazeʼ and the cash for questions scandal.
Judgement
"Overall, leaders are key to winning elections for parties and a popular opposition leader is"
certainly an electoral asset.
"In relation to leadership, though, elections are more often lost by the government rather than"
"won by the opposition. If a Prime Minister and their party is unpopular with the public, opposition leaders donʼt need to be hugely popular themselves to win, as voters often seek to punish the governing party and vote for something new anyway."
Paragraph Two     Competence
For: Arguments That General Elections In The UK Are Lost By The Government
It can be argued that general elections in the UK are lost by the government as the perceived
incompetence of the government when in office is often a key reason why voters vote for the opposition.
The failure of the government when in power was a key reason for the government losing in the
"last four elections when there was a change of government: 1979, 1997, 2010 and 2024."
"In the 1979 election, Labour was voted out in large part due to the perception they were"
"unable to manage the economy and trade unions in the context of the 1979 ‘Winter of Discontentʼ, in which the government's attempts to impose a 5% limit on pay increases led to widespread strikes and a sense of national paralysis."
This provided the Conservatives with an irresistible theme: that the country needed a
new direction and a government that could grapple with economic and social
breakdown.
The Conservative Party used the clever slogan ‘Labour Isnʼt Workingʼ.
"Perceived economic incompetence was also significant in the 1997 election. By 1997, the"
"economy was recovering from the recession of the early part of the decade, but voters didn't give the Conservatives credit for this, rather they remembered the catastrophe of 'Black Wednesday' in September 1992."
Monthly opinion polls showed Labour consistently ahead of the Conservatives from the
autumn of 1992 onwards. The Conservatives had lost their reputation as competent managers of the economy and failed to retrieve it.
The incompetence of the Conservative government since 2019 was without doubt the most
"important factor in Labourʼs landslide victory in the 2024 election. The public viewed the Conservatives as incompetent, self-serving and untrustworthy due to a large number of scandals, which led to the partyʼs vote share dropping from 43.6% in 2019 to 23.7% in 2024."
The fact that the government failed to follow its own COVID 19 regulations and held
"parties whilst the public stayed inside, revealed in late 2021 in the ‘partygate scandalʼ, was particularly damaging and resulted in the resignation of Boris Johnson as Prime Minister, who had previously been a popular leader and the partyʼs biggest electoral asset."
This was compounded by a major drop in Conservative Party support in Liz Trussʼ 49
"day premiership, as the unfunded tax cuts in her September 2022 mini-budget caused"
"the poundʼs value to plummet, increased the cost of government borrowing and led to"
increased interest rates and mortgage rates. Truss was forced to resign and the tax cuts
were reversed as a result.
YouGovʼs polling just before the election found that the majority of Labour voters did so
"to get the Tories out or because they felt that the country needed a change, rather than because they supported Labourʼs platform."
Against: Arguments That General Elections In The UK Are Won By The
Opposition
"On the other hand, it can be argued that the opposition are only able to benefit from the governmentʼs incompetence and win the election if they are perceived to be competent themselves."
"This can be seen in the 1997 election, when Labour were successful in presenting"
"themselves as an economically competent party, pledging not to increase income tax and to prioritise national finances."
"It can also be seen in the 1979 election, when a great deal of the Conservative Partyʼs"
"messaging focused on bringing down inflation. The Labour Partyʼs did too, however theirs"
lacked credibility due to their failure when in office.
"In 2024 too, the Labour Party was successful in presenting itself as competent and the"
"antithesis of the Tories. This led to electoral success, as 2019 Conservative voters felt comfortable defecting. They were boring and uninspiring, but they didnʼt put off voters due to appearing too radical."
"Labour moved to the centre ground and promised to not raise income tax, national"
"insurance or corporation tax, which made the Conservative Partyʼs usual attack line that"
they would hike taxes ineffective. Starmer continually promised a return to a
"government of service that was competent, rather than self-serving and incompetent."
Judgement
"Overall, though is it important for the opposition to appear competent themselves, incompetence when in government is often a key reason why governments lose elections."
The importance of competence therefore supports the idea that general elections are lost by
the government rather than won by the opposition.
Paragraph Three     Rational Choice and Issue Based Voting
Against: Arguments That General Elections In The UK Are Won By The
Opposition
One key argument for why general elections in the UK are won by the opposition rather than lost by the government is that the opposition is able to provide a manifesto and policy platform to the electorate that offers a real change and benefits them economically.
"This can be seen in the 1997 election, when Blair successfully rebranded the Labour Party."
"As Labour leader, Blair drove forward the policy of modernisation and abandoned old- fashioned party policies such as nationalisation, tax increases and the strengthening of Trade Union powers, which might put off middle-class voters."
Blair also gave off reassuringly tough signals of law and order (using the slogan ‘Tough
"on crime, tough on the causes of crimeʼ), an issue that mattered to voters after rising crime rates in the early 1990s, and emphasised his links to the business community."
"As a sign of the party's desire to show how responsible it was, its 1997 platform"
"stressed specific policy details where it promised to make a difference, such as reducing primary school class sizes and cutting hospital waiting lists."
"As a consequence, the Labour Party was able to offer a concrete policy platform and real"
"change to the electorate, which enabled Labour to win the election with a landslide."
For: Arguments That General Elections In The UK Are Lost By The Government
"On the other hand, it can be argued that general elections are lost by the government, as"
"opposition parties often have similar policies to the governing party, but are able to win as they provide a change in terms of leadership and arenʼt tainted by their record in government as the"
governing party is.
"This can be seen in the 1979 election, when both parties prioritised bringing down inflation"
and the Conservative Partyʼs manifesto contained very little indication Thatcher intended to move her party so far to the right.
There was a mention of returning recently nationalised industries to private hands and
"removing Trade Union powers, but no suggestion of the radical crusade to scale down"
the state sector that followed.
"In 2010 too, the policies of the Labour and Conservative parties were relatively similar, with"
"both parties supporting austerity and bringing down the deficit, however the Conservative Party had more success as their reputation for economic competence hadnʼt been damaged by the financial crash as Labourʼs had."
"Finally, in 2024, the Labour Party intentionally moved to the centre and was very careful in"
"selecting differences in policy from the Conservative Party. In many areas they were similar: they both promised to increase defence spending to 2.5%; they both promised not to raise income tax, national insurance or corporation tax; they both promised to invest in the NHS; they both promised to tackle illegal immigration."
"This meant that election was mainly fought on the governmentʼs record, rather than on"
policy positions.
Judgement
"Overall, in relation to rational choice and issue based voting, elections are sometimes lost by the government and sometimes won by the opposition."
"In some elections, especially 1997, an oppositionʼs manifesto offering change can be"
"important in winning them the election, whilst in other such as 1979, 2010 and 2024, opposition parties donʼt need to offer major changes in policy but simply a change in"
leadership.
Overall Argument
"In conclusion, when the government loses an election it is invariably a combination of the"
governmentʼs failures and the opposition offering an alternative to the electorate.
The failure of the government both in terms of the unpopularity of their leader and wrecking
"their reputation for competence is arguably more important than the oppositionʼs offering, however. The opposition party can sometimes win an election simply by not being the governing party."
General elections in the UK are therefore lost by the government more than they are won by the
opposition.
Other Possible Essay Questions To Practice Adapting
This Plan To Answer
Evaluate the view that the performance of the government when in power is the most important
factor determining general election results in the UK. 30
Follow Politics Explained For More Help With Your Politics A Level
Website → https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/
Instagram → https://www.instagram.com/polexplained/
YouTube  →  https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCQ1FvoFVL4fGJkx6dup3O-w
Twitter → https://twitter.com/Pol_Explain
