Evaluate The View That Rights Are
Effectively Protected in the UK. (30) Politics Explained Essay Plan
Topic        1. Democracy and Participation
Structure    Three paragraphs with for/against and an overall judgement within each
This Essay Plan Is Part Of A Package Of Essay Plans Covering The UK Politics Part Of The Politics
"A Level Course For The Edexcel Exam Board, Whilst Also Being Very Useful For The AQA Exam Board. It Can Be Purchased Here    https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/"
Keep In Mind       These are long plans as theyʼre intended to be revised from to cover the key
"content you need to know for the exam. In the exam, you would need to adapt them for the specific question you are asked and you certainly wouldnʼt need to include everything, especially not all of the examples. The judgements are also subjective and you donʼt have to"
agree with them!
Introduction
Key Definitions
"Rights, also known as civil liberties, are legally protected freedoms that are absolute, universal"
"and fundamental. They include the right to vote, freedom of expression and freedom of"
"movement, among many others."
Paragraph One     Civil Liberties Pressure Groups
For: It Can Be Argued That Pressure Groups Protect Rights Effectively
"Civil Liberties Pressure Groups can be seen as very effective in the protection of rights in the UK, through campaigning for the protection of rights and ensuring rights remain high-profile in the political system."
Insider Pressure Groups can play an important role in the development and passage of
legislation that furthers the protection of rights in the UK.
"LGBT   Rights Pressure Group Stonewall, for example, used its insider contacts and favour in"
"New Labour governments to introduce important new laws and policies, including equalising the age of consent for gay and straight individuals to 16 years old as part of the Sexual Offences Act 2000, for which the Parliaments Acts 1911 and 1949 had to be invoked to overrule House of Lords opposition."
Outsider Pressure Groups can also be important in defending the rights of citizens in the UK by
"initiating legal challenges against government policies and legislation, including on behalf of individuals who may not have been able to afford it themselves."
"Care4Calais, a pressure group that campaigns for the rights of refugees in the UK, was  key"
in fighting legal challenges on behalf of migrants in the UK threatened with deportation to Rwanda following a deal between the previous UK government and the Rwandan government.
Care4Calais and others argued that it was unsafe to send people to Rwanda and that it
"violates the Human Rights Act, due to factors such as discriminatory access to asylum for different groups in Rwanda, especially LGBT people."
"Along with other human rights campaigners, it had a notable success on 14 June 2022"
when the first planned deportation flight to Rwanda was emptied one by one due to successful human rights legal challenges in the European Court of Human Rights
Against: Counterarguments to Pressure Groups Protecting Rights Effectively
"On the other hand, Civil Liberties Pressure Groups can be seen as having limited effectiveness"
because it is the government that ultimately makes the final decision on legislation that effects rights and campaigns about unpopular causes often have limited success.
"This can be seen in the failure of Liberty to prevent the Police, Crime, Sentencing and Courts"
"Act from being passed in 2021, which they saw as limiting the right to protest in the UK."
"Liberty organised widespread protests under the slogan #KillTheBill, and is a very"
"experienced organisation, but was nonetheless unable to stop the bill being passed, due to sections of the public opposing disruptive protests by Just Stop Oil which the bill was in response to, and the fact that the government was intent on passing it."
Liberty and other human rights pressure groups have also failed to convince the new Labour
"Government to repeal the Public Order Act 2023, which limits the right to disruptive protest in"
"the UK, which can be seen as key to freedom of expression."
"In  March 2025, the Public Order Act was used to prevent farmers protesting against"
"inheritance tax changes from bringing tractors to their protests in Westminster and blocking the roads, due to the Act defining this as interfering with national infrastructure."
"The Howard League For Penal Reform, for example, has had limited success in advocating for"
"the rights of prisoners in the UK, mainly because the rights of convicted criminals don't make a"
popular cause.
"They have been unsuccessful, for example, in convincing the government to grant"
prisoners the vote.
Judgement
"Whilst it is true that the effectiveness of Civil Liberties Pressure Groups is somewhat dependent on the willingness of the government of the day to comply, they can be effective through legal"
challenges even when the government is opposed to their cause and have played a central role
in the passage of legislation that protects rights in the UK in the past 2 decades.
"Overall, therefore, the actions of Civil Liberties Pressure Groups do effectively protect rights in"
the UK and are an important part of the system of rights protection.
Paragraph Two    The Government/Parliament
For: The Government/Parliament Can Pass Legislation To Protect Rights And
Parliament Can Hold The Government To Account
Due to the power Parliament has to pass legislation that protects rights and the dominant
"position the Government often holds within Parliament, the Government can be seen as important in protecting rights through the ability it has to pass legislation that defends the rights of citizens in the UK."
"For example, Gordon Brownʼs government introduced the 2010 Equality Act and the"
"Coalition legalised same sex marriage in 2013, despite it not being mentioned in the Conservative Partyʼs 2010 manifesto."
It can also be argued that government measures that threaten individual rights are justified as
"they protect collective rights and the community/society, especially during emergencies."
"The removal of freedom of movement during COVID 19 lockdowns, for example, can be"
seen as necessary to prevent the spread of the virus.
"Further, Parliament can sometimes be effective in preventing the government from encroaching"
"human rights by voting down bills, especially the House of Lords due to its lack of government majority."
"In 2005, for example, the House of Commons and House of Lords voted down Tony Blairʼs"
"proposal to allow the police to hold terrorist suspects for 90 days without charge, with a"
compromise eventually passed at 28 days.
"Against: The Government/Parliament Can Pass Laws Which Threaten Rights,"
Including To Protect Collective Over Individual Rights
"On the other hand, the Government/Parliament can be argued to play a key role in threatening"
"rights in the UK, rather than effectively protecting them."
This can be seen in recent Conservative governments which have passed a number of acts that
"threaten individual rights in the UK, despite fierce opposition from human rights groups, journalists and the public."
"For example, The Policing, Crime, Sentencing and Courts Act gives greater powers to the"
"police and criminal justice system to impose restrictions on ‘unacceptable protestsʼ, among other things. This allows the Home Secretary to define certain protests as ‘unacceptableʼ, such as protests in the ‘buffer zoneʼ of Parliament, and has been criticised for impeding"
freedom of speech and the right to protest in the UK.
The Public Order Act 2023 continued this attack on the right to protest by introducing
"new offenses such as ""locking-on"" (attaching oneself to objects or other people to cause serious disruption) and interfering with national infrastructure (including the roads around Parliament), which are punishable by imprisonment or unlimited fines."
"On October 30th 2023, the Metropolitan Police swiftly intervened in a Just Stop Oil"
"'slow march' around Parliament Square, arresting over 60 activists within minutes under the new legislation."
"The law, specifically section 7, prohibits activities interfering with the use of key"
"national infrastructure, which in this case included the roads around significant governmental buildings."
Conservative figures including Robert Jenrick have also supported a proposal to leave the
"European Convention on Human Rights and replace the Human Rights Act by a ‘British Bill of Rightsʼ, in order to make it easier to deport foreign criminals by elevating public safety over the right to family life and to increase freedom of the press by elevating the right to freedom of expression over the right to privacy, are also worrying."
The proposal has been criticised by hundreds of human rights groups for seeking to
"remove rights in the UK, but hasnʼt been ruled out by Conservative Party leader Kemi Badenoch if the Conservative Party were to win the next election."
"Importantly, it can be argued that the new Labour Government has also failed to respect rights"
"in the UK, particularly the rights of asylum seekers."
"In February 2025, the government revised the “good characterˮ guidance to deny British"
citizenship applications to refugees who entered the UK through unauthorised or dangerous
"routes, including small boat crossings across the English Channel."
Critics argue that this approach violates the rights of refugees in the 1951 Refugee
"Convention, which protects asylum seekers from penalties due to illegal entry when fleeing persecution."
"Individual rights have also often not been effectively protected by the government, which has"
justified this by arguing it is necessary to protect public safety and collective rights.
This can be seen most prominently in the New Labour government response to the high
profile terrorist attacks of the 2000s.
"Among other things, the government argued they had the right to detain terror suspects"
without trial on the grounds that a national emergency existed.
"This was ruled as discriminatory by the Law Lords in December 2004 and ended, but"
"was ultimately replaced by a law that introduced a system of control orders that enabled suspects to be closely monitored, including through electronic tagging."
Judgement
"Overall, the actions of the government are a way in which rights arenʼt effectively protected in"
the UK.
While it is true that the government has passed some legislation to protect rights and parliament
"has some power to hold it to account, governments since the 2000s have passed a number of laws that threaten rights in the UK, particularly the rights of refugees and the right to protest. Though some of these can be seen as justified to protect the community/collective rights, many have gone too far."
Paragraph Three      The Judiciary and Human Rights Act
For: It Can Be Argued That the Judiciary and Human Rights Act Protect Rights
Effectively
"The Human Rights Act, passed by the New Labour government in 1998, means that the"
European Convention on Human Rights is now part of UK law and individuals can take their cases to domestic courts for British protection rather than having to go to Strasbourg.
"It can be argued that the HRA protects rights effectively in the UK. Since the HRA, it is often"
"claimed that the UK has developed a 'rights-based culture' as all new legislation must be compliant with the act and judges can declare earlier acts of parliament incompatible with it, whilst public authorities in the UK are under an obligation to abide by it. The judiciary can therefore stop government actions that go against the Human Rights Act by declaring them illegal."
Parliament usually acts to address any issues raised by the courts and parliament also has a
"Joint Committee on Human Rights to scrutinise bills and ensure they are compatible, demonstrating the 'persuasive influence' of the HRA."
"For example, in A v Secretary of State for the Home Department, part of The Anti-terrorism,"
Crime and Security Act 2001 was declared incompatible with Articles 5 and 14 of the human rights act by permitting the detention of suspected international terrorists in a way that discriminated on the grounds of nationality or immigration status. The Prevention of Terrorism Act 2005 was introduced by parliament to fix this as a result.
"Further, the HRA educates citizens about their rights and makes them more high profile in"
"the political system, especially in comparison to previously when rights were protected as"
‘negative rightsʼ.
Judicial review is also used in relation to government actions and it can be argued that it is a
"vital means of defending citizens' rights, enabling the legality of government actions to be scrutinised."
Against: Counterarguments to the Judiciary and Human Rights Act Protecting
Rights Effectively
"On the other hand, some argue that the Human Rights Act doesnʼt protect rights effectively in the UK as parliamentary sovereignty means that judges canʼt legally compel parliament to make changes to laws and the fact it is not entrenched means the HRA could be repealed by a simple act of parliament."
"Further, even though the judiciary can stop a government action that threaten right by declaring"
"it illegal, the government can then change the law to make their action legal. This can be seen"
in the Safety of Rwanda Act passed under Sunakʼs government.
"The UK government originally formed a migration partnership with Rwanda in April 2022,"
intending to relocate asylum seekers who arrived in the UK illegally to Rwanda where their asylum claims would be processed.
The Supreme Court ruled this was illegal in November 2023. The court found the policy
"unlawful, citing risks of refoulement and inadequacies in Rwanda's asylum system as major concerns. They argued that as a result, the policy was against the Human Rights Act and the 1951 Refugee Convention, as Rwanda couldnʼt be defined as a ‘safe countryʼ."
"In response, rather than changing to a different policy that was legal, the UK government"
pushed through Parliament a law that made their Rwanda policy consistent with domestic law.
The Safety of Rwanda Act was passed in April 2024. It states that Rwanda must be
considered a safe country for asylum seekers and that international law must be put aside to allow for the deportation of asylum seekers to Rwanda.
This shows the limits of the judiciaryʼs influence as they can only implement the law that
Parliament passes.
"Many critics on the right also criticise the HRA for favouring undeserving individuals, including"
"illegal migrants and terror suspects, rather than protecting the legitimate freedoms of UK"
citizens and protecting society as a whole.
"For example, Abu Qatada, a radical Muslim cleric who had advocated the use of violence to"
"promote the Islamist cause and had spent some time in British jails, was wanted by the security services to be deported to Jordan, where he was wanted for trial."
However his legal advisers managed to delay this for 8 years on the grounds that he
"might be tried using evidence obtained through torture, a breach of the HRA."
Legal challenges in relation to the HRA have also prevented the deportation of illegal
immigrants to Rwanda.
"Judicial review and the HRA have also been criticised for for giving unelected, unaccountable"
and unrepresentative judges too much power to prevent the actions of elected governments and put pressure on elected parliaments to change bills.
Judgement
"Overall, the Human Rights Act and judiciary arguably protect rights effectively in the UK. Whilst"
"it is true that it is not binding on parliament and could be repealed by an act of parliament, parliament almost always abides by the HRA and repeal is unlikely due to the outrage this would lead to."
"The Safety of Rwanda Act can be seen as an exception to the norm, where the government and"
"Parliament normally listens to the judiciary, and is set to be repealed in 2025 by the Labour Government."
Overall Argument
"In conclusion, the protection of rights in the UK is relatively effective. It is certainly true that the"
"government has the potential to, and has at times, threatened the rights of individuals in the UK, whilst recent proposals from the Conservative Party to replace the Human Rights Act are worrying."
"However, some of these measures passed by the government are justified by protecting"
"collective rights, whilst the judiciary and Human Rights Act and the actions of civil liberties pressure groups in particular are effective checks on the government. Overall, therefore, rights are relatively well protected in the UK."
Other Possible Essay Questions To Practice Adapting
This Plan To Answer
"Evaluate the view that judges, rather than politicians, are better able to protect and defends"
rights in the UK  30
Evaluate the argument that pressure groups are the most effective protector of rights in the UK
political system 30
Evaluate the view that citizens can no longer feel confident that their rights in the UK are secure
and established. 30
Follow Politics Explained For More Help With Your Politics A Level
Website → https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/
Instagram → https://www.instagram.com/polexplained/
YouTube  →  https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCQ1FvoFVL4fGJkx6dup3O-w
Twitter → https://twitter.com/Pol_Explain
