Evaluate The View That Valence
Factors Are The Most Important Factors Determining Voting Behaviour In UK Elections. (30) - Politics Explained Essay Plan
Topic      4. Voting Behaviour and The Media
Structure    Three paragraphs with for/against and an overall judgement within each
This Essay Plan Is Part Of A Package Of Essay Plans Covering The UK Politics Part Of The Politics
"A Level Course For The Edexcel Exam Board, Whilst Also Being Very Useful For The AQA Exam Board. It Can Be Purchased Here    https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/"
Keep In Mind       These are long plans as theyʼre intended to be revised from to cover the key
"content you need to know for the exam. In the exam, you would need to adapt them for the specific question you are asked and you certainly wouldnʼt need to include everything, especially not all of the examples. The judgements are also subjective and you donʼt have to agree with them!"
Introduction
Key Definitions
Valence issues are when there isnʼt significant disagreement between parties and voters
therefore choose based on which party they think is going to be most effective in government. Leadership and competence are key to this.
"These became more important in the 2010, 2015 and 2024 elections, when there were"
fewer policy differences between the parties.
Paragraph One
Voting
Leadership vs Rational Choice and Issue Based
For: Arguments That Valence Factors Are The Most Important Factors
Determining Voting Behaviour
The public image of party leaders has become more important in recent decades as politics has
"become increasingly personalised, especially since the growth of digital and social media,"
where visual images and personalities are highly important.
Commentators have talked about the 'presidentialisation' of British politics since the 1979
"election, with the suggestion being that UK election campaigns are increasingly shaped by"
"voters' perceptions of the leading figures, as they are in the US, in part due to media focus."
"Parties appreciate the importance of presenting their leaders in a good light, with attention"
"given to photo opportunities that will show the leaders' human touch, as well as leadersʼ"
debates.
"In the 2010 election, Nick Cleggʼs success in the leadersʼ debate result in a boost in the"
polls for the Liberal Democrats.
"Leadership was particularly important in the 2010, 2015 and 2024 elections, when there were"
few policy differences between the parties.
"In 2010, for example, David Cameronʼs leadership provided a fresh and young approach"
"compared the Gordon Brown, who was also viewed as cowardly and lacking in charisma."
"When Brown became PM, he briefly encouraged speculation that he would call an"
"autumn election in order to secure a personal mandate. When he decided not to do so, he was widely ridiculed for alleged cowardice and his reputation never fully recovered."
"By contrast, Cameron was relatively popular, especially in comparison to the"
Conservative Party leaders that came before him.
Leaders can be seen as important in winning over swing voters and unifying the party.
"Boris Johnson in the 2019 election is a key example of this, as his personal popularity and"
"difference from the traditional image of the Conservative Party allowed the Conservatives to win the votes of many former Labour voters in the ‘Red Wallʼ, who had never voted Tory before."
"Similarly, poor and unpopular leaders can have a detrimental impact on the popularity of a"
political party by deterring potential voters.
"Jeremy Corbyn in 2019 is a good example of this, with his personal unpopularity being a key"
"reason why many voters didnʼt vote for the Labour Party, which had its worst election result since 1935."
"In 2024, leadership was an important factor in Labourʼs victory. Rishi Sunak was one of the"
"least popular party leaders fighting an election in history, with a net favourability of  51% with the public. He was tarnished by his involvement in Partygate and viewed by the public as out of touch and smug."
"During the campaign, his popularity dropped even further after he made the highly"
"unpopular decision to leave an event commemorating D Day early to attend an ITV interview, leaving Cameron to deputise for him."
"Starmer was more popular with the public, with a net favourability of  17% on election"
day according to YouGov.
Against: Arguments That Valence Factors Arenʼt The Most Important Factors
Determining Voting Behaviour
"Rather than voting based on the leadership and personnel of political parties, it can be argued"
that voters care far more about the policies of political parties and how these would affect them
if implemented.
Rational choice theory is the idea that voters behave like consumers by looking at the available
options and evaluating which is the most beneficial for them.
"This is linked to the growth of a more educated electorate, especially with the rise of the"
internet and the abundance of information online.
"Economics of course plays an important role in this, with there also being a more rigid"
"theory; ‘economic votingʼ, which suggests that people simply vote out of self interest for the party that will benefit them economically."
This partly explains why homeowners are more likely to vote for the Conservatives and
those who rent are more likely to vote for Labour.
"Around 40% of those with mortgages, privately renting or socially renting voted for"
"the Labour Party in 2024, reflecting the fact that Labour promised improved rental conditions and mortgage rates had increased significantly under the Conservatives. By contrast, just 25% of those who owned their home outright voted for the Labour Party."
It also partly explains why many younger voters voted for Labour in the 2017 and 2019
"elections, as one of Jeremy Corbynʼs key policies was abolishing university tuition fees."
Issue based voting is similar to rational choice theory in that it suggests voters vote based on
"policy, but is different in suggesting that voters vote based on which party is closest to them on the policy they deem most important, even if they are not aligned with the partyʼs other policies."
The 2019 election was a key example of this. 74% of Leave voters voted for the Tories
"(including many in the Red Wall who had never done so before), whilst 49% of Remain"
voters voted Labour.
Issue based voting can be seen as particularly important when there are stark policy
differences between political parties.
Judgement
"Overall, both leadership and rational choice/issue based voting are without doubt key factors in"
determining voting behaviour in UK elections.
Leadership is arguably more important when there is little policy difference between political
"parties, such as in 2010 and 2015, whilst voting based on policy is arguably more important when there are clear policy differences between parties, such as in the 2017 and 2019"
elections.
Paragraph Two      Competence vs The Campaign
For: Arguments That Valence Factors Are The Most Important Factors
Determining Voting Behaviour
How competent voters perceive the current government to be is a key factor in how they vote.
"In an election, they are able to pass judgement on the governmentʼs performance in power and"
replace them if they deem them to have been incompetent.
"Competence was an important factor in the 1979 election, when Labour was voted out due"
"to the perception they were unable to manage the economy and trade unions in the context of the 1979 ‘Winter of Discontentʼ, in which the government's attempts to impose a 5% limit on pay increases led to widespread strikes and a sense of national paralysis."
This provided the Conservatives with an irresistible theme: that the country needed a
new direction and a government that could grapple with economic and social
breakdown.
The Conservative Party used the clever slogan ‘Labour Isnʼt Workingʼ.
"Perceived economic incompetence was also significant in the 1997 election. By 1997, the"
"economy was recovering from the recession of the early part of the decade, but voters"
"didn't give the Conservatives credit for this, rather they remembered the catastrophe of"
'Black Wednesday' in September 1992.
Monthly opinion polls showed Labour consistently ahead of the Conservatives from the
autumn of 1992 onwards. The Conservatives had lost their reputation as competent managers of the economy and failed to retrieve it.
"Given this context, Labour were successful in presenting themselves as an"
"economically competent party, pledging not to increase income tax and to prioritise national finances."
The incompetence of the Conservative government since 2019 was without doubt the most
"important factor in Labourʼs landslide victory in the 2024 election. The public viewed the Conservatives as incompetent, self-serving and untrustworthy due to a large number of scandals, which led to the partyʼs vote share dropping from 43.6% in 2019 to 23.7% in"
2024.
The fact that the government failed to follow its own COVID 19 regulations and held
"parties whilst the public stayed inside, revealed in late 2021 in the ‘partygate scandalʼ, was particularly damaging and resulted in the resignation of Boris Johnson as Prime Minister, who had previously been a popular leader and the partyʼs biggest electoral asset."
This was compounded by a major drop in Conservative Party support in Liz Trussʼ 49
"day premiership, as the unfunded tax cuts in her September 2022 mini-budget caused the poundʼs value to plummet, increased the cost of government borrowing and led to increased interest rates and mortgage rates. Truss was forced to resign and the tax cuts were reversed as a result."
YouGovʼs polling just before the election found that the majority of Labour voters did so
"to get the Tories out or because they felt that the country needed a change, rather than because they  supported Labourʼs  platform."
"It isnʼt just the competence of the governing party that is important, so too is the perceived"
competence of the opposition.
Int he 2019 election Labour was seen by many as far too radical and not trusted with the
"economy, due to its very left wing manifesto that included major spending pledges and 6"
big nationalisations.
Corbyn was presented and seen by many as unfit to govern and a big risk to the
economy.
Against: Arguments That Valence Factors Arenʼt The Most Important Factors
Determining Voting Behaviour
"Whilst competence can be seen as important, it can be argued that the more short term issues and events that arise in the campaign are more important in how voters decide."
"During the campaign, parties publish their manifestos and make active efforts on the ground"
"and in the media to win over voters, including spending significant amounts of money on advertising and appearing in TV interviews and debates."
"This can therefore be seen as highly important, such as in the 2017 election, when the"
"campaign started with the Conservatives significantly ahead in opinion polls, but Labour were able to gain significant ground despite how a lot of the press presented Corbyn"
negatively.
Many voters only pay attention to politics during election campaigns and they can therefore be
"seen as highly important to election results, especially if key events/gaffes happen during them."
"In the 2017 election campaign, a key moment was when Theresa May announced plans to"
"change social care so that those receiving care at home would also have to contribute to the cost of their care. This was dubbed by the media as the ‘dementia taxʼ and received a massive backlash, leading to significant damage to the Conservative Party, which dropped it within 24 hours."
In the 2010 election campaign much was made of Brown's unscripted meeting with a voter
"Duffy) in Rochdale. After she embarrassed him with a hostile question about immigration, a radio microphone picked him up describing her as a 'bigoted woman' while being driven away. The incident was seized by the media and contributed to Brownʼs unpopularity as a"
leader.
"The campaign was highly important in the 2024 election, in particular due to the rise in support"
"for Reform UK, who rose from just over 10% in the polls at the start of the campaign to 14% of the vote by 4th July, which damaged the Tory party in particular.  Particularly important to this jump was the announcement in the beginning of June that Nigel Farage would stand in Clacton and become leader of the party."
The Conservativesʼ worst electoral performance since the 19th century was partly driven by
the fact that they shot themselves in the foot on two key occasions in the campaign.
"On 6th June, Rishi Sunak was widely criticised by the public and other party leaders for"
"leaving an event commemorating D Day early to attend an ITV interview, leaving Cameron to deputise for him."
"On 12th June, it emerged that a couple of Conservative Party candidates, including"
"Parliamentary Private Secretary to the Prime Minister Craig Williams, had placed bets on a July election days before it was announced, allegedly using insider information. This contributed to the already established view that the Tories were corrupt and self- interested,  further eroding  their popularity."
Judgement
The campaign is important in how voters decide and events during it can play a role in swinging
"some voters. Overall, however, its important is limited, as voters have often already made their mind up having evaluated the performance of the government since the previous election."
Perceived competence is a central factor in determining voting behaviour in UK elections.
Paragraph Three    Valence Factors vs Social Factors
Against: Arguments That Valence Factors Arenʼt The Most Important Factors
Determining Voting Behaviour
"Rather than voting based on aspects of parties that change, such as leadership and perceived"
"competence (valence factors), it can be argued that voters often vote for a particular party irrespective of these factors."
This is especially the case when there are significant policy differences between the
"parties, as different policies appeal very differently to different parts of the population. For example, free tuition fees is likely to appeal a great deal to younger voters, but put off many older  voters."
Social factors are key to understanding this.
Up until the early 1970s voting behaviour was strongly influenced by class and social status.
"Class voting was strongly influenced by self interest, with each party defined by protecting"
and representing  different classes.
"The majority of the working class voted for the Labour Party, which was strongly"
"associated with the trade union movement and traditional ‘blue collarʼ industries such as coal, steel and textiles."
The majority of the upper and middle classes voted for the Conservative Party including
"‘white collarʼ workers including non-manual workers, business people and property owners."
"Today, age can be seen as a key determinant of voting behaviour. In 2017, YouGov called it"
the “new dividing line in British politicsˮ.
"Older voters are much more likely to vote Conservative, whilst younger voters are much"
more likely to vote for Labour or other more left wing and ‘radicalʼ parties such as the Greens and the SNP.
"In 2024, an estimated 18% of 18 24 year olds voted Green, 41% voted Labour, just"
9% voted Reform and 8% voted Conservative.
"In comparison, just 3% of over 60s voted Green. In this age group, 24% voted"
"Labour, 16% voted Reform and 40% voted Conservative."
"Turnout is also much higher among older voters, therefore benefiting the Conservative"
Party.
Turnout among the 65 age group in 2017 was around 25 percentage points higher
than among 18 24 year olds.
For: Arguments That Valence Factors Are The Most Important Factors
Determining Voting Behaviour
"On the other hand, since the 1970s and 1980s, ‘partisan dealignmentʼ has occurred, which can"
be seen as limiting the influence of ‘social factorsʼ and increasing the importance of short-term valance factors.
"In the post-WWII period, voters had strong affiliations with and attachments to political"
"parties, which were part of votersʼ identities. This was influenced by family tradition, class, the workplace and the community."
These attachments began declining in the 1970s and 80s and have continued to decline in
the 21st century. There are now a lot more swing voters who are comfortable voting for any
party (including rising minor parties) and decide each election.
"This can be seen in the unprecedented swing from the Conservatives to Labour, with a"
Tory landslide in 2019 turning into a Labour landslide in 2024.
The Conservatives won a 56 seats in the North and Wales in 2019 due to the popularity
"of Johnson and the issue of Brexit, but lost all but 4 of these seats in 2024 as voters lost trust in the Conservatives and viewed them as incompetent and self-serving."
"Further, class has greatly declined in importance since the 1970s and 1980s and now has little"
"bearing on how individuals vote, whilst age can be seen as a weaker determinant of voting"
"behaviour, as it doesnʼt form a key part of votersʼ identities like class used to."
"In this context, valence factors can be seen as the most important factors in determining voting"
"behaviour, as more voters feel comfortable voting for either of the main parties and therefore vote based on changing factors within these parties including leadership and perceived competence."
Judgement
"Overall, social factors are certainly less important determinants of voting behaviour than they used to be when class was central. In light of class dealignment and partisan dealignment, valence factors including leadership and competence are now more important factors in how"
voters decide.
Overall Argument
"In conclusion, valence factors have certainly increased in importance as determinants of voting"
behaviour as class allegiances and partisanship have declined in importance.
"In elections where the policy differences between the parties are limited, such as in 2010 and"
"2015, leadership and competence are now the most important factors in determining voting"
behaviour.
"In elections where the policy differences between parties are significant, however, such as in"
"2019 in relation to Brexit in particular, valence factors are not the most important factors"
"determining voting behaviour in UK elections. Instead, policies are more important."
Other Possible Essay Questions To Practice Adapting
This Plan To Answer
Evaluate the view that party leaders win elections for their party.  30
Evaluate the view that class voting remains the most important factor in determining the results
of general elections in the UK.  30
Evaluate the view that social factors determine voting behaviour. 30
Follow Politics Explained For More Help With Your Politics A Level
Website → https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/
Instagram → https://www.instagram.com/polexplained/
YouTube   →   https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCQ1FvoFVL4fGJkx6dup3O-w
Twitter → https://twitter.com/Pol_Explain
