Evaluate The View That Reforms To
Democracy In The UK Havenʼt Gone Far Enough. (30) Politics Explained Essay Plan
Topic        1. Democracy and Participation
Structure    Three paragraphs with for/against and an overall judgement within each
This Essay Plan Is Part Of A Package Of Essay Plans Covering The UK Politics Part Of The Politics
"A Level Course For The Edexcel Exam Board, Whilst Also Being Very Useful For The AQA Exam Board. It Can Be Purchased Here    https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/"
Keep In Mind       These are long plans as theyʼre intended to be revised from to cover the key
"content you need to know for the exam. In the exam, you would need to adapt them for the specific question you are asked and you certainly wouldnʼt need to include everything, especially not all of the examples. The judgements are also subjective and you donʼt have to agree with them!"
Introduction
Key Definitions
Paragraph One     Replacing First Past The Post
For: Reforms To Democracy In The UK Havenʼt Gone Far Enough
Perhaps the most important possible reform to democracy in the UK is replacing the First Past
The Post with a more proportional voting system.
FPTP can be seen as undermining UK democracy due to its lack of proportionality and
limited voter choice in particular.
"First Past The Post is very unrepresentative, as it is a simple plurality system that results in"
elected MPs often lacking majority support in their constituency. This lack of representation in
"constituencies translates to a lack of proportionality at the national level, with votes not"
translated into seats with any real accuracy.
FPTP favours parties with geographically concentrated support and therefore massively
under-represents the majority of minor parties.
"In 2019, the Liberal Democrats won 11.5% of the vote but just 11/650 seats 1.7% of the"
"seats). If the system was fully proportional, they wouldʼve won 75 seats."
"FPTP also results in a ‘winnerʼs bonusʼ, where the party with the most votes, even when"
"they donʼt have a majority, hugely benefits."
"In 2024, the Labour Party won a landslide with 411 seats and a 174 seat majority, despite"
receiving just 33.7% of the vote.
Voter choice is very limited under FPTP.
"Voters only get one vote and can therefore only vote for one party, preventing them from"
showing their political preferences more fully.
"This contrasts with the Additional Member System when voters get 2 votes, one for a"
party and one for a constituency member. They can therefore vote for a ‘split-ticketʼ if they wish.
This leads to votes for the party that doesnʼt win in a constituency being effectively ‘wastedʼ
"and to many voters resorting to ‘tactical votingʼ, which is where voters select a different party to their preferred party (which has little chance of winning in their constituency) to try and prevent their least favourite party from winning in their constituency."
Against: Reforms To Democracy In The UK Have Gone Far Enough
"Whilst FPTP may have limited voter choice and be unrepresentative, but it does have some advantages which lead to much of the population supporting it."
"In the 2011 Alternative Vote  AV  referendum, 68% of those who voted, voted against"
"changing the electoral system to AV (a more proportional system), on a 42% turnout."
"FPTP is extremely easy to use for voters, who only have to select one candidate/party. The"
"result is also usually known early in the morning after polling day and the government is quickly formed, with a swift and orderly transfer of power."
"In 2024, for example, the first constituency result  Sunderland South) was announced at"
23 15 on the day of the election and Starmer arrived at Downing Street as the new Prime Minister at 12 40pm the day after the election.
"FPTP has a very strong MP-constituency link, which arguably delivers effective local"
representation.
"The relatively small size of most FPTP constituencies, and the fact that a single MP is"
"responsible for those who live within the constituency, result in effective representation of local interests and a strong link between the constituency and MP. MPs handle correspondence from their constituents and problems their constituents have and hold weekly constituency surgeries."
"On December 5, 2023, 22 Conservative MPs supported a Labour amendment aimed at"
"speeding up compensation for victims of the infected blood scandal, rebelling against a 3"
line conservative whip to do so.
"The amendment, which was successfully passed by a narrow majority, called for the"
establishment of a body to administer compensation within three months of passing the Victims and Prisoners Bill.
This is a good example of the strong MP-constituency link and local representation
"under FPTP, as the rebels were influenced by strong local movements and victims of the scandal in their constituency."
"For example, Conservative MP Caroline Nokes rebelled to represent the local"
movement for greater compensation and the number of victims affected in her
Romsey and Southampton North Constituency.
Judgement
"Overall, though the MP-constituency link and ease of use are certainly benefits of FPTP, these"
benefits are outweighed by the fact that FPTP has very limited voter choice and is highly
unrepresentative.
"In the area of electoral systems, reforms to democracy in the UK therefore havenʼt gone far"
"enough, as replacing FPTP with a more proportional system would greatly improve UK"
democracy.
Paragraph Two     Extending /Reforming The Franchise
For: Reforms To Democracy In The UK Havenʼt Gone Far Enough
"Turnout is relatively low in UK elections, at just 67.3% in the 2019 general election and 59.9% in"
"2024, and it can be argued that extending the franchise would improve democracy in the UK."
One central possible reform for extending the franchise is granting the right to vote to 16 and 17
"year olds, which was supported by the Labour Party in their 2024 election manifesto but has yet to be implemented."
"One key argument in favour of this is that if 16 and 17 year olds could vote, then they would"
take part more in politics. Voting becomes a habit and starting it early is a good thing.
"Further, social media has led to increased political awareness among the young and"
they have led recent political movements such as the Fridays For Future climate strikes.
The granting of the vote to 16 and 17 years olds in Scottish elections has led to
increased political engagement.
Having a vote would give 16 and 17 year olds a say on issues that mean a lot to them
"such as university tuition fees and would increase the size of the ‘youth voteʼ, forcing them to focus more on developing policies that will appeal to young people."
"Further, 16 and 17 year olds have other legal rights; such as leaving school, starting work"
"and joining the armed forces and it can therefore be argued they should be able to vote too, if they are deemed mature enough to have these other rights."
Another possible reform for reforming the franchise in the UK is the introduction of compulsory
"voting at elections, as is the case in Australia where turnout is always over 90%."
Introducing compulsory voting would force politicians and parties to run their campaigns
"with the whole electorate in mind, therefore improving the responsiveness of parties and making Parliament more representative of the whole population."
"Further, it can be argued that voting is a social duty as well as a right and it would"
encouraged people to be engaged in politics.
Against: Reforms To Democracy In The UK Have Gone Far Enough
Though many support votes at 16 and it has been introduced in elections and referendums in
"Scotland, there are many who argue against its introduction for UK general elections in particular."
Voter turnout is very low among 18 24 year olds and there is little evidence that the majority
of 16 and 17 year olds want the vote. Many know very little about politics and would misuse the right to vote without better political education in schools at a younger age.
"Some of the legal rights 16 year olds have are limited in practice, reflecting a recognition"
that they are still children.
"For example, few 16 year olds are in full-time employment and they can't be deployed to"
the front line until they're 18.
There are also some important arguments against introducing compulsory voting.
"Making voting compulsory can be seen as undemocratic, as voting should be a matter of"
"choice, whilst it also fails to address the deeper reasons why people decide not to vote and can be seen as papering over the cracks of UK democracy."
"Also, in a preferential voting system such at STV, where candidates have to be ranked, it"
may just lead to many putting them in the order they are presented.
"Further, it wouldnʼt stop politicians focusing their campaigns on marginal seats and"
neglecting safe seats.
Judgement
"Overall, low turnout in UK elections in the 21st century are a significant problem for UK democracy. Reforming the franchise by introducing votes at 16 and compulsory voting would therefore improve democracy in UK and should be introduced, as they would increase turnout, political awareness and the degree to which Parliament is representative of the population."
Paragraph Three     Greater Use Of Direct Democracy
For: Reforms To Democracy In The UK Havenʼt Gone Far Enough
"In recent decades, referendums have been called due to public pressure and had relatively high"
"turnouts, especially in comparison to General Elections. A convention has developed that the public should be consulted on key constitutional changes."
"For example, the 2014 Scottish Independence referendum which had an 84% turnout and"
the 2016 EU referendum which had a 72.2% turnout.
"It can be argued that a greater use of referendums would improve democracy in the UK, as they"
directly involve the people in decision making on important issues on which the electorate has a
"right to be consulted, particularly as trust in Parliament and politicians is low."
The holding of referendums between General Elections gives the people an opportunity to have
"their say more frequently, preventing the government from becoming remote an unaccountable."
They are a check on 'elective dictatorships'.
Referendums also engage voters and increase their political awareness around important
constitutional issues.
The Scottish Independence referendum in 2014 has been praised for giving an opportunity
"to air a wide range of issues related to independence, such as the impact on the economy and the future of Trident. There was a very high turnout at 84.6%, including many 16 and 17 years olds who were able to vote."
"Other forms of direct democracy could also be used to a greater extent, including citizensʼ"
assemblies on important constitutional issues.
"In 2019, the UK Parliament commissioned the Climate Assembly UK to explore public"
opinions on achieving the goal of reaching net zero greenhouse gas emissions by 2050.
The assembly produced a detailed report with recommendations across various policy
"areas. Some of these recommendations have been reflected in government policy, such as advancing the ban on the sale of new petrol and diesel cars and increasing the capacity for"
renewable energy.
This shows how citizens assemblies can be an important way in which direct democracy
can improve democracy in the UK. It has been the only significant national citizens
assembly commissioned by Parliament and it can be argued they should be used more.
Against: Reforms To Democracy In The UK Have Gone Far Enough
"On the other hand, it can be argued that a greater use of direct democracy wouldnʼt improve"
"democracy in the UK, instead it would challenge parliamentary sovereignty and the effective working of representative democracy in the UK."
"Though referendums can be held due to public pressure and settle key constitutional issues,"
"they are also sometimes held for political party reasons and complicated by electoral politics, undermining their benefit to democracy."
"The Brexit Referendum, for example, was held partly in order to benefit the Conservative"
"Party, as pledging to hold an EU referendum in the 2015 election prevented the party losing"
many votes to UKIP.
The rejection of AV in the 2011 Alternative Vote Referendum can be seen in large part as a
"protest against the Liberal Democrats who had become unpopular since the 2010 General Election because of their U-turn on a pledge to scrap tuition fees, which had gained them a lot of support in 2010"
"Further, whilst recent referendums had relatively high turnouts, this is certainly not the norm,"
"with many referendums failing to engage voters, leading to the legitimacy of the outcome being questioned, as the result doesnʼt prove broad support/rejection across the population."
This can be seen in the 2011 Alternative Vote Referendum which had a turnout of just 42.2%
despite being a national referendum.
It can also be argued that citizens assemblies arenʼt a real basis for decision making in a
"democracy. The members arenʼt elected and their recommendations will likely be rejected by those who oppose them, who will also question the right of citizens assemblies to influence politics."
Judgement
"Overall, though referendums on key constitutional issues are an important part of UK"
"democracy, greater use of referendums isnʼt a reform that is necessarily needed, as there would likely be low turnouts for most referendums and political parties would call referendums for their own benefit."
Overall Argument
"In conclusion, reforms to democracy in the UK havenʼt gone far enough. The two most"
important failings of the UKʼs democracy are the unrepresentative nature of the FPTP electoral system and low turnouts in general elections in the 21st century.
"Extending the franchise to 16 and 17 year olds, making voting compulsory and replacing FPTP"
with a more proportional voting system would improve democracy in the UK and should be introduced.
Other Possible Essay Questions To Practice Adapting
This Plan To Answer
Evaluate the view that the UK has a democratic deficit. 30
Follow Politics Explained For More Help With Your Politics A Level
Website → https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/
Instagram → https://www.instagram.com/polexplained/
YouTube  →  https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCQ1FvoFVL4fGJkx6dup3O-w
Twitter → https://twitter.com/Pol_Explain
