Evaluate The Argument That First Past
The Post Is The Most Effective Electoral System Currently In Use In The United Kingdom. (30) Politics Explained Essay Plan
Topic       2. Electoral Systems
Structure    Three paragraphs with for/against and an overall judgement within each.
This Essay Plan Is Part Of A Package Of Essay Plans Covering The UK Politics Part Of The Politics
"A Level Course For The Edexcel Exam Board, Whilst Also Being Very Useful For The AQA Exam Board. It Can Be Purchased Here    https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/"
Keep In Mind       These are long plans as theyʼre intended to be revised from to cover the key
"content you need to know for the exam. In the exam, you would need to adapt them for the specific question you are asked and you certainly wouldnʼt need to include everything, especially not all of the examples. The judgements are also subjective and you donʼt have to agree with them!"
Introduction
Key Definitions
First Past The Post is the current electoral system used for UK Parliament elections and local
council elections in England and Wales. It is a simple plurality system.
"Other more proportional systems are in use in UK devolved bodies, including:"
The Additional Member System is used in Scottish Parliament Elections.
The Single Transferrable Vote System is used in Northern Ireland Parliament Elections.
Paragraph One      Representation and Proportionality
Arguments That FPTP Isnʼt The Most Effective Electoral System In Use In The
UK
"First Past The Post is very unrepresentative, as it is a simple plurality system that results in"
elected MPs often lacking majority support in their constituency.
The amount of votes for each party doesnʼt correlate to the number of seats won by each
party with much accuracy at all.
"FPTP results in a ‘winnerʼs bonusʼ, where the party with the most votes, even when they"
"donʼt have a majority, hugely benefits and enjoys a share of the seats in excess of the share of the vote it receives. This is because this party will often win a lot of the marginal seats between the two main parties, which usually determine the election outcome."
"In the 2024 election, the Labour Party won 63% of the seats with just 33.7% of the"
"vote, despite winning just 202 seats with 32.1% of the vote in 2019."
FPTP favours parties with geographically concentrated support and therefore massively
under-represents the majority of minor parties.
"In 2024, Reform UK received 14.3% of the vote, but just 5 seats  0.8% of the seats)."
The Single Transferable Vote System and the Additional Member System are much more
proportional and representative electoral systems than FPTP.
"STV is the most proportional, due to its multi-member constituencies and the Droop"
Formula which allocates seats in an effective way that takes into account the preferences of all voters.
Pressure group Make Votes Matter calculated that if the 2024 UK general election had
"been conducted under FPTP, Labour wouldʼve received 264 seats and reform 71 seats,"
a much closer result to their actual vote shares.
"AMS is also more proportional than FPTP, as the second ‘top upʼ vote for a party acts as a"
corrective to the first constituency vote.
"For example, in the 1999 Scottish Parliament election the Conservative Party won 0"
"constituency MPs despite getting 15.6% of the vote, but won 18 additional member seats in order to correct this, leading to them receiving 14% of seats overall."
Arguments That FPTP Is The Most Effective Electoral System In Use In The UK
"One the other hand, the high proportionality of STV and AMS can be seen as being at the"
"expense of single party government and the speed of the government selection process, though."
Both systems usually lead to coalition or minority governments.
"Further, the MP-constituency link can be seen as very strong under FPTP, leading to effective"
local representation in Parliament.
"On December 5, 2023, 22 Conservative MPs supported a Labour amendment aimed at"
"speeding up compensation for victims of the infected blood scandal, rebelling against a 3"
line conservative whip to do so.
"The amendment, which was successfully passed by a narrow majority, called for the"
establishment of a body to administer compensation within three months of passing the Victims and Prisoners Bill.
This is a good example of the strong MP-constituency link and local representation
"under FPTP, as the rebels were influenced by strong local movements and victims of the scandal in their constituency."
"For example, Conservative MP Caroline Nokes rebelled to represent the local"
movement for greater compensation and the number of victims affected in her
Romsey and Southampton North Constituency.
Judgement
"Overall, FPTP is certainly not the most effective electoral system in use in the UK when judged"
on representation and proportionality. It is true that the MP Constituency Link of FPTP is an
"advantage, but this is outweighed by the fact that FPTP is very unrepresentative, particularly of minor parties."
"AMS and STV, particularly the latter, are much more effective electoral systems when judged on"
representation and proportionality.
Paragraph Two     Voter Choice
Arguments That FPTP Isnʼt The Most Effective Electoral System In Use In The
UK
Voter choice is very limited under FPTP. Voters only get one vote and can therefore only vote
"for one party, preventing them from showing their political preferences more fully."
This leads to votes for the party that doesnʼt win in a constituency being effectively ‘wastedʼ
"and to many voters resorting to ‘tactical votingʼ, which is where voters select a different party to their preferred party (which has little chance of winning in their constituency) to try and prevent their least favourite party from winning in their constituency."
Pressure Group MakeVotesMatter reported that in 2024 1/5 voters intended to vote
"tactically and 58% of those who voted ended up with an MP they didnʼt vote for, the highest since WWII."
"In a more proportional system, such as STV where voters rank their preferences,"
tactical voting isnʼt a problem as voters can fully demonstrate their preferences.
Votes are also of greatly unequal value. Not only because a vote in a smaller constituency
"counts for more than it does in a larger constituency, but also due to the difference between safe and marginal seats."
"In safe seats, many voters have little hope of seeing their favoured candidate winning,"
leading to depressed turnout among certain voters. Little campaign focus by parties is
on these constituencies/voters.
"Manchester Rusholme, for example, was won by Labour in 2024 with 51.9.3% of the"
vote on a turnout of just 40%.
"In marginal seats, votes matter a lot more, leading to higher turnout. A great deal of"
campaign focus by parties is on these constituencies/voters.
"A good example of a highly important marginal seat is Thanet South, Kent, which"
has been won by the winning party at every General Election since its creation.
"Voter choice is higher in AMS, where voters get 2 votes: their first vote is like FPTP and is for a"
"constituency representative, their second vote is for a party."
This improves voters choice as it allows voters to split their ticket and support two different
"parties if theyʼd like. In particular, this can help minor parties who receive many more votes from the second party list vote."
"In the 2021 Scottish Parliament election for example, the Greens won just 1.29% of the"
"constituency votes, but 8.12% of the top-up votes and got 8 seats."
"Voter choice is the highest in STV, where voters rank candidates in order of preference, with a"
number of these candidates then being elected due to STVʼs multi-member constituencies.
Voters are therefore able to show their fully political preferences and can even choose
between candidates from the same party.
Arguments That FPTP Is The Most Effective Electoral System In Use In The UK
"Whilst FPTP may have limited voter choice, it is extremely easy to use for voters, who only have to select one candidate/party. The result is also usually known early in the morning after polling day and the government is quickly formed, with a swift and orderly transfer of power."
"In 2024, the first constituency result  Sunderland South) was announced at 23 15 on the day"
"of the election, the result was clear by the early hours of the next morning and Starmer arrived at Downing Street as the new Prime Minister at 12 40pm the day after the election."
"The simplicity and familiarity of FPTP can be seen as key factors in the public support for it, as"
"shown in the 2011 Alternative Vote  AV  referendum, in which 68% of those who voted voted"
"against changing the electoral system, on a 42% turnout."
"This rejected should be seen in part as a protest vote against the Liberal Democrats,"
though.
More complicated electoral systems such as AMS and STV in particular can confuse voters and
lead to ‘donkey votingʼ.
"For example in the 2019 local elections in Northern Ireland, In District Electoral Areas where"
"there were two candidates running from the same party, the candidate whose surname was first alphabetically was elected 85% of the time, whilst the second candidate on the ballot paper was elected only 54% of the time."
One of the key reasons why the Senedd voted in July 2024 to switch AMS to a Closed Party
List system from 2026 was that it simplified the process by only giving voters one vote for a
"party, rather than two."
Judgement
"Overall, whilst it is true that AMS and STV are more complicated than FPTP and can lead to some donkey voting, they are still far more effective than FPTP in terms of voter choice. They give voters much more opportunity to show their full political preferences."
FPTP is therefore not the most effective electoral system in use in the UK when judged on voter
choice. STV is.
Paragraph Three     Type Of Government Created
Arguments That FPTP Is The Most Effective Electoral System In Use In The UK
The key benefit of First Past The Post that is often cited is that it produces strong single-party governments that are able to pass laws effectively.
These governments have a strong mandate and are able to carry out their programme of
government and bring about effective change.
"In the 1980s, this enabled Thatcher to bring about widespread changes to the economy,"
whilst in 1997 it gave Blairʼs government the mandate to carry out extensive
constitutional reforms.
"In 2024, Starmerʼs Labour Party won a 174 seat majority with just 33.7% of the popular"
"vote, but there was limited public outrage and questioning of his mandate."
"These government are also elected very quickly, with the result usually known early in the"
morning after polling day and the government formed within 24 hours.
This contrasts with more proportional electoral systems which are more prone to causing
"minority/coalition governments, which can be seen as weak as they are more likely to lead to compromised/watered down policies and struggle to implement significant changes."
This can be seen in the breakdown of the Scottish government in April 2024. First Minister
Humza Youssaf decided to end the coalition agreements after the Greens strongly criticised the SNP for abandoning a key climate change target and pausing the prescription of
puberty blockers to new patients at Scotland's only gender services clinic for young people.
"As a result, the Greens supported a no confidence motion against Yousaf, who soon"
after resigned as party leader and First Minister.
This shows a key disadvantage of the Additional Member System  AMS ; that it routinely
leads to coalition and minority governments which are weak and vulnerable to
instability.
"STV almost always leads to coalition governments, as it is designed to do so. Whilst this can"
"be seen as a benefit in Northern Ireland as it brings rival groups together, it also leads to governments that are prone to conflict and indecision."
The Northern Ireland Assembly  Stormont) was suspended for nearly 2 years following
"the 2022 Northern Ireland Assembly elections, as the DUP refused to go into coalition with Sinn Fein in protest against the Northern Ireland Protocol."
This meant that there was no executive and business in Northern Ireland was run by
Westminster until the government was restored again in February 2024.
"STV doesnʼt just lead to coalitions in Northern Ireland, it also does so in Scottish Local"
"Elections, where after the 2022 elections 94% of councils had no overall control."
Arguments That FPTP Isnʼt The Most Effective Electoral System In Use In The
UK
"On the other hand, recently FPTP has led to some weak governments that havenʼt had"
majorities. In particular the 2010 Lib Dem-Conservative coalition and the Confidence and Supply Agreement between the Conservatives and the DUP following the 2017 election.
"Further, even though FPTP often leads to strong governments, this can be seen as a"
drawback as these governments donʼt have majority support from the population that could grant legitimacy to this strength.
"Coalitions also shouldnʼt necessarily be seen as negative. Scottish governments, for example,"
"have often been coalitions/minority governments, but they have been stable and able to pass significant changes."
"Compromise can be seen as an advantage, as it leads to more considered, representative"
policies.
Judgement
"Overall, FPTP certainly has some benefits over STV and AMS in relation to the type of government it creates. It usually creates strong governments that can implements significant changes, which can certainly be seen as important."
"This advantage shouldnʼt be overstated, however, as the strong governments under FPTP"
almost always lack majority support and can be seen as ‘elective dictatorshipsʼ.
"In terms of the type of government created, FPTP can therefore be seen as the most effective"
"electoral system currently in use in the UK, though AMS is a close second."
Overall Argument
"Overall, FPTP is not the most effective electoral system currently in use in the UK. It does have"
"some benefits, in particular that it leads to strong governments, however these benefits are greatly outweighed by the fact it is highly unrepresentative and has limited voter choice."
Both STV and AMS are more effective electoral systems. AMS in particular is arguably the most
"effective electoral system currently in use in the UK as it strikes an effective balance between being relatively proportional and offering significant voter choice, whilst not being too confusing for voters and still leading to stable and effective governments."
Other Possible Essay Questions To Practice Adapting
This Plan To Answer
Evaluate the view that FPTP is the most effective electoral system for general elections in the UK.   30
Follow Politics Explained For More Help With Your Politics A Level
Website → https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/
Instagram → https://www.instagram.com/polexplained/
YouTube  →  https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCQ1FvoFVL4fGJkx6dup3O-w
Twitter → https://twitter.com/Pol_Explain
