Evaluate The View That Proportional
Electoral Systems Have Fundamentally Affected The Political Process In The UK. (30) Politics Explained Essay Plan
Topic       3. Electoral Systems
Structure    Three paragraphs with for/against and an overall judgement within each.
This Essay Plan Is Part Of A Package Of Essay Plans Covering The UK Politics Part Of The Politics
"A Level Course For The Edexcel Exam Board, Whilst Also Being Very Useful For The AQA Exam Board. It Can Be Purchased Here    https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/"
Keep In Mind       These are long plans as theyʼre intended to be revised from to cover the key
"content you need to know for the exam. In the exam, you would need to adapt them for the specific question you are asked and you certainly wouldnʼt need to include everything, especially not all of the examples. The judgements are also subjective and you donʼt have to agree with them!"
Introduction
Key Definitions
First Past The Post is the current electoral system used for UK Parliament elections and local
council elections in England and Wales. It is a simple plurality system.
Proportional representation describes electoral systems in which the distribution of seats
corresponds closely with the proportion of the total votes cast for each party.
The Additional Member System is used in Scottish Parliament Elections and elections to the
Greater London Assembly.
The Single Transferrable Vote System is used in Northern Ireland Parliament Elections.
Paragraph One      Party Representation and Proportionality
Arguments That Proportional Systems Have Not Affected Political Processes In
The UK
"On the one hand, it can be argued that proportional representation PR has not fundamentally"
"affected political processes in the UK as it has not had a major impact on party representation or the party system in devolved bodies, which closely correspond to party representation in Westminster."
"PR aims to disperse power in the legislatures and represent all votersʼ views, however despite"
"votes for minor parties not being “wastedˮ like under First Past The Post  FPTP , this has not lead to a larger number of parties being represented in comparison to Westminster."
"Over the past two decades, one party has been able to dominate politics and government in"
"the devolved legislatures of both Wales  Labour) and Scotland (the SNP . As a result, it can be argued that PR hasnʼt created a multi-party system that significantly differs from Westminsterʼs plurality system under First Past The Post   FPTP  ."
"AMS is used in elections to the Scottish parliament and before 2024, it was also used"
"for the Welsh Assembly. AMS is more proportional than FPTP, as the second ‘top upʼ"
vote for a party acts as a corrective to the first constituency vote.
"The Scottish Parliament has 6 parties represented, with the SNP controlling 49% of"
seats. The Welsh Assembly has just 4 parties represented with Labour controlling
"56% of seats, and Labour has been the largest party in all 6 Senedd elections."
"By contrast, Westminster has 14 parties represented, with Labour controlling 62% of"
"seats. This suggests that proportional systems have had a very limited impact on political processes in the UK, as they havenʼt resulted in minor parties being given greater representation and power in comparison to FPTP, which is often cited as one of the core benefits of PR."
Arguments That Proportional Systems Have Affected Political Processes In The
UK
"One the other hand, it can be argued that proportional systems have had a big impact on"
"political processes in the UK, as the high proportionality of STV and AMS have created far more proportional election results in Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland and had a significant impact on party representation as a result."
"First Past The Post is very unrepresentative, as it is a simple plurality system where the"
"candidate with the largest number of votes in a constituency is elected as MP, even if they donʼt win a majority of the votes cast. In the 2024 election, this resulted in a majority of MPs being elected without over 50% of the vote in their constituency."
"On a national level, this means that a party can win a significant majority of seats in"
Parliament (and therefore form a government with a big majority) without having majority support from the electorate. This is a key reason why FPTP is a very unproportional system.
"In the 2024 Westminster election for example, The Labour Party won 63% of the seats"
"with just 33.7% of the vote, despite winning just 202 seats with 32.1% of the vote in 2019."
"Crucially, it also means that most minor parties (those without geographically"
"concentrated support) are greatly underrepresented, as they need major support within"
"a constituency to win a seat, even if they are supported by millions of voters across the"
country.
"For example, in the 2024 election Reform UK received 14.3% of the vote across the"
"country, but just 5 seats  0.8% of the seats)."
"It can be argued that PR has a major impact on political processes in the UK, as it is much"
more proportional and representative than FPTP which has allowed for the more effective representation of minor parties even when they donʼt have geographically concentrated support.
No votes are “wastedˮ under PR and the results are more representative of all voters in
"a constituency, not just those who voted for the winning party."
"STV is the most proportional, due to its multi-member constituencies and the Droop"
Formula which allocates seats in a highly proportional way that takes into account the full preferences of all voters.
"In the 2022 Northern Ireland Assembly Election, Sinn Fein was the largest party"
winning 28% of seats on 29% of the vote.
"Unlike FPTP this very close correlation was also reflected for minor parties,"
demonstrating how PR created a very different result compared to FPTP.
"For example, the Ulster Unionist Party won 10% of the seats with 11.2% of the"
vote.
"Similarly, under AMS in the 1999 Scottish Parliament election, the Conservative Party"
"won 18 seats all of which were from the second party list vote, resulting in them receiving 14% of seats from 15.6% of the vote. If the election had been conducted under FPTP, they would have won 0 seats, which is the number of constituency MPs they  received."
Judgement
"Overall, PR has clearly fundamentally affected political processes in the UK when judged on representation and proportionality."
It is true that there has been party dominance in the devolved assemblies in the same way there
"has been in Westminster, but this is far outweighed by the fact that FPTP greatly underrepresents minor parties without geographically concentrated support. These parties are far better represented under PR in Scotland, Wales and especially in Northern Ireland."
Paragraph Two     Voter Choice
Arguments That Proportional Systems Have Affected Political Processes In The
UK
Another important argument that proportional electoral systems have fundamentally affected
political processes in the UK is that they offer voters far greater choice than under FPTP. This allows voters to fully demonstrate their political preferences and results in less disillusionment with politics.
"There is very limited voter choice under FPTP, as voters only get one vote and vote for their"
"local MP rather than the overall party. This leads to votes for parties that donʼt win in a constituency being effectively ‘wastedʼ and to many voters resorting to ‘tactical votingʼ, which is where voters select a different party to their preferred party (which has little chance of winning in their constituency) to try and prevent their least favourite party from winning."
Pressure Group MakeVotesMatter reported that in 2024 1/5 voters intended to vote tactically
"and 58% of those who voted ended up with an MP they didnʼt vote for, the highest since WWII."
"This contrast with the more proportional systems used in the devolved bodies, such as STV"
"where voters rank their preferences and can choose between representatives from the same party, as well as in AMS where votes are able to split their ticket by voting for two different parties. This means that in Northern Ireland and Scotland, no votes are “wastedˮ and tactical voting isnʼt a problem as voters can fully demonstrate their preferences."
"As a result, there is less of a feeling in Northern Ireland and Scotland that the voting system"
is unfair and undermines the legitimacy of the government like there is in the UK where many voters and commentators have expressed dissatisfaction with the fact that Labour won a big majority with a limited vote share.
"This demonstrates how PR has had a major impact on political processes in the UK, not only"
"in elections themselves, but also on the legitimacy of the government as a result."
Arguments That Proportional Systems Have Not Affected Political Processes In
The UK
"Whilst proportional systems may lead to greater voter choice than under FPTP in England, it can"
"be argued that this hasnʼt fundamentally affected political processes in the UK, as it hasnʼt"
driven increased turnout and therefore hasnʼt better engaged voters in politics.
Turnout in elections to both Westminster and the devolved assemblies is low despite
devolved bodies having more proportional electoral systems.
"In the 2024 Westminster election turnout was just 59%, whilst the 2021 Scottish"
Parliament election and 2021 Senedd election had turnouts of just 63% and 46%
"respectively, despite being conducted under AMS."
An important reason for this is that complicated proportional electoral systems such as AMS
"and STV in particular can confuse voters, which acts as a barrier to increased participation and lead to ‘donkey votingʼ. STV is long and complex, as multiple MLAʼs are elected to each constituency, and it requires voters to rank candidates in order of preference."
"As a result, in the 2022 Northern Ireland Assembly Elections, there were 11,000 spoilt ballots"
which represented 1.3% of all votes cast.
"Overall, voter choice is therefore limited under both FPTP and under PR systems used in the"
"devolved bodies. Even though it is for different reasons in each, this suggests that proportional systems havenʼt had a major impact on political processes in the UK as voter choice is limited in both."
Judgement
"Overall, whilst it is true that AMS and STV have not significantly boosted turnout, and can lead"
"to some donkey voting, they still offer far more voter choice than FPTP and therefore should be"
seen as having had a significant impact on political processes in the UK.
"They give voters much more opportunity to show their full political preferences, whilst FPTP"
leads to many voters not being able to vote for they party they really support and resorting to tactical voting as a result.
"This doesnʼt only impact the process of elections in the UK, it also impacts whether voters"
"see the electoral system as a reason why the government is illegitimate, which is the case for the UK government, but not for the devolved governments."
Paragraph Three     Type Of Government Created
Arguments That Proportional Systems Have Not Affected Political Processes In
The UK
Perhaps the most compelling argument that proportional electoral systems have not
fundamentally affected political processes in the UK is the type of governments they have created.
One of First Past The Postʼs key benefits is that it usually produces strong single-party
majoritarian governments. These governments have a strong mandate and are able to carry out their programme of government and bring about effective change.
This is due to the “winnersʼ bonusˮ where the party with the most votes hugely benefits and
"enjoys a significant majority of the seats in Parliament, even when they donʼt receive a"
majority of votes.
"In the 1980s, this enabled Thatcher to bring about widespread changes to the economy,"
whilst in 1997 it gave Blairʼs government the mandate to carry out extensive
constitutional reforms.
"In 2024, Starmerʼs Labour Party won a 174 seat majority with just 33.7% of the popular"
"vote, but there was limited public outrage and questioning of his mandate."
"It can be argued that PR hasnʼt had a major impact on political processes in the UK, as the"
Governments produced by PR in the devolved assemblies function much like those in
Westminster.
"Under AMS in Scotland and Wales, the governments have been generally stable and able to"
deliver major reforms.
In Scotland the SNP have dominated Government since 2007 and were 1 seat short of an
absolute majority in 2021. Scottish Governments have tended to last the full 5 year term and have been able to take radical action.
"For example, in 2022 the Scottish Government raised the higher rate of income tax so it"
was 2% higher than the rest of the UK.
This shows that even when seats are allocated more proportionally and no party holds an
"absolute majority, Governments are stable and able to deliver radical change in the same"
way as in Westminster.
Arguments That Proportional Systems Have Affected Political Processes In The
UK
"On the other hand, it can be argued that PR has significantly affected political processes in the"
"UK, as proportional systems in the devolved bodies have produced more minority and coalition governments which function differently to majoritarian Westminster governments in a number of ways."
FPTP is a plurality-majority system producing Governmentʼs with large majorities even if they
"only win a plurality of votes. By contrast, PR allocates seats proportionally, and as a result it is unlikely for any party to win an absolute majority of seats."
"Rather than being able to form a government alone, this often forces the largest party to"
"form a coalition government and get support from another party, or to form a minority government and rely on the support of other parties to pass budgets and legislation."
"This has a major impact on political processes in the devolved bodies, as these"
governments tend to be less stable and more prone to conflict. This is also more likely to lead to compromised/watered down policies and governments struggling to implement
significant changes.
This can be seen in the breakdown of the Scottish government in April 2024. First Minister
Humza Yousaf decided to end the coalition agreements after the Greens strongly criticised the SNP for abandoning a key climate change target and pausing the prescription of puberty blockers to new patients at Scotland's only gender services clinic for young people.
"As a result, the Greens supported a no confidence motion against Yousaf, who soon after"
resigned as party leader and First Minister.
This shows a key disadvantage of the Additional Member System  AMS ; that it routinely
leads to coalition and minority governments which are vulnerable to instability and often
fail to implement key policy changes due to disagreement between parties.
"Similarly, in Northern Ireland STV creates coalition governments between the DUP and Sinn"
"Fein, which agree on very little. As a result, these governments are very prone to conflict and indecision."
"For example, Stormont was suspended for nearly 2 years following the 2022 Northern"
"Ireland Assembly elections, as the DUP refused to go into coalition with Sinn Fein in protest"
against the Northern Ireland Protocol.
Another way PR influences political processes in the UK is that it leads to a form of politics that
"relies on greater cooperation between parties and compromise across party lines, which is a stark contrast with Westminster when governments can almost always rely on a large majority to force through legislation."
Scottish governments often work across party lines and rely on the support of many parties
"to pass legislation. For example the 2025 26 Scottish Budget passed with the support of 4 other parties, and the Finance Secretary worked with the Greens, Lib Dems and Alba during its formulation."
Judgement
"Overall, even though both FPTP and PR create strong governments that can implement"
"significant changes, this similarity shouldnʼt be overstated as the minority and coalition"
governments that PR creates do function differently in a number of ways the to majority
governments in Westminster
"Bringing rival parties together results in much more compromise when legislating, but also"
less stable governments that break up between elections more often.
Overall Argument
"Overall, even though there are similarities between politics in Westminster and the devolved"
"bodies, proportional electoral systems have fundamentally affected political processes in the UK in a number of ways."
"Firstly, they result in far more voter choice and more proportional election results than under"
"FPTP, which is not only a major impact in itself, it also results in devolved governments"
having greater legitimacy than governments in Westminster
"Secondly, PR creates far more minority/coalition governments which are far less stable than"
governments in Westminster and also result in a form of politics more based around
compromise.
Other Possible Essay Questions To Practice Adapting
This Plan To Answer
Evaluate the view that the government would function radically differently if the Westminster
electoral system were replaced. 30
Evaluate the view that the various electoral systems in use in the UK make significant
differences to party representation and voter choice. 30
Evaluate the view that the disadvantages of the proportional electoral systems far outweigh any
of their advantages. 30
Evaluate the view that various electoral systems used in the UK make significant differences to
voter choice.  30
Follow Politics Explained For More Help With Your Politics A Level
Website → https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/
Instagram → https://www.instagram.com/polexplained/
YouTube  →  https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCQ1FvoFVL4fGJkx6dup3O-w
Twitter → https://twitter.com/Pol_Explain
