Evaluate The Argument That
Leadership is the Most Important Factor Determining the Success/Failure of Political Parties in the UK. (30) Politics Explained Essay Plan
Topic      2. Political Parties
Structure    Three paragraphs with for/against and an overall judgement within each
This Essay Plan Is Part Of A Package Of Essay Plans Covering The UK Politics Part Of The Politics
"A Level Course For The Edexcel Exam Board, Whilst Also Being Very Useful For The AQA Exam Board. It Can Be Purchased Here    https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/"
Keep In Mind       These are long plans as theyʼre intended to be revised from to cover the key
"content you need to know for the exam. In the exam, you would need to adapt them for the specific question you are asked and you certainly wouldnʼt need to include everything, especially not all of the examples. The judgements are also subjective and you donʼt have to agree with them!"
Paragraph One      Leadership vs The Electoral System
Arguments That Leadership Is The Most Important Factor Determining the
Success/Failure of Parties
"Party leaders are highly important to the success of political parties, particularly since the rise"
of TV and social media and the consequent increased presidentialisation of UK politics.
Leaders are able to provide clear direction and leadership to their party to ensure theyʼre
"providing a united, coherent and persuasive vision to the public."
Charismatic leaders also have the potential to reach beyond a partyʼs core voters and
increase their vote share.
"Boris Johnson in the 2019 election is a key example of this, as his personal popularity and"
"difference from the traditional image of the Conservative Party allowed the Conservatives to win the votes of many former Labour voters in the ‘Red Wallʼ, who had never voted Tory before."
Popular and charismatic leaders can be particularly important for minor parties who struggle to
gain political prominence and voter attention in the context of two-party dominance.
Nigel Farage is a key example of this. He is extremely popular with certain sections of the
"public that felt he was different from ‘typical politiciansʼ, which enabled UKIP to get a great deal of media coverage and to ultimately win 3.9 million votes in the 2015 General election."
"When he became party leader of Reform UK during the 2024 election campaign, their"
"support increased from around 10% in the polls to 14% by election day, establishing them as the clear 3rd party in terms of vote share."
"Similarly, poor and unpopular leaders can have a detrimental impact on the popularity of a"
political party by deterring potential voters.
"Jeremy Corbyn in 2019 is a good example of this, with his personal unpopularity being a key"
"reason why many voters didnʼt vote for the Labour Party, which had its worst election result since 1935."
"In 2024, leadership was an important factor in Labourʼs victory. Rishi Sunak was one of the"
"least popular party leaders fighting an election in history, with a net favourability of  51% with the public. He was tarnished by his involvement in Partygate and viewed by the public as out of touch and smug."
"During the campaign, his popularity dropped even further after he made the highly"
"unpopular decision to leave an event commemorating D Day early to attend an ITV interview, leaving Cameron to deputise for him."
Arguments That The Electoral System Is The Most Important Factor
Determining the Success/Failure of Parties
The electoral system in use is highly important in determining the success/failure of political
parties.
"In UK Parliament elections, where First Past the Post is used, parties with concentrated"
geographical support are able to benefit whilst smaller parties with some support across the country are greatly underrepresented.
"The FPTP electoral system therefore benefits Labour, the Conservatives, the SNP, the DUP"
"and Sinn Fein but greatly harms the prospects of other minor parties such as UKIP/The Brexit Party, the Liberal Democrats and the Green Party."
Farageʼs leadership and popularity may have been a major factor in UKIP getting 3.9 million
"votes in the 2015 election, however this only translated into 1 seat due to FPTP. Similarly in 2024, Reform received 14% of the vote but just 5 seats."
"In elections to devolved bodies, more proportional electoral systems allow smaller parties to"
have more success.
"The Scottish Greens, for example, currently have seven MSPs in the Scottish Parliament and"
have formed a coalition government with the SNP.
Counterpoint:
Whilst the electoral system is without doubt key to the electoral success of parties and
"being able to get into government, minor parties can have success and influence even when theyʼre underrepresented, through influencing the policies of the two main parties."
"Farage and UKIP/Brexit Party, for example, achieved their main goal of a hard Brexit being"
"implemented, despite having very little success in UK Parliament elections."
Judgement
Both leadership and the electoral system are without doubt important factors in the success/failure of political parties.
"If success is framed purely in electoral terms, then the electoral system is a more important"
"factor as it greatly limits the success of minor parties, even if they have effective leaders."
"A more useful understanding of party success/failure, however, also encompasses their"
"ability to influence the policies of major parties and the government, which party leaders have a lot of power over, even minor parties such as UKIP/Brexit Party."
"Overall, therefore, the electoral system is important, but leadership is the most important factor"
in the success/failure of political parties.
Paragraph Two     Leadership vs The Media
Arguments That The Media Is The Most Important Factor Determining the
Success/Failure of Parties
How favourability the media presents a political party can be an important factor in their success.
The media is seen by many as playing a key role in shaping the political views and electoral
"behaviour of voters, especially newspapers and political commentators on social media, which present an opinionated, biased view unlike the majority of TV and the radio, which is"
obligated to be politically neutral.
"A significant majority of the press is right-leaning and supports the Conservative Party, which"
"can be seen as an important factor in the political dominance of the Conservative Party from 2010 2024, winning four elections."
Many who supported The Labour Party under Corbyn believe the party was presented
"extremely unfairly by the media when Corbyn was in power, which damaged Labour's chances of winning the 2017 and 2019 elections."
"Tony Blair's ability to court traditionally Conservative Party supporting newspapers, including"
"The Sun, in the 1997 election is seen by many as an important factor in Labour's landslide victory in that election."
"Blair was able to portray himself very effectively in the media, in part due to New Labourʼs"
‘spinʼ.
The media can also play an important role by breaking key political scandals and events which
"can shape the public's views of parties, such as when Partygate broke in early 2022."
The Partygate scandal is a key reason why the Conservative Party had their worst ever
election result in 2024.
Arguments That Leadership Is A More Important Factor Determining the
Success/Failure of Parties
"Especially since the rise of TV and social media, a great deal of the focus of political media is"
"on party leaders, who represent their parties, especially in TV debates at election times and in"
key interviews.
"Party leaders are often the only politicians members of the public know, due to being"
"focused on in the media, and therefore play a key role in how the media influences the success/failure of political parties."
"In the run up to the 2010 election, The Liberal Democrats enjoyed a boost in the polls"
"following the first TV debate, in which Nick Clegg performed very well."
A series of disastrous local radio interviews were important in exposing the failure of Liz
Trussʼ economic policies and showing her unpopularity with the public. This played a part in
the declining popularity of the Conservative Party and her subsequent resignation.
Judgement
"Though less so than the electoral system, the media certainly plays an important role in the"
success/failure of political parties and has been important in facilitating the success of the Conservative Party over the past decade.
"Leadership is a more important factor in the success/failure of political parties, however, not"
"just due to how leaders are able to provide vision to their parties, but also because party leaders are crucial to how parties are presented in the media."
Paragraph Three
Competence
Leadership vs Policy and Perceived
Arguments That Policy and Perceived Competence Is The Most Important
Factor Determining the Success/Failure of Parties
The range of policies parties present to the electorate is a key factor in their success.
Successful parties are able to capture the public mood and develop attractive policies that gain them support from significant sections of the population.
"The significant support received by Reform UK in the 2024 election, for example, reflects"
"the fact that a significant portion of the public was unhappy with the increasing migration statistics of successive years, despite the Conservatives promising otherwise."
The rise in support for the SNP in the 2010s could be seen in large part as a consequence
of significant parts of the Scottish publicʼs support for independence and general centre-left attitudes.
Policy that is too radical can also play an important role in contributing to the failure of political
"parties, as they are unable to appeal to a large enough group of voters."
"In the 2019 election, for example, the Labour Party's very left wing manifesto and huge"
"spending commitments, as well as their commitment to a second referendum, were arguably important factors in their electoral failure and the subsequent resignation of Jeremy   Corbyn."
How competent a political party is when in government is also an important factor in their
"success. Voters reward parties who deliver on their manifesto policies and manage the economy and government effectively, whilst punishing those who don't."
A key example of this is the dramatic drop in support for the Lib Dems after they
participated in a coalition government with the Conservatives. They were punished severely by the electorate for failing to keep their promise to not increase university tuition fees and for their association with the Conservative Partyʼs harsh programme of austerity.
"By contrast, Labour won the 2001 and 2005 elections in part as a consequence of"
continued economic growth and effective public service provision when in power.
The incompetence of the Conservative government since 2019 was without doubt the most
"important factor in Labourʼs landslide victory in the 2024 election. The public viewed the Conservatives as incompetent, self-serving and untrustworthy due to a large number of scandals, which led to the partyʼs vote share dropping from 43.6% in 2019 to 23.7% in 2024."
YouGovʼs polling just before the election found that the majority of Labour voters did so to
"get the Tories out or because they felt that the country needed a change, rather than because they  supported Labourʼs  platform."
Arguments That Leadership Is A More Important Factor Determining the
Success/Failure of Parties
Party leaders are crucial to determining the policies of parties and communicating a clear vision
to the public. They can decide which policies to focus on and therefore which policies are
known by the public and discussed in the media.
"In the 2019 election, for example, Boris Johnson was important in shifting the Conservative"
Party in a hard Brexit direction and focusing the election on ‘Getting Brexit Doneʼ. This was important to their success.
Party leaders are crucial to whether political parties are viewed as competent or not.
"The disastrous mini-budget introduced by the Conservative Party in September 2022, for"
"example, which resulted in a massive drop in the polls for the Conservative Party due to their image of incompetence, was largely driven through by party leader Liz Truss."
Judgement
Party policy and competence are certainly crucial factors in the success/failure of political parties.
Party leaders play a central role in determining party policy and influencing how competent a
"party is perceived to be, though. Therefore, leadership is a more important factor and is the most important factor determining the success/failure of political parties."
Overall Argument
"Overall, leadership is the most important factor determining the success/failure of political"
parties. Party leaders are highly important in providing vision to their party and influencing how
"they are perceived by the public, including through how theyʼre perceived by the media."
Though the electoral system is an important factor and does limit the electoral success of minor
"parties, party leaders can enable minor parties to have success despite this through how they"
can gain media attention and influence the policies of the two main parties and therefore the
government.
Other Possible Essay Questions To Practice Adapting
This Plan To Answer
Evaluate the view that media support is the most important factor determining the
success/failure of political parties in the UK.  30
Evaluate the view that policies and manifestos are the most important factor determining the
success/failure of political parties in the UK.  30
Follow Politics Explained For More Help With Your Politics A Level
Website → https://www.politicsexplained.co.uk/
Instagram → https://www.instagram.com/polexplained/
YouTube   →   https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCQ1FvoFVL4fGJkx6dup3O-w
Twitter → https://twitter.com/Pol_Explain
